<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-13T20:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is There Any Room For The Not-Passionate Developer ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-26T06:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Passionate-Programmer-Remarkable-Development-Pragmatic-ebook/dp/B00AYQNR5U/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470025727&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+passionate+programmer"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-07-26-is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/passionate-programmer.jpg" title="The cover of The Passionate Programmer book" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Rework-Jason-Fried/dp/0307463745/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1469597091&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=rework">Rework</a>, <a href="https://basecamp.com/">Basecamp</a> guys David Heinemeier Hansson and Jason Fried advise to <a href="https://signalvnoise.com/posts/902-fire-the-workaholics">&ldquo;Fire the workaholics&rdquo;</a>, while in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Zero-One-Notes-Startups-Future/dp/0804139296/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1469801854&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=zero+to+one">Zero to One</a> Peter Thiel argues that great working conditions (as described within Google for example) result from 10x technological advantages, not the other way round.</p>

<p>Back in 1983, Bill Gates said :</p>

<blockquote><p>You have to think it’s a fun industry. You’ve got to go home at night and open your
mail and find computer magazines or else you’re not going to be on the same
wavelength as the people [at Microsoft].</p></blockquote>

<p>Where do we stand now ? Do you need to live and breath programming to remain a good developer ?</p>

<h2>What about the 40h per week rule ?</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-07-26-is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/productivity.jpg" title="A graph of the productivity when working overtime" ></p>

<p>Studies have repeatedly demonstrated that 40h per week is the most productive work load, but in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Outliers-Story-Success-Malcolm-Gladwell/dp/0316017930">Outliers, the Story of Success</a> Malcolm Gladwell explains that getting fast to the 10000 hours of practice is a required road to success. As my Aïkido professor says, the more you practice, the better you get &hellip;</p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1469801992&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=soft+skills+the+software+developer%27s+life+manual">Soft Skills: The software developer&rsquo;s life manual</a> John Somnez also makes the point for hard work, that while he long believed that smart work would be enough, it&rsquo;s only when he put more in that he managed to drastically change his career.</p>

<p>During an <a href="http://calacanis.com/2008/03/07/how-to-save-money-running-a-startup-17-really-good-tips/">argument</a>, DHH argued in favor of work life balance whereas Jason Calacanis said that working in a startup had to be an all-in activity. In the end, they agreed that what matters is passion.</p>

<p>From my own experience, whenever I work on something I am passionate about :</p>

<ul>
<li>I am more productive</li>
<li>I feel energized rather than dulled by the work</li>
</ul>


<p>When I look around me, all the great developers I know are passionate and putting in more than 40 hours per week in programming. I also noticed that passion and efforts have always been pretty good indicators of future skills.</p>

<p>But then, how do passionate people manage to remain productive when working more than 40 hours per week ?</p>

<h2>What about the under the shower idea ?</h2>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Thinking-Learning-Refactor-Programmers/dp/1934356050">Pragmatic Thinking and Learning: Refactor Your Wetware (Pragmatic Programmers)</a> (which is a great book BTW), Andy Hunt explains that our R-mode works in the background, and needs time away from the task at hand to come up with &ldquo;out of the box&rdquo; creative solutions.</p>

<p>XP argues for a <a href="http://www.sustainablepace.net/what-is-sustainable-pace">sustainable pace</a>, but at the same time, Uncle Bob says that we should put in 60 hours (40 for employer, and 20 for yourself) of work per week to become and remain &lsquo;professionals&rsquo; (I guess that&rsquo;s from <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Clean-Coder-Conduct-Professional-Programmers/dp/0137081073/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470026034&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=the+clean+code">The Clean Coder</a> if I remember correctly).</p>

<p>On my side, 6 to 8 solid hours of pair-programming on the same subject is the most I can do before becoming a <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?NetNegativeProducingProgrammer">Net Negative Producing Programmer</a>. But I can do more programming per day if I work on a side project at the same time though !</p>

<p>I guess that&rsquo;s how passionate people do it, they have different topics outside of their main work :</p>

<ul>
<li>they read books about programming</li>
<li>they have their own <a href="http://www.sideprojectbook.com/">side projects</a></li>
<li>they read articles about programming</li>
<li>they might maintain a programming blog</li>
<li>they might attend, organize or speak at meetup</li>
</ul>


<p>Most of the time, this does not make for more work, but rather for more learning. If I&rsquo;ve noticed that all the great programmers around me are passionate and strive to improve at their craft, I&rsquo;ve also noticed that overworked workaholics usually aren&rsquo;t very productive.</p>

<h2>Special challenges for mums and dads</h2>

<p>I think that Bill Gates 1983 statement still holds. If you are not passionate about programming, you&rsquo;ll have a hard time remaining and succeeding as a programmer in the long run.</p>

<p>The great thing about all this passion is that we can experience an energized work environment, always bubbling with change and novelty. On the flip side, keeping up with all is not always easy.</p>

<p>As we developers gain more experience, we tend to loose patience with everything that just feels as a pain in the ass, and will want :</p>

<ul>
<li>Powerful languages and technologies</li>
<li>An efficient working environment</li>
<li>Smart colleagues</li>
</ul>


<p>Unfortunately, that might also be the moment in your life when you become a parent, and you&rsquo;ll want  a stable income to sustain your family and some time to spend with your kids.</p>

<p>That is when things get tricky. Neither can you jump ship for the next cool and risky startup where you&rsquo;ll do great things, nor can you find enough time moonlighting to improve your skills &hellip; To add pain to injury, even with 10 years of experience in various languages and technologies, most companies won&rsquo;t look at your resume unless it contains good keywords &hellip; It looks like the developer&rsquo;s version of  <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Innovators-Dilemma-Revolutionary-Change-Business/dp/0062060244/ref=sr_1_sc_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470024448&amp;sr=8-1-spell&amp;keywords=the+innovator%27s+dilemns">The Innovator&rsquo;s Dilemna</a> !</p>

<p>Lack of passion and parenthood might partially explain why people stop being developers after a while. I can quickly think of 2 bad consequences of this :</p>

<ul>
<li>We tend to reinvent the wheel quite a lot (I&rsquo;m looking at you, .js frameworks &hellip;)</li>
<li>We might be meta ignoring (ignoring that we ignore) people skills that could make us all more efficient</li>
</ul>


<p><em><a href="http://www.inside.com.tw/2016/08/05/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer">Chinese translation</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Size Of Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/the-size-of-code/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-08T04:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/the-size-of-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The CFO&rsquo;s debt is visible in his balance sheet. The CTO&rsquo;s technical debt is invisible. What about making it visible ?</p>

<p>Developers have an intuitive sense of the technical debt in some parts of the system. But few have an accurate estimation of its full extent. Even the size of a code base is difficult to grasp. In the same way, the size of the code is just a number. But the fact are there : between 10 000 and 10 000 000 lines of code, the rules aren&rsquo;t the same, but it&rsquo;s only invisible data on hard drives &hellip;</p>

<h2>Showing It</h2>

<p>If we had a device or a trick to show to non-developers the size of the source code, people might start to feel the embarrassment of working in a bloated code base. Unfortunately, for the moment, the only ideas I had are somehow unrealistic, albeit funny !</p>

<h3>First Idea : Printouts</h3>

<p>Suppose we printed all the source code every Monday, and then keep it around for everyone to feel its size. We could leave it in the middle of the place, or in the CTO&rsquo;s office, so that he&rsquo;d actually be hindered by the space loss. The larger the code, the bigger the troubles.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s possible to print 50 lines on a sheet of paper, that&rsquo;s 100 on both sides.
That&rsquo;s 50 000 in a pack of 500 pages. And eventually, 200 000 in this kind of standard case :</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-08-the-size-of-code/paper-case.jpg" title="A 2000 sheets paper case" ></p>

<p>Keeping these printouts in sync with the real cost would make the thing even more <del>painful</del> realistic. Imagine all the printings costs, and moving around cases of paper every day &hellip; ;)</p>

<h3>Second Idea : Inflatable Device</h3>

<p>What about an inflatable device linked to <a href="http://www.sonarqube.org/">SonarQube</a> (or any other code metrics tracking system) ? It could grow as new code is written. We could make it as large as we want : 1m<sup>3</sup> for every 10K lines of Code, making the whole office a difficult place to walk around. Try to figure out how to work with this thing in the office :</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jimmykuehnle.com/artblog/inflatable-bigger-than-the-studio/"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-08-the-size-of-code/Large_Inflatable_Art.jpg" title="Large Inflatable Art (Jimmy Kuehnle)" ></a></p>

<h3>Third Idea : Sand</h3>

<p>For maximum pain, let&rsquo;s use real sand instead of an inflatable device ! Imagine the mess with some sand lying around in the office. If the only way to clean up the mess was to clean up the code, surely everyone would take the issue seriously !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-08-the-size-of-code/sand-pile.jpg" title="A sand pile on the pavement" ></p>

<h2>Final Word</h2>

<p>Obviously, these are jokes, but I guess there&rsquo;s a real need there. If we managed to make non developers feel the size and cost of the code base, it would be easier to agree on priorities.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Legacy Code Coverall Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/legacy-code-coverall-day/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-06T04:16:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/legacy-code-coverall-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-06-legacy-code-coverall-day/miners.jpg" title="Miners going to work in Coveralls" ></p>

<p>Some days, coding feels like speleology or mining &hellip; Dealing with weird and undocumented old logic can even some time be <a href="https://www.quora.com/How-do-you-keep-your-sanity-while-working-on-a-Super-Dirty-Rotten-Spaghetti-codebase">damaging to the mind</a> ! I think we should go to work wearing the adequate protection !</p>

<p>OK, maybe we cannot start to go to work wearing a coverall everyday, but let&rsquo;s say very 21st of June is now legacy code day, the day when every developer maintaining legacy code comes to work dressed like that !</p>

<p>Obviously, that&rsquo;s a joke, but it could attract the attention of other non-coding people on the state of <em>their</em> codebase and amount of <em>their</em> technical debt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anti Ugly-Code Glasses]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/anti-ugly-code-glasses/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-02T04:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/anti-ugly-code-glasses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think I found a way to fix the dirty code problem once and for all &hellip;</p>

<p>In <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy">The Hitchhiker&rsquo;s Guide to the Galaxy</a> Zaphod Beeblebrox has some anti panic glasses. They feature some special danger detection mechanism that turns them opaque black to save their bearer from panicking.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-02-anti-ugly-code-glasses/zaphod.jpg" title="Zaphod Beeblebrox" ></p>

<p><em>(It turns out that Zaphod has two heads &hellip;)</em></p>

<p>In 2016, it&rsquo;s shocking that some many hours are lost by poor developers reading ugly code.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s build anti ugly-code glasses ! We&rsquo;d just need an IDE or editor plugin, connect it to <a href="http://www.sonarqube.org/">Sonar</a> in order to get the quality of the current file, and if too bad, shut the glasses black !</p>

<p>Finally the killer feature for augmented reality glasses !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How To Keep Up With Software Technologies]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-30T04:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I started to program professionally 15 years ago, a lot of things have changes. A lot of technologies appeared and became mainstream while others fell out of fashion.</p>

<p>As software developers, it is really challenging to stay fit and productive in new technologies. I cannot obviously say that I am an expert in all new technologies, but I can say that I can get up to speed in a pretty short time in nearly all.</p>

<p>If there is a single reason for that I strongly believe it is because &ldquo;I studied my classics&rdquo; !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/outdated.jpg" title="An outdated computed covered in spider webs" ></p>

<h2>How does it work</h2>

<p>At the same time I started to program all day long for my living, I also started to read a lot of programming books on my spare time. This allowed me to learn at night and practice at day, setting everything in my brain.</p>

<p>This might come as a surprise, but I never read a lot of books about the technologies I was using. I&rsquo;d rather study fundamental programming books. These contain a lot of transportable knowledge, unlike in most books about a particular technology.</p>

<p>I believe this is a pretty good use of time since it made me a better programmer and also greatly reduced the time I need to master most new technologies. I can now easily relate them to some more general concept I learned before.</p>

<p>For example, I never read a book about UI. By the time I had to do some UI programming, I had absolutely no issue getting up to speed on the topic. I had already seen quite some UI code examples in other books, I knew that most UI frameworks are built from a set of Object Oriented patterns. Coming from a different perspective, I was even able to suggest improvements to the code that UI experts had not thought of.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s not to say that I never read books about a particular technology, sometimes, that&rsquo;s just what you need to start something new. But when I do, I usually find them quite easy to read and digest. And I tend to skip things I intuitively understand and use them as cookbooks containing recipes for particular problems rather than end to end walk-through.</p>

<h2>My books</h2>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Programmer-Journeyman-Master/dp/020161622X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666382&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+pragmatic+programmer">The Pragmatic Programmer: From Journeyman to Master</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Programmer-Journeyman-Master/dp/020161622X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666382&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+pragmatic+programmer"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/the-pragmatic-programmer.jpg" title="Cover of the pragmatic programmer book" ></a></p>

<p>As a young programmer this book made me understand that my job was not only about writing code, but about building maintainable systems. It provided me with tools to do so, 10 years later, I can still remember &ldquo;The power of plain text&rdquo;. This is also the book that made me have a first look into Ruby :).</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666776&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=refactoring+improving+the+design+of+existing+code">Refactoring: Improving the Design of Existing Code</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666776&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=refactoring+improving+the+design+of+existing+code"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/refactoring.jpg" title="Cover of the refactoring book" ></a></p>

<p>Here is the theory behind all automated IDE refactorings. Reading this book had a profound influence on my coding style. The examples made me understand the difference between readable and unreadable code &hellip; It&rsquo;s also the foundation for any kind of incremental design and architecture. That&rsquo;s the book that got me started with TDD.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666833&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design+eric+evans">Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666833&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design+eric+evans"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/ddd.jpg" title="Cover of the DDD book" ></a></p>

<p>This book teaches good object oriented programming. Some say it is tough to read, but it&rsquo;s definitely worth doing so. Among other things, it explains how to use functional programming concept in your object oriented project, by separating Value Objects and Entities for example.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Programming-Language-Brian-W-Kernighan/dp/0131103628/ref=pd_sim_14_2?ie=UTF8&amp;dpID=41qX6YdIJ7L&amp;dpSrc=sims&amp;preST=_AC_UL160_SR122%2C160_&amp;refRID=035C81Y95A0A1C6K25F6">The C Programming Language</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Programming-Language-Brian-W-Kernighan/dp/0131103628/ref=pd_sim_14_2?ie=UTF8&amp;dpID=41qX6YdIJ7L&amp;dpSrc=sims&amp;preST=_AC_UL160_SR122%2C160_&amp;refRID=035C81Y95A0A1C6K25F6"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/c.jpg" title="Cover of the C book" ></a></p>

<p>With around 250 pages, it&rsquo;s pretty difficult to find a programming book with a greater value/page ratio. This one will teach you all there is to learn about C, and help you understand everything that was built on top of C (and that&rsquo;s quite a lot &hellip;)</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Structure-Interpretation-Computer-Programs-Engineering/dp/0262510871/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666981&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=sicp">Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Structure-Interpretation-Computer-Programs-Engineering/dp/0262510871/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666981&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=sicp"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/sicp.jpg" title="Cover of the SICP book" ></a></p>

<p>Compared to C, Lisp is at the other side of the language spectrum. Learning C and Lisp gives the ability to put nearly anything in contrast to these 2 languages. Lisp is dynamic, functional and meta. It can be morphed into nearly anything and SICP teaches how to do so. There&rsquo;s a Lisp practice that is invaluable to any programmer : use your language to express your problem as simply as possible. SICP teaches that.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Programming-Erlang-Concurrent-Pragmatic-Programmers/dp/193778553X/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464667113&amp;sr=1-2&amp;keywords=erlang+programming">Programming Erlang: Software for a Concurrent World</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Programming-Erlang-Concurrent-Pragmatic-Programmers/dp/193778553X/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464667113&amp;sr=1-2&amp;keywords=erlang+programming"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/erlang.jpg" title="Cover of the Erlang book" ></a></p>

<p>Neither the C book nor SICP deals with distribution and concurrency. That&rsquo;s what this book does. I had never programmed distributed systems before reading this book. After I read it, I learned how to code for distribution in a maintainable way. The lessons taught by Erlang are applicable in many languages.</p>

<h2>Not the best books</h2>

<p>I did not and will never read all programming books available. There might be newer books that treat the same subjects better, but these books are the ones that taught me the most about our craft. My point is that learning fundamentals and things far away from our daily technologies will teach us more.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
