<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-28T20:01:23+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Top 5 talks I attended at JavaOne 2016 (Part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/top-5-talks-i-attented-at-java-one-2016-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-28T19:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/top-5-talks-i-attented-at-java-one-2016-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With a few other colleagues, I had the chance to be sent to San Francisco last week to attend the <a href="https://www.oracle.com/javaone/index.html">JavaOne 2016</a> conferences by my <a href="http://www.murex.com">company</a>.</p>

<p><a href="/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/exhibition-hall.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/exhibition-hall-small.jpg" title="Photo of the JavaOne exhibition hall" ></a></p>

<p>Here is super short list of the conferences I attended which I found really interesting</p>

<h2>Preventing errors before they happen</h2>

<p><a href="https://ece.uwaterloo.ca/~wdietl/">Werner Dietl</a> &amp; <a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~mernst/">Michael Ernst</a></p>

<p>Since Java 6, it is possible to pass custom annotation processors to javac. Since Java 8, it is possible to add annotations to types. The guys behind the <a href="http://checkerframework.org">Checker Framework</a> used this to create custom pluggable type systems for your Java programs. These type systems enforce properties on your program, and will emit warnings or errors at compile time otherwise.</p>

<p>Here are a few example :</p>

<ul>
<li>declare <code>@Immutable MyObject myObject</code> to make sure that myObject won&rsquo;t be muted</li>
<li>declare <code>@NonNull MyObject myObject</code> to make sure that myObject is never null</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/type-systems.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/type-systems-small.jpg" title="Architecture of the type checker" ></a></p>

<p>Under the hood, the compiler behaves as if <code>@Immutable MyObject</code> and <code>MyObject</code> where completely separate types, and it knows and tracks specific ways of converting between the two. The framework provides a simple API to define your own type systems. They did a live demo showing how to quickly define things like <code>@Regex String</code>, <code>@Encrypted String</code> or <code>@Untainted String</code> (which forbids user input strings to avoid SQL injections).</p>

<p>The talk was really interesting, the framework seems lightweight and to integrate well with the typical tool stack. I definitely will give it a try the next time I have a bit of slack time.</p>

<p>Here are <a href="http://types.cs.washington.edu/checker-framework/2016-javaone/2016-09-19%20CF%20@%20JavaOne.pdf">the slides</a> and a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kb6nz85jbuQ">previous session of the presentation</a></p>

<h2>Keeping Your CI/CD Pipeline as Fast as It Needs to Be</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/abrahammarin?lang=fr">Abraham Marin-Perez</a></p>

<p>Continuous Delivery and Microservices are what you need to do, aren&rsquo;t they ? Well, when actually trying to setup a CI / CD pipeline for all your code, things quickly get complicated pretty fast ! The speaker presented how to deal with this complexity by using metrics from your VCS and build servers to draw an annotated graph of your build pipeline.</p>

<p><a href="/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/build-pipeline.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/build-pipeline-small.jpg" title="Graph of the build pipeline" ></a></p>

<ul>
<li>He used the build time to set the size of every node : the longer, the larger</li>
<li>The color for the change rate : the more often it was built the warmer the color</li>
</ul>


<p>It was then possible to determine other metrics such as :</p>

<ul>
<li>the impact time of every node : build time + build time of all the dependencies</li>
<li>the weighted impact time : impact time * change rate</li>
<li>the overall average impact time : sum of all the weighted impact times</li>
<li>the overall max impact time : max of all the impact times</li>
</ul>


<p>Using this and your SLAs it is possible to define policies for your build times such as &ldquo;the max build time should not be more than X&rdquo;. If you want to speed up your build, you can set a target build time and analyzing the graph should help you to understand what architecture changes you need to make to your system in order to meet this build time (this sounds a lot like <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">Toyota&rsquo;s Improvement Kata</a> &hellip;)</p>

<p>I loved this talk ! I found the speaker captivating, he presented novel ideas which is not always the case.</p>

<p>Here are <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/AbrahamMarinPerez/keeping-your-cicd-pipeline-as-fast-as-it-needs-to-be">the slides</a>, and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8JxoKJng_eQ">the same presentation at Devoxx UK</a>.</p>

<h2>To Be Continued</h2>

<p>I promised 5, and that&rsquo;s only 2 talks ! Stay tuned, I&rsquo;ll write about the 3 others in the coming weeks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flavors of TDD]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/flavours-of-tdd/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-20T20:54:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/flavours-of-tdd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During the years doing some coding dojos with the same circle of people, I came up with my own style of practicing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development">TDD</a>. Lately, I had the chance to do a pair programming session with someone I did not know. That made me realize that they are in fact even more ways to practice TDD than I thought.</p>

<h2>Mockist vs Classisist</h2>

<p>A lot has already been written (and discussed) about these two approaches. I myself have already <a href="/hitting-the-middle-ground-between-classicist-and-mockist-tdd/">blogged</a> about the subject, I even gave a <a href="/how-not-to-use-mocks-my-talk-at-paris-rb/">talk</a> about it. From my own point of view, I believe that the inconvenients of making mocking the default far outweights the benefits. I&rsquo;m not saying that mocks aren&rsquo;t useful from time to time, but rather that they should remain the exception.</p>

<h2>Top-Down vs Bottom-Up</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s the reason why I wrote this post. This is the main difference I found between my style and my pair&rsquo;s. Let me explain.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-20-flavours-of-tdd/topdown-vs-bottomup.jpg" title="Top-Down vs Bottom-Up" ></p>

<h3>Top-Down</h3>

<p>Doing TDD top-down means starting with high level end to end tests, implementing the minimum to make it work, refactor and repeat. A bit like BDD, the point is to focus on the expected behavior, and avoid writing useless things. The bad point is that the refactoring part can get pretty difficult. On real life code, strictly following top-down would mean writing a feature test first, passing it with a quick and dirty implementation, to then spend hours trying to refactor all that mess &hellip; good luck !</p>

<p>Here is another example, from coding dojos this time. Having had success with the top-down approach during previous dojos, we once intentionally tried to code <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life#">Conway&rsquo;s Game of Life</a> using a top-down approach. We did so by writing high level tests that were checking special patterns (gliders &hellip;). That was a nightmare ! It felt like trying to reverse engineer the rules of the game from real use cases. It did not bring us anywhere.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-20-flavours-of-tdd/glider.gif" title="Conway&rsquo;s game of life gliders" ></p>

<h3>Bottom-Up</h3>

<p>At the other side of the spectrum, you can do bottom-up TDD. This means unit testing and implementing all the small bricks you think you&rsquo;ll need to provide the expected overall feature. The idea is to avoid tunnels and to get fast feedback on what you are coding. The bad side is that you might be coding something that will end up being unnecessary. Be careful, if you find yourself spending a lot of time building up utility classes, you might be doing too much bottom-up implementation.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://codingdojo.org/cgi-bin/index.pl?KataRomanNumerals">Numerals to Romans Kata</a> is a good exercise to fail at bottom-up. Every time I did this exercise during a coding dojo, people new to it would start to come up with complicated ways to do it (often involving complex array manipulation). Compared to that, applying disciplined bottom-up TDD brings a <a href="https://github.com/FreeCodeCamp/FreeCodeCamp/wiki/Algorithm-Roman-Numeral-Converter">brutally effective solution for Numerals to Romans</a>.</p>

<h2>Mixed approach</h2>

<p>Both approaches have their pros and cons. I really believe developers who are serious about TDD should master both, and learn when to apply each. In fact, as often, the best approach lies somewhere in the middle. Here&rsquo;s my recipe :</p>

<ol>
<li>Start with a high level feature test</li>
<li>try to make it pass &hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip; (usually) fail</li>
<li>rollback or shelve your test and draft implementation</li>
<li>build a brick</li>
<li>unshelve</li>
<li>try to make it pass &hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip; and so one until the high level test finally passes.</li>
</ol>


<p>In fact, it&rsquo;s a lot like the <a href="https://mikadomethod.wordpress.com/">Mikado Method</a> for building features instead of refactoring.</p>

<h2>Practice in dojos</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s possible to intentionally practice this in coding dojos as well. Most kata should be OK, as long as the group agrees to fix it using this particular approach up front.</p>

<p>If during the dojo, you&rsquo;ve just written a test, suddenly realize that it won&rsquo;t be easy to get it passing, and that you&rsquo;ve got the elements spread out in your code, this is the time ! Comment the test, get the green bar, refactor, uncomment the test, try to make it pass, repeat &hellip; Eventually, you&rsquo;ll have all the bricks to make it easy to pass your test.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-20-flavours-of-tdd/cargo-cult.jpg" title="Cargo Cult : People thought that by building something that looks like a plane, they would be able to fly" ></p>

<p>Some might say this is not &lsquo;pure&rsquo; TDD, but that sounds like cargo cult to me ! As long as you make sure you are not building useless stuff, and that you keep the feedback loop as short as possible, you&rsquo;re on the right track.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is There Any Room For The Not-Passionate Developer ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-26T06:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Passionate-Programmer-Remarkable-Development-Pragmatic-ebook/dp/B00AYQNR5U/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470025727&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+passionate+programmer"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-07-26-is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/passionate-programmer.jpg" title="The cover of The Passionate Programmer book" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Rework-Jason-Fried/dp/0307463745/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1469597091&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=rework">Rework</a>, <a href="https://basecamp.com/">Basecamp</a> guys David Heinemeier Hansson and Jason Fried advise to <a href="https://signalvnoise.com/posts/902-fire-the-workaholics">&ldquo;Fire the workaholics&rdquo;</a>, while in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Zero-One-Notes-Startups-Future/dp/0804139296/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1469801854&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=zero+to+one">Zero to One</a> Peter Thiel argues that great working conditions (as described within Google for example) result from 10x technological advantages, not the other way round.</p>

<p>Back in 1983, Bill Gates said :</p>

<blockquote><p>You have to think it’s a fun industry. You’ve got to go home at night and open your
mail and find computer magazines or else you’re not going to be on the same
wavelength as the people [at Microsoft].</p></blockquote>

<p>Where do we stand now ? Do you need to live and breath programming to remain a good developer ?</p>

<h2>What about the 40h per week rule ?</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-07-26-is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/productivity.jpg" title="A graph of the productivity when working overtime" ></p>

<p>Studies have repeatedly demonstrated that 40h per week is the most productive work load, but in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Outliers-Story-Success-Malcolm-Gladwell/dp/0316017930">Outliers, the Story of Success</a> Malcolm Gladwell explains that getting fast to the 10000 hours of practice is a required road to success. As my Aïkido professor says, the more you practice, the better you get &hellip;</p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1469801992&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=soft+skills+the+software+developer%27s+life+manual">Soft Skills: The software developer&rsquo;s life manual</a> John Somnez also makes the point for hard work, that while he long believed that smart work would be enough, it&rsquo;s only when he put more in that he managed to drastically change his career.</p>

<p>During an <a href="http://calacanis.com/2008/03/07/how-to-save-money-running-a-startup-17-really-good-tips/">argument</a>, DHH argued in favor of work life balance whereas Jason Calacanis said that working in a startup had to be an all-in activity. In the end, they agreed that what matters is passion.</p>

<p>From my own experience, whenever I work on something I am passionate about :</p>

<ul>
<li>I am more productive</li>
<li>I feel energized rather than dulled by the work</li>
</ul>


<p>When I look around me, all the great developers I know are passionate and putting in more than 40 hours per week in programming. I also noticed that passion and efforts have always been pretty good indicators of future skills.</p>

<p>But then, how do passionate people manage to remain productive when working more than 40 hours per week ?</p>

<h2>What about the under the shower idea ?</h2>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Thinking-Learning-Refactor-Programmers/dp/1934356050">Pragmatic Thinking and Learning: Refactor Your Wetware (Pragmatic Programmers)</a> (which is a great book BTW), Andy Hunt explains that our R-mode works in the background, and needs time away from the task at hand to come up with &ldquo;out of the box&rdquo; creative solutions.</p>

<p>XP argues for a <a href="http://www.sustainablepace.net/what-is-sustainable-pace">sustainable pace</a>, but at the same time, Uncle Bob says that we should put in 60 hours (40 for employer, and 20 for yourself) of work per week to become and remain &lsquo;professionals&rsquo; (I guess that&rsquo;s from <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Clean-Coder-Conduct-Professional-Programmers/dp/0137081073/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470026034&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=the+clean+code">The Clean Coder</a> if I remember correctly).</p>

<p>On my side, 6 to 8 solid hours of pair-programming on the same subject is the most I can do before becoming a <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?NetNegativeProducingProgrammer">Net Negative Producing Programmer</a>. But I can do more programming per day if I work on a side project at the same time though !</p>

<p>I guess that&rsquo;s how passionate people do it, they have different topics outside of their main work :</p>

<ul>
<li>they read books about programming</li>
<li>they have their own <a href="http://www.sideprojectbook.com/">side projects</a></li>
<li>they read articles about programming</li>
<li>they might maintain a programming blog</li>
<li>they might attend, organize or speak at meetup</li>
</ul>


<p>Most of the time, this does not make for more work, but rather for more learning. If I&rsquo;ve noticed that all the great programmers around me are passionate and strive to improve at their craft, I&rsquo;ve also noticed that overworked workaholics usually aren&rsquo;t very productive.</p>

<h2>Special challenges for mums and dads</h2>

<p>I think that Bill Gates 1983 statement still holds. If you are not passionate about programming, you&rsquo;ll have a hard time remaining and succeeding as a programmer in the long run.</p>

<p>The great thing about all this passion is that we can experience an energized work environment, always bubbling with change and novelty. On the flip side, keeping up with all is not always easy.</p>

<p>As we developers gain more experience, we tend to loose patience with everything that just feels as a pain in the ass, and will want :</p>

<ul>
<li>Powerful languages and technologies</li>
<li>An efficient working environment</li>
<li>Smart colleagues</li>
</ul>


<p>Unfortunately, that might also be the moment in your life when you become a parent, and you&rsquo;ll want  a stable income to sustain your family and some time to spend with your kids.</p>

<p>That is when things get tricky. Neither can you jump ship for the next cool and risky startup where you&rsquo;ll do great things, nor can you find enough time moonlighting to improve your skills &hellip; To add pain to injury, even with 10 years of experience in various languages and technologies, most companies won&rsquo;t look at your resume unless it contains good keywords &hellip; It looks like the developer&rsquo;s version of  <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Innovators-Dilemma-Revolutionary-Change-Business/dp/0062060244/ref=sr_1_sc_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470024448&amp;sr=8-1-spell&amp;keywords=the+innovator%27s+dilemns">The Innovator&rsquo;s Dilemna</a> !</p>

<p>Lack of passion and parenthood might partially explain why people stop being developers after a while. I can quickly think of 2 bad consequences of this :</p>

<ul>
<li>We tend to reinvent the wheel quite a lot (I&rsquo;m looking at you, .js frameworks &hellip;)</li>
<li>We might be meta ignoring (ignoring that we ignore) people skills that could make us all more efficient</li>
</ul>


<p><em><a href="http://www.inside.com.tw/2016/08/05/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer">Chinese translation</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Size Of Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/the-size-of-code/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-08T04:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/the-size-of-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The CFO&rsquo;s debt is visible in his balance sheet. The CTO&rsquo;s technical debt is invisible. What about making it visible ?</p>

<p>Developers have an intuitive sense of the technical debt in some parts of the system. But few have an accurate estimation of its full extent. Even the size of a code base is difficult to grasp. In the same way, the size of the code is just a number. But the fact are there : between 10 000 and 10 000 000 lines of code, the rules aren&rsquo;t the same, but it&rsquo;s only invisible data on hard drives &hellip;</p>

<h2>Showing It</h2>

<p>If we had a device or a trick to show to non-developers the size of the source code, people might start to feel the embarrassment of working in a bloated code base. Unfortunately, for the moment, the only ideas I had are somehow unrealistic, albeit funny !</p>

<h3>First Idea : Printouts</h3>

<p>Suppose we printed all the source code every Monday, and then keep it around for everyone to feel its size. We could leave it in the middle of the place, or in the CTO&rsquo;s office, so that he&rsquo;d actually be hindered by the space loss. The larger the code, the bigger the troubles.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s possible to print 50 lines on a sheet of paper, that&rsquo;s 100 on both sides.
That&rsquo;s 50 000 in a pack of 500 pages. And eventually, 200 000 in this kind of standard case :</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-08-the-size-of-code/paper-case.jpg" title="A 2000 sheets paper case" ></p>

<p>Keeping these printouts in sync with the real cost would make the thing even more <del>painful</del> realistic. Imagine all the printings costs, and moving around cases of paper every day &hellip; ;)</p>

<h3>Second Idea : Inflatable Device</h3>

<p>What about an inflatable device linked to <a href="http://www.sonarqube.org/">SonarQube</a> (or any other code metrics tracking system) ? It could grow as new code is written. We could make it as large as we want : 1m<sup>3</sup> for every 10K lines of Code, making the whole office a difficult place to walk around. Try to figure out how to work with this thing in the office :</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jimmykuehnle.com/artblog/inflatable-bigger-than-the-studio/"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-08-the-size-of-code/Large_Inflatable_Art.jpg" title="Large Inflatable Art (Jimmy Kuehnle)" ></a></p>

<h3>Third Idea : Sand</h3>

<p>For maximum pain, let&rsquo;s use real sand instead of an inflatable device ! Imagine the mess with some sand lying around in the office. If the only way to clean up the mess was to clean up the code, surely everyone would take the issue seriously !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-08-the-size-of-code/sand-pile.jpg" title="A sand pile on the pavement" ></p>

<h2>Final Word</h2>

<p>Obviously, these are jokes, but I guess there&rsquo;s a real need there. If we managed to make non developers feel the size and cost of the code base, it would be easier to agree on priorities.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Legacy Code Coverall Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/legacy-code-coverall-day/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-06T04:16:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/legacy-code-coverall-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-06-legacy-code-coverall-day/miners.jpg" title="Miners going to work in Coveralls" ></p>

<p>Some days, coding feels like speleology or mining &hellip; Dealing with weird and undocumented old logic can even some time be <a href="https://www.quora.com/How-do-you-keep-your-sanity-while-working-on-a-Super-Dirty-Rotten-Spaghetti-codebase">damaging to the mind</a> ! I think we should go to work wearing the adequate protection !</p>

<p>OK, maybe we cannot start to go to work wearing a coverall everyday, but let&rsquo;s say very 21st of June is now legacy code day, the day when every developer maintaining legacy code comes to work dressed like that !</p>

<p>Obviously, that&rsquo;s a joke, but it could attract the attention of other non-coding people on the state of <em>their</em> codebase and amount of <em>their</em> technical debt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
