<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-05-03T06:12:41+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Immutable Value Objects vs Mocks : Fizz Buzz]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/immutable-value-objects-vs-mocks-fizz-buzz/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-03T19:28:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/immutable-value-objects-vs-mocks-fizz-buzz</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="/how-immutable-value-objects-fight-mocks/">previous post</a> I explained how <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/ValueObject.html">Immutable Value Objects</a> help us to avoid mocks. In this post, I&rsquo;ll illustrate this in practice with real code.</p>

<p>This is the third post on a <a href="/blog/categories/how-to-avoid-mocks-series/">series about how to avoid mocks</a>. If you haven&rsquo;t, you can start reading the full story <a href="/careless-mocking-considered-harmful/">here</a>.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2018-04-17-immutable-value-objects-vs-mocks-fizz-buzz/immutable-fizz-buzz.jpg" alt="A drawing &quot;FIZZ BUZZ&quot; rock fallen and sealed in the ground" /></p>

<h2>Fizz Buzz Example</h2>

<p>As a simple example, I&rsquo;ll go through the classic <a href="http://codingdojo.org/kata/FizzBuzz/">Fizz Buzz</a>. I&rsquo;ve implemented and tested it with and without immutable value objects. Please keep in mind that this is a toy example, where problems are obvious and easily fixed. I try to highlight at small scale the same problems that get hidden by the complexity of a large scale program.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start with a typical FizzBuzz implementation.</p>

<p>```ruby
1.upto(100) do |i|
  if (i%3 == 0 and i%5 == 0)</p>

<pre><code>STDOUT.puts("FizzBuzz\n")
</code></pre>

<p>  elsif (i%3 == 0)</p>

<pre><code>STDOUT.puts("Fizz\n")
</code></pre>

<p>  elsif (i%5 == 0)</p>

<pre><code>STDOUT.puts("Buzz\n")
</code></pre>

<p>  else</p>

<pre><code>STDOUT.puts("#{i}\n")
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Suppose you need to add some tests around the code. The most straightforward way is to mock <code>STDOUT</code> :</p>

<p>```ruby
require &lsquo;rspec&rsquo;</p>

<p>def fizzBuzz(max, out)
  1.upto(max) do |i|</p>

<pre><code>if (i%3 == 0 and i%5 == 0)
  out.puts("FizzBuzz\n")
elsif (i%3 == 0)
  out.puts("Fizz\n")
elsif (i%5 == 0)
  out.puts("Buzz\n")
else
  out.puts("#{i}\n")
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<h1>main</h1>

<p>fizzBuzz(100,STDOUT)</p>

<p>describe &lsquo;Mockist Fizz Buzz&rsquo; do</p>

<p>  it &lsquo;should print numbers, fizz and buzz&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>out = double("out")
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("1\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("2\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("Fizz\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("4\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("Buzz\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("Fizz\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("7\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("8\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("Fizz\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("Buzz\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("11\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("Fizz\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("13\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("14\n").ordered
expect(out).to receive(:puts).with("FizzBuzz\n").ordered

fizzBuzz(15, out)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>Unfortunately, there are a few problems with this code :</p>

<ul>
<li>With nested logic and complicated mock setup, both code and tests aren&rsquo;t very readable</li>
<li>They both seem to violate the single responsibility principle as well</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s depending on a mutable output. Within a larger program, something could be messing around with this output stream. That would break FizzBuzz.</li>
</ul>


<p>Let&rsquo;s now try to use as many immutable values objects as possible, and see what happens to the mocks.</p>

<p>```ruby
require &lsquo;rspec&rsquo;</p>

<h1>We extracted a function to do the fizz buzz on a single number</h1>

<p>def fizzBuzzN(i)
  if (i%3 == 0 and i%5 == 0)</p>

<pre><code>"FizzBuzz"
</code></pre>

<p>  elsif (i%3 == 0)</p>

<pre><code>"Fizz"
</code></pre>

<p>  elsif (i%5 == 0)</p>

<pre><code>"Buzz"
</code></pre>

<p>  else</p>

<pre><code>i.to_s
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<h1>We replaced the many calls to STDOUT.puts by building a single</h1>

<h1>large (and immutable) string</h1>

<p>def fizzBuzz(max)
  ((1..max).map {|i| fizzBuzzN(i)}).join(&ldquo;\n&rdquo;)
end</p>

<h1>main, with a single call to STDOUT.puts</h1>

<p>STDOUT.puts fizzBuzz(100)</p>

<p>describe &lsquo;Statist Fizz Buzz&rsquo; do</p>

<p>  it &lsquo;should print numbers not multiples of 3 or 5&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>expect(fizzBuzzN(1)).to eq("1")
expect(fizzBuzzN(2)).to eq("2")
expect(fizzBuzzN(4)).to eq("4")
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  it &lsquo;should print Fizz for multiples of 3&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>expect(fizzBuzzN(3)).to eq("Fizz")
expect(fizzBuzzN(6)).to eq("Fizz")
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  it &lsquo;should print Buzz for multiples of 3&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>expect(fizzBuzzN(5)).to eq("Buzz")
expect(fizzBuzzN(10)).to eq("Buzz")
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  it &lsquo;should print FizzBuzz for multiples of 3 and 5&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>expect(fizzBuzzN(15)).to eq("FizzBuzz")
expect(fizzBuzzN(30)).to eq("FizzBuzz")
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  it &lsquo;should print numbers, fizz and buzz&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>expect(fizzBuzz(15)).to start_with("1\n2\nFizz").and(end_with("14\nFizzBuzz"))
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>As we can see, using immutable value objects got us rid of the mocks. Obviously, this new code will not be as efficient as the original version, but most of the time, this does not matter. As a bonus though we get finer grain and more readable tests.</p>

<h3>Other testing advantages</h3>

<p>Appart from preventing mocks, Immutable Value Objects have other advantages related to testing.</p>

<ul>
<li>We can directly assert their equality, without having to dig into their guts</li>
<li>We can call methods as many times as we want, without the risk of changing anything and breaking the tests</li>
<li>Immutable Value Objects are a lot less likely to contain invalid state. This removes the need for a whole range of validity tests.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>💡 Immutable Value Objects simplify testing in many ways.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Convincing your teammates</h3>

<p>We&rsquo;ve seen that Immutable Value Objects have a ton of advantages when testing. People have found that they also have many other benefits :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/20140528113353-16837833-6-benefits-of-programming-with-immutable-objects-in-java/">6 Benefits of Programming with Immutable Objects in Java</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hackernoon.com/5-benefits-of-immutable-objects-worth-considering-for-your-next-project-f98e7e85b6ac">5 Benefits of Immutable Objects Worth Considering for Your Next Project</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Surprisingly though, it&rsquo;s difficult to persuade programmers to use more immutability. It&rsquo;s tricky to explain why returning a modified copy is simpler than just adding a setter.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Why is it so hard to persuade other developers to use immutable data structures ?</p></blockquote>

<p>I had the most success by far when encountering a bug resulting of share mutable state. When this happens, the long term benefits and safety of the immutable design wins people over. The good thing is that as you convince more people in the team, immutability will spread like a virus !</p>

<p>Outside of this situation, you might try some of the following arguments to move people :</p>

<ul>
<li>Immutable values prevent bugs caused by different parts of the system changing the same mutable state</li>
<li>They make it easier to deal with the program in smaller parts and to reason about the system in general</li>
<li>Immutable values don&rsquo;t need any synchronization and make multithreaded programming easier</li>
<li>When tempted to add a simple setter instead of keeping a class immutable, highlight the stressful debugging time to come</li>
<li>If you&rsquo;re dealing with a Design By Contract adept, explain how <a href="/almost-15-years-of-using-design-by-contract/">immutability has it built-in</a></li>
<li>Admit that mainstream languages have bad support for Immutable Value. Point to patterns like <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/immutability-with-builder-design-pattern">Data Builders</a> that work around these limitation</li>
</ul>


<h2>Next post</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m done with immutable value objects. It was a far longer post than I thought, but there was a lot to say. This was the third post in a <a href="/blog/categories/how-to-avoid-mocks-series/">series about avoiding mocks</a>. In next post, I&rsquo;ll dig into another small scale mock fighting pattern : <a href="http://www.natpryce.com/articles/000714.html">Test Data Builders</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=PhilippeBourgau&amp;loc=en_US">Stay tuned !</a> !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Immutable Value Objects fight Mocks]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-immutable-value-objects-fight-mocks/"/>
    <updated>2018-04-26T08:51:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-immutable-value-objects-fight-mocks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Excessive use of mocks makes tests very painful to maintain. If we stick painful mocks for too long, we&rsquo;ll end up abandoning unit testing. Eventually, the system will degrade into legacy. </p>

<p>There are many techniques to avoid mocks. Some of the most effective involve architecture changes. Unfortunately, there are not the most straightforward to use. Re-architecting involves people and time that you may not dispose of right now. In the following posts, I&rsquo;ll go over techniques that any developer can use in his day to day code to avoid mocks. These battle tested techniques that I&rsquo;ve used on different projects in the past. Check <a href="/careless-mocking-considered-harmful/">the previous post</a> if you&rsquo;re interested to learn how I came to use them.</p>

<p>This is the second post <a href="/blog/categories/how-to-avoid-mocks-series/">of a series about how to avoid mocks</a> in automated tests. If you haven&rsquo;t yet, I recommend you to read my <a href="/careless-mocking-considered-harmful/">first post</a> to understand the perils of mocks in more details.</p>

<p>The first mock fighting small-scale technique I&rsquo;ll go over is <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/ValueObject.html">Immutable Value Objects</a>.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2018-04-17-how-immutable-value-objects-fight-mocks/immutable-rock.jpg" alt="A drawing of a rock written &quot;Immutable Value Object&quot;" /></p>

<h2>What are Immutable Value Objects ?</h2>

<p>Behind this weird name is something very simple to understand. Immutable Value Objects :</p>

<ul>
<li>Cannot change their state after construction</li>
<li>Only depend on other Immutable Value Objects</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t change the state of the whole system in any way</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t do side effects, like inputs and outputs for example</li>
</ul>


<p>Eric Evans popularized the name in the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1523985269&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design">Domain-Driven Design Blue Book</a>. Immutable Value Objects have existed for decades in functional languages though. We say these objects are immutable (they cannot change) and pure (they cannot do side effects). Here are 2 interesting properties of Value Objects :</p>

<ul>
<li>you can call a method any number of times with no risk of changing anything to the system</li>
<li>you&rsquo;ll always get the same result every time you call the same method on the same object</li>
</ul>


<p>These by itself, can already be handy when testing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1523985269&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design"><img src="../imgs/2018-04-17-how-immutable-value-objects-fight-mocks/ddd.jpg" alt="Cover of Eric Evans's DDD book" /></a></p>

<h2>How do they prevent mocks ?</h2>

<p>That was a bit theoretical, so let&rsquo;s see how this helps to reduce mocking.</p>

<h3>Simpler &ldquo;init path&rdquo;</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take it the other way round and see how side effects can lead to mocking. Every test starts with setting the state in which to run the test. Side effects make this complicated, as many objects need to collaborate to set this state up. When this becomes too painful, people start hacking around with mocks. This in turn makes the tests more fragile :</p>

<ul>
<li>We are not testing a &ldquo;real&rdquo; situation</li>
<li>We need to keep this setup in line with the real code</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>💡 Intricate state initialization encourage people to use mocks.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Isolates parts of the system</h3>

<p>Unfortunately, that is not all the story ! Mutable state also, tricks us into using mocks. As soon as your test deals with mutable state, there is a chance that this state is changed in the &lsquo;real&rsquo; system. This means that some bugs might &lsquo;escape&rsquo; unit tests and appear in end to end tests or in production. That&rsquo;s where the mocks strike ! In order to detect this bug in a fast feedback loop, we&rsquo;re likely to add larger scope tests and use mocks to speed them up &hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Mutable state and side effects make unit tests less effective.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Reduces code with side effects</h3>

<p>But there&rsquo;s another reason why Immutable Value Objects help us to avoid mocks. As we&rsquo;ll try to use them more and more for the previous two reasons, we&rsquo;ll need to adapt our programming style. As we&rsquo;ll push more and more code in Immutable Value Objects, the &lsquo;imperative&rsquo; part will shrink. This &lsquo;imperative&rsquo; part is where side-effect happen. This is the part where mocking out IOs makes sense. To summarize, the more Immutable Value Objects we use, the more isolated the IOs are, and the less mocking we need.</p>

<p>Javascript expert Eric Elliot also wrote about the immutability and mocks <a href="https://medium.com/javascript-scene/mocking-is-a-code-smell-944a70c90a6a">here</a>.</p>

<h2>Next week</h2>

<p>This was the second post in a <a href="/blog/categories/how-to-avoid-mocks-series/">series about how to prevent mocks</a> in your automated tests. <a href="/immutable-value-objects-vs-mocks-fizz-buzz/">Next post</a> will be an example of using immutable value objects on the <a href="http://codingdojo.org/kata/FizzBuzz/">FizzBuzz kata</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Careless Mocking Considered Harmful]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/careless-mocking-considered-harmful/"/>
    <updated>2018-04-19T13:13:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/careless-mocking-considered-harmful</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>💡 Mock hell : when excessive use of test mocks makes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_refactoring">refactoring</a> extremely slow or difficult.</p></blockquote>

<p>A few years ago, I managed to get a side project out of mock hell. Since then, I&rsquo;ve been using what I learned to avoid mocks in all the projects I&rsquo;ve worked on. This is the start of a series of posts about my mock-avoiding techniques.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2018-04-10-careless-mocking-considered-harmful/mocks-dont-rock.jpg" alt="A tag &quot;Mocks don't rock !&quot;" /></p>

<h2>Escape from Mock Hell</h2>

<p>Between 2010 and 2014, I was working on a side project I called <a href="https://github.com/philou/mes-courses">http://mes-courses.fr</a>. Which actually means &ldquo;my house shopping&rdquo; in English. I wanted people to be able to do their house shopping in 5 minutes, by using a better UI for online groceries. I was using Ruby, and I had just read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Growing-Object-Oriented-Software-Guided-Tests/dp/0321503627/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1523422024&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=growing+object-oriented+software+guided+by+tests">Growing Object Oriented Software Guided by Tests</a>. I got a bit too excited with mocking, and was using it way too much.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d been practicing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development">Test Driven Development</a> for more than 5 years and I was expecting great results with a language like Ruby. After a few months though, I could feel that something was not going as well as it should. The test initialization code was getting longer and longer, as it included a lot of mock setup. This made the tests more complex and less readable. It also made them unreliable, as it was not rare for all my unit tests to pass while the system was not working. I was taking the habit of running my end to end test more and more often. I was also losing a lot of time maintaining the mock setup code in line with the real classes. Mocks also tricked me into the bad practice of keeping a 1 to 1 mapping between code and test files. That again increased my maintenance burden when moving code from one file to another.</p>

<p>It reached a point where I could not take it anymore. All these problems were pointing at mocks, so I tried to remove them from a test file. Here are the techniques I ended up using to remove them mocks : </p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/ValueObject.html">Value Objects</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.natpryce.com/articles/000714.html">Test Data Builders</a></li>
<li><a href="https://relishapp.com/rspec/rspec-expectations/docs/custom-matchers">Test Matchers</a></li>
<li><a href="http://alistair.cockburn.us/Hexagonal+architecture">Hexagonal architecture</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.martinfowler.com/articles/mocksArentStubs.html">In-memory fakes</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wincent.com/wiki/Proxy_(test_double">Proxy doubles</a>)</li>
</ul>


<p>The end result was beyond my hopes, as my problems almost magically disappeared. The code got simpler, I became a lot more confident about my unit tests, and they got easier to maintain. As an illustration, here is an excerpts from the diff of a rails controller test file which went through this mock diet.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/philou/mes-courses/commit/2c9fce17f9b59d0b3828f309015c07b17cceddf4?diff=split"><img src="../imgs/2018-04-10-careless-mocking-considered-harmful/diff.jpg" alt="A screen capture of a Github diff showing a test file going on a mock diet" /></a></p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s the long term risk ?</h2>

<p>Basically, excessive mocking arms the maintainability of the tests. Here is what would have happened if I&rsquo;d done nothing. Tests would have become so painful to maintain that I would have started to ignore or delete them. As coverage would decrease, more and more code would become untested. That&rsquo;s exactly Michael Feathers' definition of Legacy Code :</p>

<blockquote><p>Legacy Code is code without tests. <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Working-Effectively-Legacy-Michael-Feathers/dp/0131177052/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1523422039&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=legacy+code">Michael Feathers</a></p></blockquote>

<p>To summarize, excessive use of mocks leads to legacy code ! As most of us have learned the hard way, the further a system drifts into legacy, the lower the productivity.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Excessive use of mocks leads to legacy code</p></blockquote>

<h2>Next posts</h2>

<p>Others already spoke about the dangers of mocks :</p>

<ul>
<li>Uncle Bob through <a href="http://blog.cleancoder.com/uncle-bob/2014/05/10/WhenToMock.html">his blog</a></li>
<li>DHH in the <a href="https://www.google.fr/search?q=is+TDD+dead&amp;safe=active&amp;tbm=vid">&ldquo;Is TDD Dead&rdquo; series</a></li>
</ul>


<p>In <a href="/blog/categories/how-to-avoid-mocks-series/">this series of posts</a>, I&rsquo;ll go through the details of the different techniques I used to remove mocks. Here is my plan :</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="/careless-mocking-considered-harmful/">Careless Mocking considered Harmful</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-immutable-value-objects-fight-mocks/">How Immutable Value Objects fight mocks</a></li>
<li><a href="/immutable-value-objects-vs-mocks-fizz-buzz/">Immutable Value Objects vs Mocks : Fizz Buzz</a></li>
<li>How to use Test Data Builders to avoid mocks and keep your tests clear</li>
<li>One last small scale technique to avoid mocks : Test Matchers</li>
<li>Large scale techniques to avoid mocks</li>
<li>Mocking in special contexts like legacy and dynamically or statically typed languages</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10 things to know that will make you great at refactoring legacy code]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/10-things-to-know-that-will-make-you-great-at-refactoring-legacy-code/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-28T06:35:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/10-things-to-know-that-will-make-you-great-at-refactoring-legacy-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We write tons of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legacy_code">legacy code</a> everyday. Experienced developers understand that legacy code is not something special. Legacy code is our daily bread and butter.</p>

<p>Should we abandon all hope as we enter legacy code ? Would that be professional ? In the end, code is only a bunch of bytes, somewhere on a drive. We are the software professionals. We need to deal with that.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-07-28-10-things-to-know-that-will-make-you-great-at-refactoring-legacy-code/keep-calm-and-take-the-power-back-4.jpg" alt="Keep Calm and Take The Power Back" /></p>

<h2>1. Master non legacy refactoring first</h2>

<p>Please calm down before this &ldquo;Bring &lsquo;em out&rdquo; energy goes to your head.</p>

<p>I did not say that refactoring legacy code is easy. Legacy code can bite &hellip; bad. I&rsquo;ve been in teams which literally spent nights fixing a bad refactoring gone to production &hellip;</p>

<p>Before you can refactor legacy code, you need to be good at refactoring new code. We all learned to swim in the shallow pool, it&rsquo;s the same with refactoring. Mastering green code refactoring will help you when tackling legacy code.</p>

<p>First, you&rsquo;ll know the ideal you&rsquo;d like to get to. Knowing how productive a fast feedback loop is will motivate you to keep on refactoring.</p>

<p>Second, you&rsquo;ll have a better idea of the baby steps to take you through a tricky refactoring.</p>

<p>If you are not yet at ease with greenfield refactoring, have a look at <a href="/how-to-start-learning-the-tao-of-incremental-code-refactoring-today/">my previous post</a>.</p>

<h2>2. Understand that refactoring legacy code is different</h2>

<p>The next thing to remember is that refactoring legacy code is different. Let&rsquo;s assume <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/4174867/what-is-the-definition-of-legacy-code">Michael Feather&rsquo;s definition of legacy code</a> : &ldquo;Code without tests&rdquo;. Getting rid of legacy code means adding automated tests.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, trying to force push unit tests in legacy code usually results in a mess. It introduces lot&rsquo;s of artificial mocks in a meaningless design. It also creates brittle and unmaintainable tests. More harm than good. This might be an intermediate step, but it is usually not the quickest way to master your legacy code beast.</p>

<p>Here are alternatives I prefer.</p>

<h2>3. Divide and conquer</h2>

<p>This is the most straightforward way to deal with legacy code. It&rsquo;s an iterative process to repeat until you get things under control. Here is how it goes :</p>

<p>(1) Rely on the tests you have, (2) to refactor enough, (3) to test sub-parts in isolation. (4) Repeat until you are happy with the speed of the feedback loop.</p>

<p>Depending on the initial state of your tests, this might take more or less time. Your first tests might even be manual. This is the bulldozer of refactoring. Very effective, but slow.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-07-28-10-things-to-know-that-will-make-you-great-at-refactoring-legacy-code/bulldozer.jpg" alt="Bulldozer" /></p>

<h2>4. Pair or mob program</h2>

<blockquote><p>Given enough eyeballs, all bugs are shallow.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linus%27s_Law">Linus&rsquo;s Law</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Changing legacy code is a lot easier when you team up. First, it creates a motivating &ldquo;we&rsquo;re all in this together&rdquo; mindset. Second, it guards us against silly mistakes.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mob_programming">Mob programming</a>, might seem very expensive, so let me explain why it is not. Suppose you want to introduce some tests in a tricky section of code.</p>

<p>With mob programming, all the team gathers for half a day to work on this change. Together, they find and avoid most of the pitfalls. They commit a high quality change, which creates only one bug down the road.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s see the alternative.</p>

<p>Using solo programming, a poor programmer tries to tackle the change all by himself. He spends a few days to understand and double check all the traps he can think of. Finally, he commits his change, which results in many bugs later on. Every time a bug pops up, it interrupts someone to fix it ASAP.</p>

<p>The savings in interruptions are greater than up front cost of mob or pair programming. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/p_pvslS4gEI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>5. Seams</h2>

<blockquote><p>A software seam is <em>a place where you can alter behavior in your program without editing in that place.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://wiki.c2.com/?SoftwareSeam">Michael Feathers</a></p></blockquote>

<p>This is one of the many interesting things I learned from Michael&rsquo;s book about legacy code.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0131177052/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0131177052&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=edaadc6370c2c8c9e943348d9fbdafb9"><img src="../imgs/2017-07-28-10-things-to-know-that-will-make-you-great-at-refactoring-legacy-code/legacy-code.jpg" alt="Cover of Working Effectively with Legacy Code" /></a></p>

<p>Object polymorphism is only one kind of seam. Depending on your language, many other types of seams can be available. </p>

<ul>
<li>Type seam for generic languages</li>
<li>Static link seam for static libraries</li>
<li>Dynamic link seam for dynamic libraries</li>
<li>&hellip;</li>
</ul>


<p>Finding seams in your program is something opportunistic. Keep in mind though that testing through seams is not the end goal. It is only a step to bootstrap the test-refactor loop and start your refactoring journey.</p>

<h2>6. Mikado Method</h2>

<p>How do you get to your end then ? How to you refactor only what&rsquo;s useful for your features ? How do you do large refactorings in baby steps ?</p>

<p>Over time, I found that the mikado method is a good answer to all these issues. The goal of the <a href="https://mikadomethod.wordpress.com/">Mikado Method</a> is to build a graph of dependent refactoring. It can then use it to perform all these refactorings one by one. Here is the mikado method by the book.</p>

<p>Before anything else, you&rsquo;ll need a large sheet of paper to draw the graph. Then repeat the following :</p>

<ol>
<li>try to do the change you want</li>
<li>If it builds and the tests pass, great, commit and you&rsquo;re done</li>
<li>Otherwise, add a node for the change you wanted to do in your mikado graph</li>
<li>Write down the compilation and test errors </li>
<li>Revert your change</li>
<li>Recurse from 1 for every compilation or test error</li>
<li>Draw a dependency arrow from the nodes of errors to the node of your initial change</li>
</ol>


<p>Once you built the full graph, tackle the refactorings from the leaves. As leafs have no dependencies, it should be easy to do and commit them.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-07-28-10-things-to-know-that-will-make-you-great-at-refactoring-legacy-code/mikado.jpg" alt="A Sample Mikado Graph" /></p>

<p>When I first read about the mikado method, it seemed very simple and powerful. Things got more complex when I tried to apply it. For example, the fact that some changes don&rsquo;t compile hide future test failures. That means that very often, the &ldquo;Build the graph&rdquo; and &ldquo;Walk the graph&rdquo; phases overlap. In real life, the graph evolves and changes over time. </p>

<p>My advice about the Mikado Method is not to take it to the letter. It&rsquo;s a fantastic communication tool. It helps not to get lost and to avoid a refactoring tunnel. It also helps to tackle refactoring as a team.</p>

<p>It is not a strict algorithm though. Build and tests are not the only way to build the graph. Very often, a bit of thinking and expert knowledge are the best tools at hand.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1617291218/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1617291218&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=f7405cd74335b3cbb8b263f1a5c37c1d"><img src="../imgs/2017-07-28-10-things-to-know-that-will-make-you-great-at-refactoring-legacy-code/mikado-book.jpg" alt="Cover of The Mikado Method book" /></a></p>

<h2>7. Bubble Context</h2>

<p>Refactoring needs to be opportunistic. Sometimes there are shortcuts in your refactoring path.</p>

<p>If you have access to a domain expert, the <a href="http://dddcommunity.org/library/evans_2011_2/2">Bubble Context</a> will cut the amount of refactoring to do. It&rsquo;s also an occasion to get rid of all the features that are in your software but that are not required anymore. </p>

<p>The Bubble Context originated from the <a href="http://dddcommunity.org/library/evans_2011_2/">DDD community</a>, as a way to grow a domain in an existing code base. It goes like that :</p>

<ol>
<li>Find a domain expert</li>
<li>(Re)write clean code for a very tiny sub domain</li>
<li>Protect it from the outside with an <a href="https://softwareengineering.stackexchange.com/questions/184464/what-is-an-anti-corruption-layer-and-how-is-it-used">anticorruption layer</a></li>
<li>Grow it little by little</li>
</ol>


<p>I have friends who are fans of the bubble context. It is super effective provided you have a domain expert. It is a method of choice in complex domain software.</p>

<h2>8. Strangler</h2>

<p>Bubble Context works great when refactoring domain specific code, what about the rest ? I had good results with the <a href="https://www.martinfowler.com/bliki/StranglerApplication.html">Strangler pattern</a>.</p>

<p>For example, we had to refactor a rather complex parser for an internal DSL. It was very difficult to incrementally change the old parser, so we started to build a new one aside. It would try to parse, but delegate to the old one when it failed. Little by little, the new parser was handling more and more of the grammar. When it supported all the inputs, we removed the old one.</p>

<p>The strangler is particularly well suited for refactoring technical components. They have more stable interfaces and can be very difficult to change incrementally.</p>

<h2>9. Parallel Run</h2>

<p>This is more of a trick than a long term strategy. The idea is to use the initial (legacy) version of the code as a reference for your refactoring. Run both and check that they are doing the same thing.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-07-28-10-things-to-know-that-will-make-you-great-at-refactoring-legacy-code/railroad.jpg" alt="Parallel Railroads" /></p>

<p>Here are some variations around this idea.</p>

<p>If the code you want to refactor is side effect free, it should be easy to duplicate it before refactoring. This enables running both to check that they compute the same thing.</p>

<p>Put this in a unit test to bootstrap a test-refactor loop. You can also run both in production and log any difference. You&rsquo;ll need access to production logs &hellip; Devops teams have a refactoring advantage !</p>

<p>Here is another use of your logs. If the code writes a lot of logs, we can use them as a reference. Capture the logs of the old version, and unit test that the refactored version prints the same logs out. That&rsquo;s an unmaintainable test, but good enough to bootstrap the test-refactor loop.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/emilybache/GildedRose-Refactoring-Kata">Gilded Rose kata</a> is a good exercise to practice this last technique.</p>

<h2>10. Dead code is better off dead</h2>

<p>You don&rsquo;t need to refactor dead code ! Again, access to production logs is a great advantage for refactoring.</p>

<p>Add logs to learn how the real code runs. If it&rsquo;s never called, then delete it. If it&rsquo;s only called with some set of values, simplify it.</p>

<h2>No silver bullet</h2>

<p>That was a whirlwind tour of the legacy code refactoring techniques I know. It&rsquo;s no promise that refactoring will become easy or fast. I hope it is a good starting point to set up and walk a refactoring plan.</p>

<p>This was the last post of a series of 3 about how to learn refactoring techniques. If you didn&rsquo;t already, check part 1 <a href="/7-reasons-why-learning-refactoring-techniques-will-improve-your-life-as-a-software-engineer/">7 Reasons Why Learning Refactoring Techniques Will Improve Your Life as a Software Engineer</a> and part 2 <a href="/how-to-start-learning-the-tao-of-incremental-code-refactoring-today/">How to Start Learning the Tao of Incremental Code Refactoring Today</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to start learning the tao of incremental code refactoring today]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-start-learning-the-tao-of-incremental-code-refactoring-today/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-21T08:05:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-start-learning-the-tao-of-incremental-code-refactoring-today</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="/7-reasons-why-learning-refactoring-techniques-will-improve-your-life-as-a-software-engineer/">last post</a>, I explained why incremental refactoring techniques will make you both more productive and relaxed.</p>

<p>As anything worth its salt, the path to full mastery is long and requires dedication. The good news is that you&rsquo;ll start to feel the benefits long before you are a master.</p>

<h2>Dedicated Practice</h2>

<p>The quickest thing that will get you up to speed is dedicated practice. Take some time to do some exercices outside of any &lsquo;production&rsquo; code.</p>

<h3>TDD Coding Katas</h3>

<p>The most famous practice to learn TDD also works very well to learn refactoring. That shouldn&rsquo;t be a surprise as incremental refactoring is an integral part of TDD.</p>

<p>There are many ways to do your first coding kata. You could find a coding dojo near you (ask <a href="https://www.meetup.com/">meetup.com</a>). Or you could find motivated colleagues to start one at your company &hellip; I wrote in more details about how to attend a coding dojo in <a href="/from-apprentice-to-master-how-to-learn-tdd-test-driven-development/">this post</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/919811803X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=919811803X&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=340ea938a5e4f00178676804ac6c2278"><img src="../imgs/2017-07-21-how-to-start-learning-the-tao-of-incremental-code-refactoring-today/coding-dojo.jpg" alt="Emily Bache's Coding Dojo book cover" /></a></p>

<p>You can also practice katas on your own. My friend <a href="https://twitter.com/tpierrain">Thomas Pierrain</a> rehearses the same katas to discover deeper insights.</p>

<h3>Refactoring Golf</h3>

<p>The goal of incremental refactoring is to keep the code production ready all the time. Smaller commits is one happy consequence of that.</p>

<p>You can stretch your refactoring muscles by doing coding katas and keeping the code compiling all the time. You&rsquo;ll need to master your IDE and its automated refactoring. Most of all, it will shift your attention from the goal to the path !</p>

<p>I learned at <a href="https://www.spaconference.org/spa2017/">SPA conference</a> that we call this &lsquo;Refactoring golf&rsquo;. The name comes from Golf contests, <a href="http://wiki.c2.com/?PerlGolf">popular in the Perl community</a>. Their goal is to write the shortest program possible to do a specific goal. The goal of a Refactoring Golf is to go from code A to code B in the fewest transformations possible.</p>

<p>They are a few <a href="https://github.com/search?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;q=refactoring+golf&amp;type=">refactoring golf repos on Github</a>, I tried one and found it fun ! Give it a try too !</p>

<h2>Study some theory</h2>

<p>Real mastery does not come by practice alone. Studying theory alongside practice yields deeper insights. Theory enables to put your practice into perspective and to find ways to improve it. It saves you from getting stuck in bad habits. It also saves you from having to rediscover everything by yourself.</p>

<h3>Develop your design taste</h3>

<p>In <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/taste.html">Taste for Makers</a> Paul Graham explains why taste for is fundamental to programming. Taste is what allows you to judge if code is nice or bad in a few seconds. Taste is subjective, intuitive and fast, unlike rules which are objective but slower. Expert designers use taste to pinpoint issues and good points in code on the spot.</p>

<p>Within the fast TDD &ndash; Refactoring loop, taste is the tool of choice to drive the design. Guess what : we can all improve our design taste !</p>

<p><a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/code-smells/">Code smells</a> are the first things to read about to improve your design taste. Once you know them well enough, it will be possible to spot things that might need refactoring as you code.</p>

<p>Spotting problems is nice, but finding solutions is better ! <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_design_pattern">Design Patterns</a> are just that &hellip; There has been a lot of controversy around Design Patterns. If overusing them leads to bloated code, using them to fix strong smells makes a lot of sense. There is even a book about the subject :</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321213351/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0321213351&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=d79d093008fb9e77f75ea2089d6cbdae"><img src="../imgs/2017-07-21-how-to-start-learning-the-tao-of-incremental-code-refactoring-today/refactoring-to-patterns.jpg" alt="Joshua Kerievsky's Refactoring To Patterns book cover" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, there&rsquo;s a third and most common way to improve our design taste. It&rsquo;s to read code ! The more code we read, the better our brain becomes at picking small clues about what nice and what is not. It&rsquo;s important to read clean code but also bad code. To read code in different languages. Code built on different frameworks. </p>

<p>So, read code at work, read code in books, read code in open source libraries, good code, legacy code &hellip;</p>

<h3>Learn your refactorings</h3>

<p>As with most topics in programming there is a reference book about refactoring. It&rsquo;s Martin Fowlers&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0201485672/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0201485672&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=73fc09a5a451402a7036509ae62e8c66">Refactoring, improving the design of existing code</a>. Everything is in there, smells, unit testing and a repository of refactoring walkthroughs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0201485672/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0201485672&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=73fc09a5a451402a7036509ae62e8c66"><img src="../imgs/2017-07-21-how-to-start-learning-the-tao-of-incremental-code-refactoring-today/refactoring.jpg" alt="Martin Fowler's refactoring book cover" /></a></p>

<p>The book is said to be a difficult read, but the content is worth gold. If you have the grit, give it a try ! At the end, you should understand how your IDE does automated refactoring. You should also be able to perform all the refactorings that your IDE does not provide by hand ! This will enlarge your refactoring toolbox, and help you to drive larger refactorings from A to B.</p>

<h2>Develop a refactoring attitude</h2>

<p>Practice makes perfect. Whatever our refactoring skill, there is something to learn by practicing more.</p>

<h3>Make it a challenge</h3>

<p>As you are coding, whenever you find a refactoring to do to your code, make it a challenge to perform it in baby steps. Try to keep the code compiling and the tests green as much as possible.</p>

<p>When things go wrong, revert instead of pushing forward. Stop and think, try to find a different path.</p>

<p>If you are pairing, challenge your pair to find a safer track.</p>

<p>This might delay you a bit at first, but you&rsquo;ll also be able to submit many times per day. You&rsquo;ll see that your refactoring muscles will grow fast. You should see clear progress in only 1 or 2 weeks.</p>

<h3>Team up against long refactorings</h3>

<p>If your team prioritizes a user story that will need some re-design, try to agree on a refactoring plan. The idea is to find a coarse grain path that will allow you to commit and deliver many times. This plan might also help you to share the work on the story.</p>

<p>Having to question and explain your assumptions will speed up your learning. </p>

<h2>Legacy code</h2>

<p>Refactoring is most useful with bad legacy code. Unfortunately, it also where it is the most difficult. Next week&rsquo;s blog post will be about what we can do to learn how to refactor legacy code.</p>

<p>That was my second post in this mini-series about refactoring. First one was <a href="/7-reasons-why-learning-refactoring-techniques-will-improve-your-life-as-a-software-engineer/">7 Reasons Why Learning Refactoring Techniques Will Improve Your Life as a Software Engineer</a>. The third and last is <a href="/10-things-to-know-that-will-make-you-great-at-refactoring-legacy-code/">10 things to know that will make you great at refactoring legacy code</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
