<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-06-28T22:54:30+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to get your team to do code reviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-get-your-team-to-do-code-reviews/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-19T09:18:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-get-your-team-to-do-code-reviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As software developers, we very <del>always</del> often get to work in code bases that are not perfect. In this situation we have 3 choices : leave, grumble, or make some changes ! Team wide code reviews are a recognized way to increase the quality of the code.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, installing code reviews as part of the daily work habits of a team can be very challenging. When I joined my team 3 years ago, no one was doing any kind of code reviews. With a small push here and there, I managed to get the team to adhere to a strict 4 eyes principle (full story <a href="/from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/">here</a>).</p>

<p>Here are a few strategies that I have either used or seen that should get your team mates to do code reviews.</p>

<h2>Overall principle</h2>

<p>Even if you are at the bottom of the org chart, you have far more influence than you would first think. My favorite way of bringing change is to demonstrate a valuable practice :</p>

<ul>
<li>First, you need to be trustworthy</li>
<li>Then, do the practice you want to introduce</li>
<li>Make sure it is seen as valuable</li>
<li>Be ready to forgo the credits of the introduction of the practice</li>
<li>Keep on until people start to copy what you are doing</li>
</ul>


<p>As <a href="http://quoteinvestigator.com/2010/12/21/doing-good-selfless/">someone famous</a> said</p>

<blockquote><p>A man may do an immense deal of good, if he does not care who gets the credit</p></blockquote>

<p>I won&rsquo;t go in the details about how to be trustworthy, which could be a post of its own. Basically, putting our customers interests first, speaking the truth and avoiding to appear dogmatic can get us a long way already. <a href="https://www.amazon.fr/dp/B0050JLC9Y/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1">The Clean Coder</a> is an excellent read on the subject.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.fr/dp/B0050JLC9Y/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><img src="../imgs/2017-04-19-how-to-get-your-team-to-do-code-reviews/clean-coder.jpg" alt="Front cover of the Clean Coder book" /></a></p>

<h2>Strategies</h2>

<h3>If you have retrospectives in place</h3>

<p>In this case, you already have a place and time dedicated to discussing changes to your working agreements. Expressing your concerns about code quality (or another problem related to code reviews) and suggesting code reviews as a way to fix that problem might get a quick team buy-in.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t manage to get a definitive buy-in, try to get the team to &lsquo;beta-test&rsquo; code reviews for a while. If the experiment demonstrates value, it will convert into a full fledged working agreement.</p>

<h3>If you practice collective code ownership</h3>

<p>Unfortunately, if you don&rsquo;t have retrospectives in place, or if you did not manage to get your team to discuss code reviews in retrospectives, yo&rsquo;ll need to find another way to introduce them.</p>

<p>If you have collective code ownership, it should be ok to comment on your team mates code (if not, jump directly to the next strategy). In this setting, just start to do some code reviews for others ! Make sure your reviews are helpful and &lsquo;nice&rsquo;.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll need to stick to doing code reviews long enough before people actually start to mimic you. Reserve some time in your daily agenda for code reviews. Your goal is to win over people, so it might be a good idea to start with a selected few at the beginning, preferably people who are more likely to jump in. If asynchronous (tool based) reviews don&rsquo;t get answered, be ready to fallback to face to face discussions : review on your own, then just ask the author for a few minutes so that you can discuss his change. When you feel someone is interested by your reviews, ask him to review your own code in return.</p>

<p>Remember to always try to get some feedback : ask people what they think of the exercise, keep note of the good points, and adapt to smooth out the rest.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-04-19-how-to-get-your-team-to-do-code-reviews/collective.jpg" alt="Illustration of a team working collectively" /><div class="image-credits">Photo from <a href="https://www.emotuit.com/blog">emotuit</a></div></p>

<p>Once you won over your first team mate, involve him in your grand plan to spread the practice, explaining how much you think this could make a difference. As more and more people get convinced, the practice will eventually tacitly become part of your working conventions.</p>

<p>Depending on your context, this might take more or less time. I said it was possible, I never said it would be easy ! Grit, patience and adaptation are key here.</p>

<h3>Otherwise</h3>

<p>This is the worst starting point, basically, you have nothing yet. The strategy is very similar to the one with collective code ownership, with a different first move.</p>

<p>Instead of providing code reviews to your team mates, start by walking over to them to ask for a face to face code review of your own commits. Use the same tactic as stated before : stick to the same people at first. Once the practice starts to stick within this group, bring in a basic tool to ease up the process.</p>

<p>At some point, you should be asked to review others code, that&rsquo;s a good sign ! If not, try again with other people.</p>

<p>Continue using the same strategy as with collective code ownership and you should eventually get there !</p>

<h3>When it does not seem to stick</h3>

<p>There could be many reason why the practice is not adopted. The key for you is to understand why and to adapt your strategy. The reason is often that the perceived value is not big enough, for example :</p>

<ul>
<li>the team is not aware of its problems that reviews would fix : try to make them more visible</li>
<li>reviews are seen as too expensive or painful : try better tools or taking more on yourself</li>
<li>the team has bigger problems to fix first : spend your energy on these first !</li>
<li>reviews just don&rsquo;t work in your context (ex: your job is to write one time, throw away code) : it&rsquo;s up to you to stay or leave !</li>
</ul>


<h2>Tools</h2>

<p>There are a ton of tools and best practices to run code reviews. It&rsquo;s important that you know them, so that you know where you are going.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t expect to use the best tools from the start though. At the beginning, your goal is to win over your team mates. In this context, only 2 things matter :</p>

<ul>
<li>It should have almost no adoption curve, so that others start using it</li>
<li>It should have almost no maintenance cost, as you don&rsquo;t want to spend your time doing that</li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s why at the beginning, low tech tools are so great. Spending a month setting up a top notch code review system before the first review won&rsquo;t work. If your VCS has code reviews built-in, by all means use it ! Otherwise, diff in mails and face to face conversations are a good starting point. You&rsquo;ll later hook something in your VCS to automatically send mails with commit diffs &hellip;</p>

<p>As people gradually get convinced of the value of code reviews, regularly meet and discuss a better setup. This is how you&rsquo;ll introduce state of the art tools and agree on refinements such as pre or post commit reviews.</p>

<h3>Best practices</h3>

<p>As a code review champion, it&rsquo;s very important that you provide great reviews to your team mates. You must become the local expert on the subject ! You don&rsquo;t want all your efforts to be ruined because one of your reviews has been perceived as aggressive.</p>

<p><a href="https://static.rainfocus.com/oracle/oow16/sess/1473264722807001CoS2/ppt/code-reviews-vs-pull-requests.pdf"><img src="../imgs/2017-04-19-how-to-get-your-team-to-do-code-reviews/atlassian.jpg" alt="A slide from Atlassian presentation about styles of code reviews" /></a></p>

<p>There is a ton of resources on the internet about how to perform good code reviews, here are a few :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/mariakhalusova">Maria Khalusova</a>&rsquo;s talk at Devoxx 2016 <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-tcy4z0hszg">How to stop wasting your time and start performing useful code reviews</a></li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@kannonboy/">Tim Pettersen</a> from <a href="https://www.atlassian.com">Atlassian</a> talked about <a href="https://static.rainfocus.com/oracle/oow16/sess/1473264722807001CoS2/ppt/code-reviews-vs-pull-requests.pdf">Code Reviews vs Pull Request</a> at JavaOne 2016</li>
<li><a href="http://marcotroisi.com/">Marco Troisi</a> wrote an extensive blog post about <a href="http://marcotroisi.com/how-run-code-reviews-in-your-workflow/">How to run code reviews in your dev team&rsquo;s workflow</a></li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@mrjoelkemp">Joel Kemp</a>&rsquo;s post <a href="https://medium.com/@mrjoelkemp/giving-better-code-reviews-16109e0fdd36">Giving better code reviews</a></li>
<li>Gareth Wilson&rsquo;s post <a href="https://blog.fogcreek.com/effective-code-reviews-9-tips-from-a-converted-skeptic/">Effective Code Reviews – 9 Tips from a Converted Skeptic</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>What&rsquo;s next ?</h2>

<p>Congratulations ! Your team will start to reap the benefits of code reviews. Keep on improving the practice !</p>

<p>To end the story, after a few months of code reviews, during a retrospective, my team (<a href="http://www.murex.com/">at work</a>) decided to take it one step further and started to do almost full time pair programming ;&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A seamless way to keep track of technical debt in your source code]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-seamless-way-to-keep-track-of-technical-debt-in-your-source-code/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-12T08:48:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-seamless-way-to-keep-track-of-technical-debt-in-your-source-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I eventually stumbled upon a way to keep track of technical debt in source code that is both straightforward and already built-in most tools : simple <code>TODO</code> comments !</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-04-12-a-seamless-way-to-keep-track-of-technical-debt-in-your-source-code/todo-comment.jpg" alt="Photo of a screen displaying source code with #TODO comments" /></p>

<h2>How it happened ?</h2>

<p>Some time ago, we tried to add <a href="/a-plan-for-technical-debt-lean-software-development-part-7/"><code>@TechnicalDebt</code></a> annotations in our source code. Unfortunately, after a few month, we came to the logical conclusion that it was too complex to be effective :</p>

<ul>
<li>It involved too much ceremony, which frightened people</li>
<li>It made people uneasy to change anything around the annotation instead of sending a call to action</li>
<li>As a result, it was always out of date</li>
</ul>


<p>After a bit of discussion with my colleagues, we decided to replace all these annotations with simple <code>TODO</code> comments.</p>

<p>When the refactoring to do seems fairly obvious (but also premature) we&rsquo;ll use a straightforward <code>//TODO (example) introduce a factory</code> message. Next time a pairs gets to work on this part of the code, they get the silent opinion of their peers to help them decide what to do about this piece of the code. Other times, the code might be smelly, yet without us knowing what to do about it yet, in this case, we agreed to use <code>//TODO SMELL (example) responsibilities are not clear in this class</code> which is still a <code>TODO</code> comment, but not a clear call to action.</p>

<p>When I started my <a href="https://github.com/philou/planning-poker">current side project</a>, I naturally started to use them. They display nicely in <a href="https://codeclimate.com/github/philou/planning-poker/issues">CodeClimate</a>.</p>

<h3>The pros</h3>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-04-12-a-seamless-way-to-keep-track-of-technical-debt-in-your-source-code/codeclimate.jpg" alt="Screenshot of the CodeClimate issue dashboard displaying TODO comments" /></p>

<p>The great thing about <code>TODO</code> comments is that, as a very old programming trick, they are already supported out of the box by most tools <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/">IntelliJ</a>, <a href="https://www.sonarqube.org/">SonarQube</a>, <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a>, <a href="https://codeclimate.com">CodeClimate</a> and I guess many others. Only one day after I refactored to <code>TODO</code> comments, a team mate fixed one that had appeared in his IDE&rsquo;s TODO tab !</p>

<h3>The cons</h3>

<p>Some tools, IDEs in particular, tend to assume that you should fix all your <code>TODOs</code> before you commit anything. That&rsquo;s not exactly how we are using them to track lasting technical debt. So that&rsquo;s one thing you need to keep in mind.</p>

<p>Tools like Sonar on the other hand, assign a fixed remediation cost to any <code>TODO</code> you have in the code, which is usually not the case at all !</p>

<h2>How to set it up in your project</h2>

<p>As you might guess, this is pretty easy. Just start adding <code>TODO</code> comments in your code &hellip;</p>

<h3>Teamwise</h3>

<p>It is worth first validating the practice with your colleagues though. There are many ways to do that, depending on your team&rsquo;s work habits :</p>

<ul>
<li>Use your team <a href="https://slack.com/">Slack</a> (or whatever chat room you use) to share a link to this post (for example) and create a yes/no poll</li>
<li>Or if you think you need it, create some wiki page explaining the practice and detailing its rationals in your context, add a yes/no poll, and finally share this page with your team</li>
<li>Eventually, if you think that this topic deserves it, setup a meeting with everyone and discuss the point. It might be worth sharing information about the practice beforehand to make the meeting more efficient. You can end the vote with a <a href="http://www.plays-in-business.com/thumb-voting/">thumb vote</a> (up : yes, down : no, side : whatever)</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="../imgs/2017-04-12-a-seamless-way-to-keep-track-of-technical-debt-in-your-source-code/thumb-vote.jpg" alt="Thumbs voting positions" /><div class="image-credits">Photo from <a href="http://www.plays-in-business.com/thumb-voting/">Plays in Business</a></div></p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t wait for unanimity to start the practice, majority is enough ! Make sure that people who voted the other way will follow the team practice in the end though. Remember that whatever the answer, discussing team practices is good.</p>

<p>Once all the team agreed on using (or not) <code>TODO</code> comments, mention the practice in your team&rsquo;s coding conventions or working agreements (which I strongly recommend to have written somewhere). If you don&rsquo;t have any yet, create some !</p>

<h3>Toolswise</h3>

<p>Most tools will handle <code>TODO</code> out of the box.</p>

<ul>
<li>Rails comes with a <code>rake notes</code> task to list <code>TODO</code> comments.</li>
<li>CodeClimate and SonarQube both lists <code>TODOs</code> as issues in their default config</li>
<li>Most IDEs have a &lsquo;TODO&rsquo; tab which will display the <code>TODO</code> comments in the project</li>
<li>Otherwise, good old grep will very happily find <code>TODO</code> comments in your code</li>
</ul>


<p>Some tools might require small tweaks to improve the experience :</p>

<ul>
<li>In IntelliJ, in the commit window, uncheck the &lsquo;Check TODO&rsquo; checkbox to avoid getting a warning at every commit</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="../imgs/2017-04-12-a-seamless-way-to-keep-track-of-technical-debt-in-your-source-code/intellij-commit.jpg" alt="IntelliJ's commit window, with its 'Check TODO' check box" /></p>

<ul>
<li>SonarQube uses the same fixed remediation cost for every TODO comment. It&rsquo;s up to you to adapt this remediation cost to your context.</li>
</ul>


<h2>What&rsquo;s next ?</h2>

<p><code>TODO</code> comments are a good starting point to track technical debt. Once you start using them, there are a few things you can do :</p>

<p>First, remember to fix some regularly. Very old <code>TODO</code> comments are technical debt of their own ! Using code quality dashboards like SonarQube or CodeClimate help to continuously improve your code.</p>

<p>If your tools allow it, you might consider setting up a simpler <code>//SMELL ...</code> instead of <code>//TODO SMELL ...</code> or whatever other special comment that might be useful in your context.</p>

<p>Finally, there is a lean continuous improvement practice which consists of logging problems as they occur. Doing this could help your team to decide which technical debt hotspots are the most important to fix. When appropriate, link the problems with the <code>TODO</code> comments. After a few weeks of this, walking through all the problems during a retrospective should shed light on what parts of the code are causing the most troubles.</p>

<h2>Edit 2017-04-19</h2>

<p>Thanks a lot for your comments ! People have suggested a ton of great improvements over my basic setup :</p>

<ul>
<li>plugins to other tools that also support <code>TODO</code> comments</li>
<li>activating automatic sync between issues in CodeClimate and your issue tracking system</li>
<li>using custom comments markers</li>
<li>adding an &lsquo;X&rsquo; to your comment every time you are bothered by the technical debt, tools can configured to assign a higher severity to issues with a lot of &lsquo;X&rsquo;</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Almost 15 years of using Design By Contract]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/almost-15-years-of-using-design-by-contract/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-14T18:57:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/almost-15-years-of-using-design-by-contract</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I first read about Design By Contract in 2002, in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Object-Oriented-Software-Construction-Book-CD-ROM/dp/0136291554/ref=sr_1_2?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1490073815&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=object+oriented+software+construction+meyer">Object Oriented Software Construction 2</a>. As soon as I read it, I was convinced, today, I still believe it&rsquo;s a great and fundamental technique. That&rsquo;s why, I almost never write a contract ! Let me explain.</p>

<h2>Phase 1 : DbC ignorance</h2>

<p>I started to code professionally in 2001. This was a time where design and quality software meant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_Rational_Rose_XDE">Rational Rose</a> (a UML design and code generation tool) while I, at the contrary, was just <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cowboy_coding">Cow Boy Coding</a> my way out of any problem I was given.</p>

<p>I wasn&rsquo;t really doing Object Oriented programming, but rather imperative programming, using objects as structs, getters, setters, and classes as a way to organize the code &hellip; In this context, my design skills were improving slowly, and I was at the risk of falling in love with a local-optimum practice that would prevent me from growing further.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s why I started to read books such as the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Design-Patterns-Elements-Reusable-Object-Oriented/dp/0201633612/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1490074343&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=design+patterns">Gang Of Four Design Patterns</a>, or <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Object-Oriented-Software-Construction-Book-CD-ROM/dp/0136291554/ref=sr_1_2?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1490073815&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=object+oriented+software+construction+meyer">OOSC2</a>.</p>

<h2>Phase 2 : DbC enlightenment</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Object-Oriented-Software-Construction-Book-CD-ROM/dp/0136291554/ref=sr_1_2?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1490073815&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=object+oriented+software+construction+meyer"><img src="../imgs/2017-03-14-almost-15-years-of-using-design-by-contract/OOSC2.jpg" alt="The cover of the Object Oriented Software Construction 2" /></a></p>

<p>Reading this book was a profound experience to me. My programming changed fundamentally before and after reading it. The chapter about contracts, taught me what objects are.</p>

<p>One the one hand, Pre and Post conditions can be used in any kind of programming and are just a kind of C <code>assert</code> macro on steroids. Class invariant, on the other hand, is a completely different kind of beast. The invariant of a class is a predicate about an instance of this class that should always be true. For example : field X should never be null, or the value of field N should always be greater than 0.</p>

<p>In some way, grasping the concept of invariant is close to understanding what a class is.</p>

<h2>Phase 3 : DbC everywhere</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s when I started to write contracts everywhere. I was writing C++ code at the time, and my code must have looked something like that :</p>

<p>```c++
class MonkeyWrench
{</p>

<pre><code>bool _isStarted;
std::vector&lt;Part&gt;* _movingParts;
</code></pre>

<p>protected:</p>

<pre><code>virtual void invariant() const
{
    assert(_isStarted == (_movingParts != NULL));
}
</code></pre>

<p>public:</p>

<pre><code>MonkeyWrench()
{
    this-&gt;_isStarted = false;
    this-&gt;_movingParts = NULL;

    invariant();
}

bool isStarted() const
{
    return this-&gt;isStarted();
}

void start()
{
    assert(!this-&gt;isStarted());
    invariant();

    this-&gt;_movingParts = ...

    invariant();
    assert(this-&gt;isStarted());
}

const std::vector&lt;Part&gt;&amp; movingParts() const
{
    assert(this-&gt;isStarted());
    invariant();

    return *this-&gt;_movingParts;
}
...
</code></pre>

<p>};
```</p>

<p>I definitely over-abused contracts, it made the code unreadable. Plus sometimes, I was using excessively long and intricate assertions which made the problem even worse.</p>

<p>Hopefully, overusing contracts also taught me a lot in a short time. Here are some of the lessons I learned :</p>

<ul>
<li>DbC is not very well supported, it&rsquo;s never something built in the language, and edge cases like inheriting an invariant or conditions can become messy pretty fast.</li>
<li>Checking for intricate contracts at every method call can be pretty slow.</li>
<li>Checking everything beforehand is not always the simplest thing to do, at times, throwing an exception on failure just does a better job.</li>
<li>It happened that removing the contract made the code do just what I wanted. It&rsquo;s easy to write unnecessary strict contracts.</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Command%E2%80%93query_separation">Command Query Separation Principle</a> is great ! Having &lsquo;const&rsquo; or &lsquo;pure&rsquo; queries that don&rsquo;t change anything make writing contracts a lot simpler.</li>
<li>Preconditions on queries are painful. When possible, returning a sensible &lsquo;null value&rsquo; works better, nothing is worse than getting an error when trying to call a const query from the interactive debugger.</li>
<li>Finally, the more immutable a class is, the simpler the invariant. With a lot of mutable fields, you might resort to have the invariant check that fields are synchronized as expected. If fields are immutable, this simply vanishes.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Phase 4 : DbC hangover</h2>

<p>At the same time I discovered all these small subtleties about contracts, I fell upon Martin Fowler&rsquo;s book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1490074424&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=refactoring+improving+the+design+of+existing+code">Refactoring, improving the design of existing code</a> and started to use Unit Tests extensively. This lead me to the following conclusions :</p>

<ul>
<li>Tests are more efficient at producing quality software</li>
<li>Contracts can be an hindrance when trying to do baby steps refactorings as described in Martin Fowler&rsquo;s book</li>
</ul>


<p>On top of that, as DbC is not natively supported by languages, no documentation is generated, meaning that most of the time, the callers still have to look into the code. As a result, I was using contracts less and less often.</p>

<h2>Phase 5 : DbC Zen</h2>

<p>Looking back, I might not be writing a lot of <code>asserts</code> in my code, but I am still thinking in terms of contracts all the time. In fact, there are a ton of ways to use DbC without writing assertions :</p>

<ul>
<li>Use as much immutability as possible. An immutable class does not need to check its invariant all the time, just throwing from the constructor if arguments are not valid is enough.</li>
<li>Use conventions as much as possible, for example, constructor arguments should be set for all the life of the object (cf <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Growing-Object-Oriented-Software-Guided-Tests/dp/0321503627/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1490074450&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=growing+object+oriented+software+guided+by+tests">Growing Object Oriented Software Guided by Tests</a> which describes the different ways to inject something in an object)</li>
<li>Looking back at my DbC assertions, most relate to null values. Again conventions work better ! At work, we simply forbid passing null values around. If something can be null, it means it&rsquo;s optional, Java has an <code>Optional&lt;T&gt;</code> class for just that (I&rsquo;m pretty sure it is possible to do something even better with C++ templates). In this case, if the contract is broken, NullReferenceException will eventually be our assertion.</li>
<li>Replace as many pre &amp; post conditions with invariants on the callee, the arguments or the return objects as possible. It makes sense as it&rsquo;s just making sure we are using &lsquo;valid&rsquo; objects everywhere. Again, if these objects are immutable, it makes the whole thing even simpler !</li>
<li>To take further benefit of the invariant of immutable objects, introduce new types. For example, instead of changing an object&rsquo;s state through a command with associated involved contracts, split the class in 2 and make the method a query returning an immutable object, potentially making the initial class immutable as well. Remember, immutable classes mean almost no assertions !</li>
<li>Use your language. Ex, instead of asserting that 2 lists remain of the same length, refactor to a list of pairs ! (I know that&rsquo;s an obvious example, but you get the point)</li>
<li>If you are using a statically typed language, use types ! For example, I remember at one project I worked on, we had an bug involving a duration : somewhere in the code milliseconds got mistaken for seconds &hellip; We fixed that by replacing the <code>integer</code> by <code>TimeSpan</code> all over the place. Again, that&rsquo;s so obvious !</li>
<li>Eventually, when all else fails, or when it&rsquo;s just too much overhead, use the simple asserts provided by your language or common libraries.</li>
</ul>


<p>To come back at the previous code section, this how it could be written without assertions :</p>

<p>```c++
class MovingMonkeyWrench
{</p>

<pre><code>const std::vector&lt;Part&gt; _parts;
</code></pre>

<p>public:</p>

<pre><code>MovingMonkeyWrench() : _parts(...) {}

const std::vector&lt;Part&gt;&amp; parts() const
{
    return this-&gt;_parts;
}
...
</code></pre>

<p>};</p>

<p>class MonkeyWrench
{ <br/>
public:</p>

<pre><code>MovingMonkeyWrench start() const
{
    return MovingMonkeyWrench();
}
...
</code></pre>

<p>};
```</p>

<p>Details are omitted, but it&rsquo;s easy to see how shorter the code is.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>When applying all the techniques above, you&rsquo;ll see that cases for explicit assertions are rare. Less assertions also workarounds the issues coming from the poor support for DbC : no documentation and intricate cases.</p>

<p>In the end, assertions made my code more &lsquo;functional&rsquo;. I&rsquo;m not alone to have done the same journey, and if you are interested you should read Eric Evans' <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1490082811&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design">DDD</a> book where he presents things like immutable value objects and specification objects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developer ! Are you losing your rat race ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/developer-are-you-losing-your-rat-race/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-09T05:37:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/developer-are-you-losing-your-rat-race</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>A rat race is an endless, self-defeating, or pointless pursuit. It conjures up the image of the futile efforts of a lab rat trying to escape while running around a maze or in a wheel.</p></blockquote>

<p>Are we building our own <del>maze</del> self defeating landscape by our exacerbated focus on technology ? Let me explain.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2017-02-09-developer-are-you-losing-your-rat-race/rat-maze.jpg" title="A rat in a maze" ></p>

<h2>The context</h2>

<p>As <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marc_Andreessen">Marc Andreessen</a> famously said &ldquo;Software is eating the world&rdquo;, which means that there is more and more demand for software. At the same time, giant countries like China, India, Russia or Brazil are producing more and more master&rsquo;s degrees every year. This also means more and more software engineers. The consequence is that there has never been so many new technologies emerging than these days. The software landscape his huge, growing and complex.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s great for progress, but it&rsquo;s a puzzle for hiring. In this chaotic environment, years of experience with a particular technology is something that remains easy to measure, that&rsquo;s why employers (and developers) tend to use keywords to cast for a job.</p>

<h2>The effects</h2>

<p>As a result, developers tend to pick a few technologies to become masters at, to put them on their CV and get job offers. There&rsquo;s a danger with specializing on a particular technology : eventually, it will become deprecated, in this keyword driven world, it&rsquo;s almost like if you&rsquo;ll have to start from zero again. Even if a specialization is wide enough now, as time goes on and more and more technologies are created, any area of expertise will become a tiny spot in all the landscape. One might think this is only an issue for old guys that did not stay up to date &hellip; I strongly believe this is wrong, it happened to all past technologies, I don&rsquo;t see why today&rsquo;s latest .js framework wouldn&rsquo;t be legacy stuff one day.</p>

<p>One could think that sticking to a good employer is a good fix against that. It is &hellip; for some time ! Sticking to an company actually means <em>betting</em> on this company. What would happen if it went out of business, or through difficult times and you&rsquo;re asked to leave ? When you reach the job market after so long with a single employer, you&rsquo;ll be a de-facto specialist, on proprietary stuff that no one is interested about.</p>

<p>Finally, you might work hard not to specialize, but it&rsquo;s going to be a lot more difficult to get a job as a generalist, only a few shops actually hire this way.</p>

<p>To summarize, we are forced into specialization, which is great in the short term, but risky in the long run.</p>

<h2>1€ advice</h2>

<p>So what can we do about this ? Obviously, we cannot change the world &hellip; The only ones we can act on are ourselves !</p>

<h3>Learning</h3>

<p>In our fast moving tech world, learning remains key ! But instead of trying to keep up with all the cool new techs that are invented every day, we should study fundamental skills, and only learn just enough specific skills to get the job done. To me fundamental skills are all the things you&rsquo;ll apply whatever the language and technology you are using, for example :</p>

<ul>
<li>design</li>
<li>architecture (whatever that is &hellip;)</li>
<li>clean code</li>
<li>refactoring</li>
<li>legacy code</li>
<li>testing</li>
<li>tooling</li>
<li>mentoring &amp; coaching</li>
<li>programming paradigms (functional, dynamic, static, imperative, OO, concurrent &hellip;)</li>
<li>process flow</li>
<li>communication</li>
<li>product definition</li>
<li>concurrency</li>
<li>performance</li>
</ul>


<p>I wrote <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/">this post</a> that explains how I did learn some of these skills (by no mean would I say that this is the only way). Good mastery of these skills should be enough to quickly get up to speed in any project you are involved. This other article <a href="https://blog.bradfieldcs.com/in-2017-learn-every-language-59b11f68eee#.l2n6kouuz">In 2017, learn <em>every</em> language</a>, which I found through the excellent <a href="http://www.hackernewsletter.com/">hackernewsletter</a>, explains how this is possible.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, knowing is not enough &hellip;</p>

<h3>Selling</h3>

<p>How do you convince others that you are up to the job in a particular technology ? Unfortunately, I don&rsquo;t have a definitive answer yet &hellip;</p>

<p>Regularly, people try to coin a word to describe the competent generalist developer : polyglot, full stack, craftsman &hellip; If it&rsquo;s good enough, it usually gets taken over quite fast by the industry and just becomes yet another buzzword (the only exception being eXtreme Programming, but who would like to hire and eXtreme Programmer ?).</p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1473135683&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=soft+skills">Soft Skills</a>, John Somnez says the trick is to explain to people that you might not have experience in a technology &lsquo;yet&rsquo;. This might work, if your resume gets through, which is not sure.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s my try : the next time I&rsquo;ll polish my resume, I&rsquo;ll try to put forward my fundamental skills first, for example with 5 stars self-assessments. Only after will I add something like &ldquo;By the way, I could work with tech X Y Z &hellip;&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Independence</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Jobs-Meaning-9-5/dp/1619613352/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1486713381&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+end+of+jobs"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2017-02-09-developer-are-you-losing-your-rat-race/the-end-of-jobs.jpg" title="Cover of the book &lsquo;The End of Jobs&rsquo;" ></a></p>

<p>Being your own boss could be a solution in the long term. I recently listened to <a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Jobs-Meaning-9-5/dp/1619613352/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1486713381&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+end+of+jobs">The End of Jobs</a> in which the author explains that entrepreneurship is an accessible alternative these days, and that like any skill, it&rsquo;s learnable. The catch is that there are no schools, no diplomas, and that it seems a lot riskier in the short run. Despite that, he makes the point that the skills you&rsquo;ll learn makes it quite safe in the long run !</p>

<h2>Questions</h2>

<p>I feel like my post asks more questions than it provides answers :&ndash;). Honestly, I&rsquo;d really love to read other people&rsquo;s opinions and ideas. What are your tricks to market yourself on new technologies ? As a community, what could we do to fight our planned obsolescence ? Do you think I&rsquo;m totally wrong and that the problem does not exist ? What do you think ?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Happens to Non-Enthusiast Programmers in the Long Run ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/what-happens-to-non-enthusiast-programmers-in-the-long-run/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-10T05:57:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/what-happens-to-non-enthusiast-programmers-in-the-long-run</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago, after receiving good feedback from my regular readers, I posted my latest article <a href="/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/">Is There Any Room for the Not-Passionate Developer ?</a> on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/">Hackernews</a> and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/programming/">Reddit</a>. I got a <a href="/how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging/">huge number of visits</a>, a lot more than I typically get !</p>

<p>I also got a lot more comments, some nice, some tough, some agreeable and some challenging !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2017-01-10-what-happens-to-non-enthusiast-programmers-in-the-long-run/professional.jpg" title="A logo of a guy wearing a suit" ></p>

<h2>First, a summary</h2>

<p>In this previous article, I wanted to contrast the different views about work/life balance in the software industry.</p>

<p>Some, like agile gurus and companies like Basecamp, and <a href="http://lifehacker.com/working-over-40-hours-a-week-makes-you-less-productive-1725646811">studies</a>, strongly advocate for sane work hours. They explain that it results in greater productivity and healthy life.</p>

<p>On the other hand, the software field is always bubbling with novelty, and keeping up to date with technologies is by itself a challenge that takes time. For some companies, which might already be fighting for their survival against competition, it is almost impossible to grant some extra training time to their employees. The problem becomes particularly difficult when engineers get older, become parents and cannot afford to spend some extra time learning the latest JavaScript framework.</p>

<p>As a conclusion, I said that for most of us, it&rsquo;s really difficult to remain a developer in the long run without the grit that only passion for programming brings. I encourage you to <a href="/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/">read it</a> for more details.</p>

<h2>What I learned from the comments</h2>

<p>First of all, thanks a lot for all these, they were very valuable, they forced me to think even more about the issue.</p>

<h3>People have been burnt !</h3>

<p>The word &lsquo;passion&rsquo; in particular, triggered engaged comments. As some pointed out, &lsquo;enthusiast&rsquo; or &lsquo;professional&rsquo; should be favored. It seems that some companies have asked their employees for unquestionable passion for their business (and not for engineering or programming) at the cost of the people&rsquo;s own lives. As a commenter said, a lot of shops do not integrate the absolute necessity for their programmers to learn continuously in their business model. It made me kind of sad to feel once more this state of our industry.</p>

<p>As a result, people are weary of any statement of &lsquo;passion&rsquo; in the workplace, and would prefer to be seen as very skilled professional, dedicated to keeping their skills up to date.</p>

<h3>The particular question of France</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2017-01-10-what-happens-to-non-enthusiast-programmers-in-the-long-run/france.jpg" title="A photo of the Eiffel tower" ></p>

<p>I received some comments from all over the world, but my observations came from where I work : in France. Here, all in all, we have at least 7 weeks of paid leaves per year. It&rsquo;s a lot more than in other parts of the world. I think it&rsquo;s around 2 weeks in the US (other <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2016-10-18/americans-work-25-more-than-europeans-study-finds">sources</a> point the same fact). Imagine two companies, one from France, and one from the US. The one in the US can invest 5 weeks per year in exploratory learning (which can result in good things for both the business and the employee) while still producing as much as the french one.</p>

<p>Obviously, there are other parameters to take into account for overall productivity like hours per day, the effects of holidays or long hours on creativity, or funding &hellip; but here are some facts about software engineering in France :</p>

<ul>
<li>20% time policy, hackathons and other exploratory learning are extremely rare (I&rsquo;ve seen it once in 15 years)</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s slowly getting better, but if you remain a programmer in your thirties, you&rsquo;re seen as a loser</li>
<li>France has no software powerhouse like Microsoft, Google, Apple &hellip;</li>
</ul>


<p>This lead me to this open question : What&rsquo;s the effect of the 7 weeks of paid leaves on the french software industry ?</p>

<p>By no means will I try to give an answer, I just don&rsquo;t know. Plus, for those who might be wondering : I love my 7 weeks of holidays !</p>

<h2>The conclusion I came to</h2>

<p>Yet, I can try to draw a conclusion at the individual level. In France, if you&rsquo;re not really enthusiastic about programming, you won&rsquo;t put the extra effort off-the-job to learn the latest technologies. Within a few years, you&rsquo;ll be &lsquo;deprecated&rsquo;, which will leave you with mainly 2 options :</p>

<ul>
<li>become a manager</li>
<li>stick to your current codebase (and become completely dependent of your employer)</li>
</ul>


<p>To me, the sad truth is that if you want to make a career as a professional developer in France, you&rsquo;d better be ready to spend some of your free time practicing !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
