<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: learning | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-30T06:26:08+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I got my feet wet with machine learning with 'The First 20 Hours']]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-i-got-my-feet-wet-with-machine-learning-with-the-first-20-hours/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-29T21:09:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-i-got-my-feet-wet-with-machine-learning-with-the-first-20-hours</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m currently wrapping up an alpha of a unit testing <a href="https://github.com/philou/complexity-assert">ruby gem</a> that allows to assert the complexity of a piece of code. It&rsquo;s the result of an experiment to learn some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machine_learning">Machine Learning</a> skills in 20 hours &hellip; not bad for a first a try at Data Science ! This is the story of this experiment.</p>

<h2>How it all started ?</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/First-20-Hours-Learn-Anything/dp/1591846943/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1483258282&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+first+20+hours"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-12-29-how-i-got-my-feet-wet-with-machine-learning-with-the-first-20-hours/book-cover.jpg" title="The cover of the book &lsquo;The First 20 Hours&rsquo;" ></a></p>

<p>A few months ago, I read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/First-20-Hours-Learn-Anything/dp/1591846943/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1483258282&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+first+20+hours">The First 20 Hours</a>. The book describes a technique to get up to speed and learn some practical skills on any particular subject in only 20 hours. As examples, the author details how he managed to teach himself a pretty decent level of Yoga, Ukulele, Wind Surfing, Programming, Go and touch typing.</p>

<p>I decided to give it a try. In order to get a boost, I found a few motivated people at work to do it with me. I started by presenting them the technique described in the book, and asked everyone what they wanted to learn. After a quick vote, we set out to learn more about Machine Learning.</p>

<h2>The technique</h2>

<p>The method is meant to allow anyone to learn necessary skills to accomplish a specific task in about 20 hours. I my case, I could expect to get a basic understanding of the Machine Learning concepts, as well as some practical skills to do something involving Machine Learning. Here are the details of the technique :</p>

<ol>
<li>H0 : Deep dive in the main concepts and theory of machine learning</li>
<li>H6 : Define an ambitious and practical goal or skill level to achieve by the end, and an outline of how to get there</li>
<li>H6 to H20 : Learn by doing</li>
</ol>


<p>As you see, the technique is pretty simple !</p>

<h2>How did it work ?</h2>

<h3>For the group</h3>

<p>The plan for the group was :</p>

<ul>
<li>to meet weekly for 2 hours</li>
<li>to share what we learned at the end of every session</li>
<li>to bound by similar goals</li>
</ul>


<p>At first, people were enthusiastic about learning something like machine learning. After a while, I started to get the following remarks :</p>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t really see the point of doing this together rather than independently&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;I&rsquo;m feeling a bit lost by not having a concrete goal and a plan from H0&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;I picked up a target that&rsquo;s too large for me&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>The learning curve must have proven too steep, because as time went by, a lot of people droped out, and we ended up being only 2 !</p>

<h3>For me</h3>

<p>The first phase was the toughest. As the author had warned in his book, &ldquo;You&rsquo;ll get deep above your head in theory and concepts you don&rsquo;t know&rdquo;, &ldquo;You&rsquo;ll feel lost&rdquo;. He had some reassuring words though : &ldquo;The steeper the learning curve, the more you&rsquo;ll be learning !&rdquo; I actually like this feeling of unknown things to learn, and that&rsquo;s why I stuck to it.</p>

<p>I took me 8 hours, and not 6 to get a good overall grasp of Machine Learning techniques. The theory was just too wide and interesting and I could not cut the learning after just 6 hours :&ndash;). I studied <a href="https://xyclade.github.io/MachineLearning/#cross-validation">Machine Learning for developers</a> plus a few other pages for details on specific points. I took and kept notes about what I learned. I chose my subject &ldquo;unit testing algorithm complexity&rdquo; for the following reasons :</p>

<ul>
<li>I could imagine some utility</li>
<li>I had been writing benchmarks at work for 3 years, and I knew the practice well enough</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s pretty easy to generate data for this subject : just run your algorithm !</li>
<li>It seems a good first step, doable with basic Machine Learning techniques like linear regression</li>
<li>It seems small enough to get something working in 12 hours</li>
<li>I could use ruby, which I find both fast and pleasant to program</li>
</ul>


<p>This is the plan I set out :</p>

<ol>
<li>Generate data with a linear algorithm (O(n))</li>
<li>Run linear regression on the data</li>
<li>Compute the the <a href="https://xyclade.github.io/MachineLearning/#root-mean-squared-error-rmse">RMSE</a> of the model</li>
<li>Deal with Garbage Collection in order to make reduce its noise</li>
<li>Deal with interpreter warm-up for the same reason</li>
<li>Generate data for a constant (O(1)) algorithm and build a model for it</li>
<li>Find a way to identify if an algorithm is constant or linear from it&rsquo;s execution timings</li>
<li>Generate data for a quadratic (O(2)) algorithm and build a model for it</li>
<li>Identify if an algorithm is constant, linear or quadratic</li>
<li>Package all this in an <a href="http://rspec.info/">RSpec</a> library</li>
</ol>


<p>It started well, and I made good progress. Unfortunately, as people dropped out of the group and I got more urgent things to do at work, I had to pause my project for a while. It&rsquo;s only been since last week that I got some time during my holidays to finish this off. I&rsquo;m currently at H18, and I&rsquo;ve completed all steps from 1 to 9.</p>

<p>As I said the project is still in early alpha. They is a lot of points in which it could be improved (more complexities, faster, more reliable &hellip;). Even though I did not tackle the more advanced machine learning techniques, I now understand the overall process of ML : explore to get an intuitive grasp of the data, try out a model, see what happens, and repeat &hellip; I feel that learning these more advanced techniques would be easier now.</p>

<h2>My opinion on the method</h2>

<p>Overall, I found the experiment really effective, it&rsquo;s possible to learn quite a lot by focusing on it for 20 hours. A word of warning though : you need to be really motivated and ready to stick through difficulties.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also been very pleasant. I&rsquo;ve always loved to learn new things, so I might be a little biased on that aspect. I liked the first part when I felt that there was a lot to learn in a large subject I knew almost nothing about. I loved the second part too, although this might be more related to machine learning, because I felt like exploring an unknown (data set) and trying to understand it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve never been afraid to learn something, doing this experiment taught me I can learn anything fast ! I&rsquo;ll definitely re-use it again.</p>

<p>One last word about doing this in group. My own experiment did not work very well. Most people were not comfortable with the first &lsquo;explore&rsquo; phase. I guess one could make it work better by starting 6 or 8 hours before the rest of the group, enough to grasp the basic concepts and come up with a few end goals. Having concrete targets from day 1 should help people to stick through and to collaborate. The &lsquo;guide&rsquo; could also help the others through the first phase.</p>

<p>Stay tuned, I&rsquo;ll present my gem in <a href="/verify-the-big-o-complexity-of-ruby-code-in-rspec/">a following post</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
