<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: scrum | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/scrum/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-18T09:45:16+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Most Scrum teams are not agile]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-09T06:36:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being agile is about adapting to change and continuously improving. I&rsquo;ve seen (and been) in too many teams blindly following Scrum (<a href="/how-to-kill-scrum-zombies/">Scrum Zombies</a>) without figuring out how to continuous improve. The most obvious symptom is a boring (or no) retrospective.</p>

<p>Usually, it did not start that way, people had good intentions, and tried to follow the Scrum cookbook. Unfortunately, without any guidance or extreme perseverance, it is plain too easy to mess up the retrospective. If no concrete actions are scheduled at the end of the retro, if the same problems keep coming up at every retro, or if no problems at all are raised during the retro : your Scrum is somehow broken !</p>

<p>One of the promises of Scrum is to keep code quality high, in order to be able to adapt to late changes. Without a good retro to update the coding standards, the working agreements, or to spot and organize large scale refactoring, this will not happen.</p>

<p>One of the agile principle <a href="http://agilemanifesto.org/principles.html">explicitly states</a> the need for motivated team members. In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Drive-Surprising-Truth-About-Motivates/dp/1594484805/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494561757&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=pink+drive">Drive</a> Daniel Pink explains that one of the ingredient for motivation is autonomy. As a way to fix recurring problems, effective retrospectives will create autonomy, and enable motivation. Dysfunctional retros will slowly kill both &hellip;</p>

<p>Although continuous improvement at all levels is one of the most important element in your process, it needs a bit of practice to setup right. After trying different approach in different teams, I compiled a list of the things that worked for me :</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Drive-Surprising-Truth-About-Motivates/dp/1594484805/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494561757&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=pink+drive"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-09-most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/drive.jpg" alt="The cover of the Daniel Pink's &quot;Drive&quot; book" /></a></p>

<h2>How to do successful retrospectives</h2>

<h3>Start !</h3>

<p>Sounds obvious ! The first step is to schedule a recurring meeting and invite all the team. Someone should take care of facilitating. If you want to improve things, do this yourself at the beginning ! Once the practice is in place and everyone sees the benefits, you&rsquo;ll be able to get some help.</p>

<p><a href="/how-we-introduced-efficient-agile-retrospectives/">Here</a> is a crash-course about how to organize and drive your first retrospective. If your team is distributed, you&rsquo;ll need a slightly different setup. In my previous team, we had success using <a href="https://trello.com">Trello</a>, you can read more about it <a href="/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">here</a>.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-05-09-most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/just-do-it.jpg" alt="Just Do It picture" /></p>

<h3>Make sure everyone talks</h3>

<p>Retros should not be &ldquo;just-another-boring-meeting&rdquo; ! People should be excited to be there and to solve their recurring problems. I&rsquo;ve seen retros where no one would speak, as if there was absolutely nothing to improve ! I&rsquo;ve also been in retros where people raised collaboration issues, and came up with drastic improvements to the way they work, like adopting pair-programming for example.</p>

<p>There can be many reason why people don&rsquo;t speak : habit, organizational culture &hellip; Whatever the cause, if you show them the path, if you demonstrate that retro work and that it is safe to speak, you&rsquo;ll get them to participate.</p>

<p>Here are a few tricks to guide a team there :</p>

<ul>
<li>It is said that if someone does not speak in the first 5 minutes of a meeting, he&rsquo;ll remain silent for the rest. That&rsquo;s why <a href="www.funretrospectives.com/category/energizer/">energizers</a> work. They force everyone to participate to a Fun activity right from the start. <a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/">Fun Retrospective</a> contains a lot of engaging energizers.</li>
<li>Bring food ! Having food at work was one of Kent Beck&rsquo;s main advises in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0201616416/ref=sr_1_2?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494561932&amp;sr=1-2&amp;keywords=extreme+programming+explained+embrace+change">eXtreme Programming, Embrace Change</a>. Food is social and create a more relaxed and safer atmosphere.</li>
<li>Before you start the meeting, it might be useful to repeat the <a href="http://www.retrospectives.com/pages/retroPrimeDirective.html">Retrospective&rsquo;s Prime Directive</a>.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>Regardless of what we discover, we understand and truly believe that everyone did the best job they could, given what they knew at the time, their skills and abilities, the resources available, and the situation at hand.</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li>As the animator, you should make sure the discussions don&rsquo;t degenerate into some kind of trolling or blaming. If it&rsquo;s the case, remind that this is not the way the retro is meant to work. In worst case, give a 5 minutes break to everyone to calm down.</li>
<li>If needed, have a private discussion with people outside the retro to make sure that they understand the &ldquo;Blame the process, not the people&rdquo; principle of the retro well enough.</li>
</ul>


<p>Dealing with &ldquo;bad&rdquo; behavior in retros is a wide topic which I am only scratching the surface here. I guess I could write a full post about it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-09-most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/fun-retro.jpeg" alt="The cover of the &quot;Fun Retrospectives&quot; book" /></a></p>

<h3>Get out of with actionable tasks</h3>

<p>If you want a sure way to screw up your retros here it is : end the first one with no actionable things to do ! People will learn that it&rsquo;s a useless pscho-blabla meeting for agile softies.</p>

<p>This should be the absolute priority during the first retros. There are various kind of actionable tasks. Teams can adopt new conventions, decide to tackle some specific refactoring, or build a small new tool &hellip;</p>

<p>Actionable items should be small enough to be completed in one sprint. This is fine for refactoring a class, adding a <a href="https://www.sonarqube.org/">SonarQube</a> rule or asking for something from another team. What about larger tasks ? Suppose you just identified a large refactoring to do, how do you get started ? I know 2 strategies for that :</p>

<ul>
<li>Only identify the first step of what you want to start. At least, that&rsquo;s enough to get started and learn what to do later.</li>
<li>Agree on a <a href="https://mikadomethod.wordpress.com/">Mikado</a> discovery task to understand what needs to be done. Code is not the only thing that can be refactored with the Mikado method ! People have used it to transform <a href="http://nomad8.com/organisational-change-with-mikado/">organizations</a> !</li>
</ul>


<p>It&rsquo;s also a good habit to book the rooms for extra time after the official retro time. Nothing is as frustrating as being interrupted while investigating a promising improvement !</p>

<p>Finally, I think it&rsquo;s a good practice to review what happened of the improvements that were selected during last retro. It stresses the importance of doing what was scheduled in retrospective. It also gives a chance to investigate the reason why they were not done !</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mikado-Method-Ola-Ellnestam/dp/1617291218/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494562230&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=mikado+method"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-09-most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/mikado-method.jpg" alt="The cover of the &quot;Mikado Method&quot; book" /></a></p>

<h3>Put them in the sprint</h3>

<p>When actions are selected in the retro, you should add them to the coming sprint before it starts. Obviously, you&rsquo;ll add non business related items in your sprint backlog. Whatever you might have hear from agile zealots, do it ! Process improvements are fist class backlog citizens, just don&rsquo;t discuss them with your <a href="https://www.scrum.org/resources/blog/who-professional-scrum-product-owner">product owner</a>.</p>

<p>If you want a chance to deliver what you committed to in your sprint backlog, you&rsquo;ll need bandwidth for that ! They are many ways to do get that. Some teams use <a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/slack.html">slack time</a>, others reserve an &lsquo;improvement day&rsquo; every sprint. My personal favorite (and the one we&rsquo;ve been doing at work) is to estimate the improvements in story points and reserve a fraction (ex 20%) of your story points for improvements.</p>

<p>You can try to negotiate your improvement ratio with your product owner &hellip; or you might also just set it yourself ! The team is responsible for the quality of its work. Better be sorry than ineffective. If you stick to your ratio and only work on the most important improvements, it&rsquo;s usually pretty easy to justify working on them. Plus if you manage to go under the radar for a few sprints, the results of the improvements should speak by themselves.</p>

<h3>Do them as soon as the sprint starts</h3>

<p>One last thing. Start to work on your improvements as soon as the sprint starts.</p>

<p>Improvements are similar to investments : you invest in process, tools or code in exchange for more value creation downstream. Once you&rsquo;ve decided to invest in something, what&rsquo;s the point of waiting 1 week ? Plus if you wait for later in the sprint, you run the risk of having unfinished improvements at the next retro, which might interfere when prioritizing new ones.</p>

<h2>Continuously improving teams</h2>

<p>Being part of a continuously improving team is easier to live than to describe. It feels like the future is bright. Once a team has mastered continuous improvement, people can be optimistic that they&rsquo;ll manage to adapt to change later down the road :</p>

<ul>
<li>They could switch gears and go full speed on a particular re-architecture</li>
<li>They could change their working agreements to adapt to new constraints</li>
<li>They could re-focus their efforts to handle a maintenance pike</li>
</ul>


<p>At the end of the day, bottom-up continuous improvement makes everyone&rsquo;s lives easier. Developers experience more autonomy while improving their productivity, they can do good work (which also means spending less time bug-fixing). Product owners learn that they can trust the team to do their best. Sponsors get more value for their money.</p>

<blockquote><p>Agile teams bend so they don&rsquo;t break !</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Straightforward Way to Scale to More Than 1 Scrum Team]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-straightforward-way-to-scale-to-more-than-1-scrum-team/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-02T06:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-straightforward-way-to-scale-to-more-than-1-scrum-team</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How come the &ldquo;agile scaling&rdquo; landscape seems so daunting and bloated ?</p>

<p>Being agile should be about taking baby steps, doing things incrementally, starting with the simplest thing that could possibly work, slowly but continuously improving and trying out experiments.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a real-life 2 hours change that kicks-off a very efficient organization for a few scrum teams.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-05-02-a-straightforward-way-to-scale-to-more-than-1-scrum-team/dive-jump.jpg" alt="A guy jumping from a cliff into the sea" /><div class="image-credits">&ldquo;SafeLess&rdquo; : everything will go fine as long as you follow the principles</div></p>

<h2>A classic story</h2>

<p>Without doing anything about it, there are a lot of situations in where <a href="https://www.scrum.org/">Scrum</a> teams will collaborate inefficiently. For example if you are a developer within a medium or large company, suffering from communication loss between your team and others. Or you could be the owner of a software startup, needing to dramatically grow your dev team.</p>

<p>Whatever your situation, without good collaboration, the output of two Scrum teams is bound to be a fraction of the sum of their individual outputs.</p>

<h3>Our own situation</h3>

<p>We are a group of 4 teams that spun out of the R&amp;D division. We are working to build a highly reusable component for the future versions of <a href="http://www.murex.com">Murex</a>&rsquo;s main product.</p>

<p>While in R&amp;D, teams were aligned with technologies. Now shifting to a product focus, this layered team structure makes it hard for us to organize efficiently. To make things even more tricky, the component we are building is something huge by itself, and we really need to find a way to deliver it incrementally.</p>

<p>This tech-oriented, low synchronization organization of team backlog was really underdelivering. It was not rare to see stories jump from one team to another, as dependencies were discovered, taking one full sprint every time. Integrating end to end features often took a few sprints instead of a few hours &hellip;</p>

<p>Clearly, we needed to do something.</p>

<h3>The simplest things that could possibly work</h3>

<p>Hopefully, all teams were following Scrum. We first had a look at scaling frameworks, especially since other parts of the company are moving to <a href="http://www.scaledagileframework.com/">SAFe</a> but we found that they required too much budget and re-organization for our means (remember, we are just a few motivated developers).</p>

<p>While we were discussing what to do, someone had an idea that was simple, cheap and easy : &ldquo;Let&rsquo;s start by doing all our scrum ceremonies together&rdquo;.</p>

<p>We took the opportunity to add a &lsquo;product&rsquo; retro after the teams retros, and a &lsquo;product&rsquo; planning just before the teams plannings. We were hoping that regular higher level retros would bring continuous improvement at the product scale and bring in all the other practices required to make it work.</p>

<h3>The situation now</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s now been 2 sprints that we have set this up. Every 2 weeks, Friday is what we call Demo-Day. It&rsquo;s a meeting heavy day where all the teams have their scrum ceremonies together</p>

<ul>
<li>Product demo</li>
<li>Team retros</li>
<li>Product retro</li>
<li>Product planning</li>
<li>Team planning</li>
</ul>


<p>Sure as hell, 1 day of meetings is exhausting, but unfortunately, it is not possible to efficiently grow a team without increasing the communication overhead. The good side of the coin is that it allows the teams to focus on building valuable stuff during the 9 other days.</p>

<p>Here are the first effects we have seen.</p>

<h4>Improved team spirit &amp; product focus</h4>

<p>The first noticeable effect was on team spirit. Having a demo and planning for the whole team showed to everyone that we are all pulling towards the same goal. It helped everyone to understand what his current role is in this greater scheme, but also ways to tweak our individual roles to bring more value.</p>

<h4>Visible problems</h4>

<p>The second good effect is that problems are now visible. If teams are not working in the same direction, it&rsquo;s visible at the demo and plannings. If a team delivers a story too late for another one to integrated it, it&rsquo;s again visible at demo and planning.</p>

<p>Another example : after the product planning, Product Managers had to admit that they had not managed to feed high value stories to all teams. They asked to do a pre-planning preparation meeting (which is a standard practice in <a href="https://less.works">LeSS</a> for example)</p>

<h4>Better continuous improvement</h4>

<p>During our first team retro in this setting, we directly stumbled upon on a recurring systemic issue that we never managed to do anything about. Instead of going around in circle on the topic again, we pushed it to the product retro. We worked on another team related problem, for which we scheduled improvement actions.</p>

<p>During the product retro, we raised our recurring unsolved issue. With everyone in place, people higher in the organization had the chance to understand its consequences. Eventually, we managed to come up with concrete actions.</p>

<h2>How to do it</h2>

<h3>Pre-requisites</h3>

<p>There&rsquo;s only one thing required : that the teams are already following Scrum. All the rest is easy stuff.</p>

<p>This technique is a bottom-up agile adoption. If you want to switch your whole company from waterfall to something more agile, take a look at <a href="http://www.scaledagileframework.com/">SAFe</a>.</p>

<h3>Organizing the Demo-Day</h3>

<p>Here is our planning for our demo day</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th> Time </th>
<th> Meeting </th>
<th> Who </th>
<th> Details </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> 10h &ndash; 12h </td>
<td> Demo </td>
<td> Everyone </td>
<td> 30m per team |</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> 12h30 &ndash; 14h </td>
<td> Team Retro </td>
<td> Teams </td>
<td> Every team has a different retro in a different room |</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> 14h30 &ndash; 15h30 </td>
<td> Product Retro </td>
<td> Scrum master, volunteers, and decision makers </td>
<td> Decision makers are important to be able to take actions |</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> 16h &ndash; 17h </td>
<td> Product Planning </td>
<td> Product managers or owners, volunteers </td>
<td> Product people present what they would like to see in the product in one sprint |</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td> 17h &ndash; 18h </td>
<td> Team Planning </td>
<td> Teams </td>
<td> Every team has a different planning in a different room |</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>We had to negotiate a bit with other people in the company to get enough rooms for all these meetings at the same time, but all in all, it did not take more than 2 hours.</p>

<p>All meetings are open to anyone, everyone should have the right to come to any of them !</p>

<p>Obviously, that&rsquo;s a long day ! It&rsquo;s also full of team energy. In 2 sprints, we found the following improvements :</p>

<h4>Food</h4>

<p>We pre-order food to be delivered at work, so that we can all eat together. Did you know that food makes retros more efficient ?</p>

<h4>Product Retro</h4>

<p>You might have noticed that the product retro is only 1 hour long. To make it all fit in one day, we had to cut some time here and there &hellip; In order to gain some time on the product retro, we decided to pre-fill its &lsquo;gather data&rsquo; phase.</p>

<p>During team retros, if people find product scale issues, they can directly save them for the product retro items (As we are distributed, we use <a href="/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">Trello for retrospectives</a>). This way, when the product retro starts, the gather data phase is almost done, pre-filled with genuine points.</p>

<h4>Keep the energy high</h4>

<p>One full day of meetings is long. People get tired. In order to keep the energy high and the overall experience fun, we deliberately added some fun throughout the day :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/category/energizer/">Energizers</a> at beginning of meetings</li>
<li>Board games during breaks</li>
<li>End of day celebration outside the office. You could go out and have a drink all together for exemple.</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Asmodee-TIM01USASM-Timeline/dp/B005N57CNU/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1493870547&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=timeline"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-02-a-straightforward-way-to-scale-to-more-than-1-scrum-team/timeline.jpg" alt="The Timeline board game box" /></a><div class="image-credits">We had fun playing this game between the meetings</div></p>

<h3>Preparing the product Backlog</h3>

<p>Depending on your situation, you might (or not) have a prioritized product backlog. My advice is to start with what you have.</p>

<p>If you are scaling your single team to 2, keep a unique backlog for both teams and create 2 feature teams. You&rsquo;ll be heading to the <a href="https://less.works">LeSS</a> organization, which you&rsquo;ll be able to refer to.</p>

<p>If you are applying this on existing scrum teams with their own backlogs, it might be easier to create a product backlog for the product managers. This is more akin to what <a href="http://www.scaledagileframework.com/">SAFe</a> suggests. It&rsquo;s not as straightforward as having a single backlog for everyone, you&rsquo;ll need to add some links between team and product stories to be able to track progress. Nevertheless, it provides visibility to everyone. As a side note, this is what we actually did.</p>

<p>Keep in mind that it&rsquo;s only a starting point anyway, product retrospectives might transform all this down the road any way.</p>

<h3>Start where you are now !</h3>

<p>The most important thing to do is to start ! There are always a ton of reasons why things are not ready and need more preparation. Remember the agile principles : integrate early and often, adapt, experiment &hellip; Here are few examples of bad reasons  not to start</p>

<ul>
<li>You cannot get all the good people in the room : start, invite them anyway, and send them a report of what has been decided without them. I cannot promise that&rsquo;s it&rsquo;s going to work at the end, but at least, it will create some discussions</li>
<li>The product backlog is not ready : start, and see what happens ! It will make it clear to everyone that product backlog is super important. People will organize to provide enough product features next sprint.</li>
<li>You need some other regular meetings for X, Y or Z. For example, <a href="https://www.agilealliance.org/glossary/scrum-of-scrums/">Scrum of Scrum</a> has daily SoS Meetings. Start anyway, if there&rsquo;s a need, people will ask for these extra meetings, which will save you some goodwill. You might also discover that you don&rsquo;t need these meetings at all and save some time !</li>
</ul>


<p>With a product retrospective every sprint, important issues will get addressed !</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-05-02-a-straightforward-way-to-scale-to-more-than-1-scrum-team/just-do-it.jpg" alt="Just Do It" /></p>

<h2>Does &lsquo;Agile Scaling&rsquo; even exist ?</h2>

<p>We did this on 4 teams. I have no ideas how it would work with more teams. We did not use any framework, even though we took ideas here and there. What we really did is to follow the agile principles, for example :</p>

<ul>
<li>KISS</li>
<li>Do the simplest thing that could work</li>
<li>Baby steps</li>
<li>Continuous improvement</li>
<li>Experiment</li>
</ul>


<p>Others have noticed similar things :</p>

<ul>
<li>LeSS : <a href="https://less.works/less/framework/introduction.html">&ldquo;Truly scaled scrum is Scrum scaled.&rdquo;</a></li>
<li>In the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nature-Software-Development-Simple-Valuable/dp/1941222374/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1493870372&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+nature+of+software+development">Nature of Software</a> <a href="http://ronjeffries.com/">Ron Jeffries</a> explains that for a company is agile if it just focuses on delivering software &ldquo;feature by feature&rdquo;</li>
<li>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Practical-Approach-Large-Scale-Agile-Development/dp/0321821726/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1493870423&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=large+scale+hp">A Practical Approach to Large-Scale Agile Development [&hellip;]</a>, the authors explain that they did not use any frameworks at HP, but just followed the agile principles</li>
</ul>


<p>Agile scaling frameworks might be a good starting point (the Shu in <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shuhari">Shu-Ha-Ri</a>), but only as long as the agile principles and values have not been understood by the organization.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How we introduced efficient agile retrospectives]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-introduced-efficient-agile-retrospectives/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-22T06:13:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-introduced-efficient-agile-retrospectives</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>6 months ago, our team started to run systematic iteration retrospectives. Within these 6 months, our team became more agile than ever. Running efficient retrospectives is what makes good teams great, it is what truly makes a team agile. Here is our story.</p>

<p>At the begining, we started with a standard retrospective format inspired from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Agile-Development-James-Shore/dp/0596527675/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1398141097&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+agile+development">The Art Of Agile Development</a> (A truly great book by the way). As I was used to running retrospectives, I did the first one. This is how it goes :</p>

<ul>
<li>Repeat Norm&rsquo;s Kerth&rsquo;s prime directive to everyone (5 minutes) :</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>Regardless of what we discover today, we understand and truly believe that everyone did the best job they could, given what they knew at the time, their skills and abilities, the resources available, and the situation at hand.</p></blockquote>

<p>If the message is awkward, the animator can explain that the point is to avoid counter productive blaming (even if it is unlikely to happen in your setting &hellip;)</p>

<ul>
<li>Do some kind of brainstorming (10 minutes) :</li>
</ul>


<p>One his own, everyone writes what went well on green post-its, and what did not went so well on blue post-its. Everybody sticks them up on the flipchart.</p>

<ul>
<li>Group insights togethers (15 minutes) :</li>
</ul>


<p>The animator reads every post-it aloud, asking team members for details, and tries to group notes together. When everyone is ok with the groups, dot vote : every team member gets 3 points, that he can assign as he wishes on any group. Here is what the board should look like at this point.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-04-22-how-we-introduced-efficient-agile-retrospectives/insights.jpg" title="Photo of the flipchart with gathered insights" ></p>

<ul>
<li>Find actions to improve the process (30 minutes) :</li>
</ul>


<p>Pick up the 3 most voted issues, give everyone 5 minutes to think of useful actions to fix these. Then take another 5 minutes so that people can discuss their solutions in pairs, and another 5 minutes to do the same in groups of 4. Eventually, as the animator reports on the flipchart, do the same altogether. Make sure that the solutions are <strong>doable</strong> within the next sprint, if not discuss and split them until they are. Again, dot vote for the prefered actions.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-04-22-how-we-introduced-efficient-agile-retrospectives/actions.jpg" title="Photo of the flipchart with agreed actions" ></p>

<ul>
<li>Do it :</li>
</ul>


<p>As soon as the retrospective is finished, the animator must enter the actions in the coming sprint backlog. These actions are not user stories, but they <strong>must</strong> be done. If there are not, the team cannot be agile as they will be no continuous improvement. Don&rsquo;t assign any story points to these items, but let the velocity auto adjust for a given amount of improvements during every sprint.</p>

<p>After the first one, every team member animated such a retrospective, one after the other. When everyone was at ease with this, we changed the format. We bought <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Agile-Retrospectives-Making-Teams-Great/dp/0977616649/ref=pd_sim_b_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;refRID=0QA643CPNSQE9E0GSG5E">Agile Retrospectives: Making Good Teams Great</a> and everyone was responsible for designing his own retrospective session when his turn came. This allows different and various insights.</p>

<p>To conclude, here are a few retrospectives hints and guidelines</p>

<ul>
<li>Everyone&rsquo;s voice should be equal, everyone should feel free to talk</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t worry if good ideas are not selected the first time, they&rsquo;ll come back</li>
<li>At the begining of every retrospective, review what happened about what was decided during the previous one</li>
<li>Use sticky flipcharts and stick them on the wall as you go through the different activities</li>
<li>Prepare flipcharts in advances to make the retrospective run more smoothly</li>
<li>Use colored post its to highlight different aspects (good things, bad things or whatever)</li>
<li>Use markers to write on post its (how can one read it from the back of the room otherwise ?)</li>
</ul>


<p>If you haven&rsquo;t yet, you have no excuses not to start now !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sprints are not sprints]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/sprints-are-not-sprints/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T06:22:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/sprints-are-not-sprints</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I really don&rsquo;t know why <a href="http://www.scrum.org">Scrum</a> Sprints are called sprints ! From my experience, the number one mistake made by team starting with Scrum is to work as quickly and dirty as possible to complete the sprint, forgetting the <a href="http://www.sustainablepace.net/">sustainable pace</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-01-07-sprints-are-not-sprints/marathoner-vs-retail-sprinter.jpg" title="Side by side photos of a marathoner and a sprinter" ></p>

<p>Finding another word is difficult though, I thought of &lsquo;stage&rsquo; or &lsquo;milestone&rsquo; that both convey the long run idea, but both feel more content than time bounded. A more exotic word could be a &lsquo;Scrum push&rsquo;, it conveys slow and intense action action rather than quick results.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/1a/ST_vs_Gloucester_-_Match_-_23.JPG/640px-ST_vs_Gloucester_-_Match_-_23.JPG">http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/1a/ST_vs_Gloucester_-_Match_-_23.JPG/640px-ST_vs_Gloucester_-_Match_-_23.JPG</a>" title="A rugby scrum (Wikimedia)" ></p>

<p>Overall, the traditional agile &lsquo;iteration&rsquo; is not bad at all, at least a lot better than Sprint.</p>

<p><strong>EDIT 01/08/2014:</strong></p>

<p>The &lsquo;Quick and Dirty&rsquo; Sprint strategy, is like trying to win a marathon with a greedy algorithm:</p>

<p><code>ruby
while not finished
  sprint(100m)
end
</code></p>

<p>Not likely to work &hellip; Marathoners know that they&rsquo;ve got to stick to a constant speed during the whole race in order to finish it. The way to get faster is to :</p>

<ul>
<li>increase this cruise speed just a bit</li>
<li>get at ease with it during a few races</li>
<li>repeat</li>
</ul>


<p>Is there something to learn from this to improve software development speed ?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
