<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: complexity | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/complexity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-11T17:37:46+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Software is like writing and revising a giant book]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/software-is-like-writing-and-revising-a-giant-book/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-23T03:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/software-is-like-writing-and-revising-a-giant-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With time, I discovered a way of explaining the subtleties of my developer job to my uninformed relatives and friends.</p>

<p>Sharing what your developer job is about with others can be very frustrating. Some people think you are &ldquo;Just playing around with computers&rdquo; as if it was not serious work. Others think that it is an extremely Cartesian and solitary activity with no place for communication or creativity. Trying to explain the diversity and richness of a developer&rsquo;s work is often a disappointing experience.</p>

<h2>The book metaphor</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-23-software-is-like-writing-and-revising-a-giant-book/book.jpg" title="An old book" ></p>

<p>I explain to people that writing software is not unlike writing a huge book. A book long many millions of lines. I explain that the challenge is to maintain the whole story of the book coherent. I stress how difficult this is given that no one can take the time to read the full book, that the authors come and go, and that the book is under constant heavy revision.</p>

<h2>Details of our work</h2>

<p>The metaphor is quite valid and even holds about more subtle aspects of our work. Here is a summary of the last discussion I had about the book metaphor :</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>(Him) Do you have some &lsquo;gatekeepers&rsquo; for different sections of the story to make sure that these parts remain coherent ?</li>
<li>(Me) That&rsquo;s what we would call strong code ownership, this was the norm 20 years ago, but that the industry is moving to more collective code ownership, in order to decrease the bus factor.</li>
<li>(Him) What is the bus factor ?</li>
<li>(Me) The number of person who need to be hit by a bus to block your development progress</li>
<li>(Him) I see, that&rsquo;s kind of funny. But then, does that mean that any developer can change any part of the code ? Isn&rsquo;t that dangerous ?</li>
<li>(Me) Sure that would be difficult, that&rsquo;s not really how we do it. We make a lot of efforts to split the big story in many smaller independent ones as much as possible. This way, teams specialize on different &lsquo;chapters&rsquo; and work collectively within it.</li>
<li>(Him) I see</li>
<li>(Me) And if you need to change something in another &lsquo;chapter&rsquo; you should ask the guys who know it better to help you.</li>
<li>(Him) That makes sense. And what happens if two developers want to modify the same part of the story at the same time</li>
<li>(Me) That can happen. People might even want to modify the story in conflicting ways ! We&rsquo;ve got tools, processes and best practices to minimize this. If nothing is done, we&rsquo;ll get what we call a &lsquo;merge conflict&rsquo;.</li>
<li>(Him) Ho &hellip; I wouldn&rsquo;t have guessed, but it seems collaboration is really important in your work, isn&rsquo;t it ?</li>
<li>(Me) Sure it is !</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<h2>We are software writers</h2>

<p>All this reminds me of DHH&rsquo;s talk about writing software :</p>

<iframe class="center" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9LfmrkyP81M" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Programming as an exponential problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/programming-as-an-exponential-problem/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-21T06:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/programming-as-an-exponential-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As said Tom Cargill</p>

<blockquote><p>The first 90% of the code accounts for the first 90% of the development time. The remaining 10% of the code accounts for the other 90% of the development time.</p></blockquote>

<p>By extrapolation, this would mean that every time we increase the requirements by 10%, we need to double the total development time ! That would mean that solution complexity is an exponential function of the complexity of the problem.</p>

<p>That could explain why techniques that work well for small problems don&rsquo;t work well at all for large problems, and vice et versa. For example</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center"> In the small (think one page script) </th>
<th align="center"> In the large (think multi millions lines system)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center"> Dynamic typing                       </td>
<td align="center"> Static typing</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"> Mutable globals                      </td>
<td align="center"> Immutability</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"> Imperative style                     </td>
<td align="center"> Declarative style</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"> Manual memory management             </td>
<td align="center"> Garbage collection</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"> Shared memory                        </td>
<td align="center"> Message passing</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<br/>


<p>Just for fun, let&rsquo;s suppose that we could deduce a unique constant C for every language such that</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-02-21-programming-as-an-exponential-problem/formula.png" title="Secret formula linking problem and solution complexities" ></p>

<p>Here is a plot of this formula with different values of C (0.5, 1 and 2)</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-02-21-programming-as-an-exponential-problem/close-plot.png" title="Plot of the formula for different C constant values" ></p>

<p>We can see that small values of C are best for small problems, whereas greater values are evolve better with larger problems. For a given problem, there is quite a difference in the solution complexity, if the formula was true, and that we knew in which zone of complexity our problem will always be, we could choose the appropriate technology ! Experienced engineers already have the gut knowledge about how to chose the right tool for the job !</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s not all, let&rsquo;s have a bird&rsquo;s eye view of the same formulas</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-02-21-programming-as-an-exponential-problem/wide-plot.png" title="Same plot at a larger scale" ></p>

<p>I increased the maximum problem complexity by a factor of 3, I had to multiply the solution complexity by 100 ! In the end, these exponential curves all seem frighteningly vertical. This could explain why the divide and conquer approach works so well in software : 2e<sup>x</sup> &lt; e<sup>2x</sup>. Abstract and powerful APIs might be our best weapon against complexity.</p>

<p>People behaviour does not match this exponential hypothesis though :</p>

<ul>
<li>At work, I&rsquo;ve seen quite a few projects started from scratch, and everybody expecting it to maintain it&rsquo;s initial speed during its whole lifetime</li>
<li>Some recent hiring or investing trend seem to rely on hackathons, startup week ends, or coding games, all &lsquo;in the small&rsquo; exercises</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ve observed in quick and dirty overtime work to meet a deadline &hellip; If productivity is proportional to the solution complexity, that crunch mode would be completely unproductive</li>
</ul>


<p>This leads to more interesting questions :</p>

<ul>
<li>Is my exponential model complete garbage ?</li>
<li>Or are humans particularly bad at forecasting an exponential behaviour ?</li>
<li>If so, what practices could we adopt to stop relying on this misleading gut feeling ?</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
