<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: workplace | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/workplace/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-12T06:32:53+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Lego Office Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-lego-office-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-20T05:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-lego-office-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rome wasn&rsquo;t built in a day, neither will be your Lego Office &hellip; This week is Devoxx in Paris, for the occasion, we decided to stream a <a href="/recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/">Lego office</a> experiment that my team did.</p>

<h2>What are Lego Offices</h2>

<p>I wrote about Lego office in a previous post, as a concept and a set of material that would allow teams to easily configure their workspaces as they wish. At that time, I thought of :</p>

<ul>
<li>laptops</li>
<li>extra monitors</li>
<li>tables and chairs on wheels</li>
<li>movable walls</li>
<li>movable white boards</li>
<li>movable wall screens</li>
<li>a good Wifi</li>
</ul>


<h2>Our experiment</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/empty-meeting-area.jpg" title="Meeting area in the empty office" >
<img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/empty-work-area.jpg" title="Work area in the empty office" ></p>

<p>The last floor of our building in Paris has a nice (really) open space area with rolling tables that we could use. We moved all the team there for one week. As we don&rsquo;t have laptops with Wifi, we simply asked for enough power and network plugs.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/setup-work-area.jpg" title="Setup work area" >
<img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/setup-meeting-area.jpg" title="Setup meeting area" >
<img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/setup-rest-area.jpg" title="Setup rest area" ></p>

<p>The place is large enough to have dedicated rest and meeting space. We managed to create a visio setup using our build monitor. We even had a remote lunch once, which we should repeat more often !</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s missing</h2>

<p>Obviously, this was a quick experiment, nothing like a fully architectured Lego workspace, still it helped us to discover issues and blocking points. It turns out that cables <em>are</em> an issue !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/cables.jpg" title="Cables on the floor" ></p>

<p>After getting some feedback throughout the company, it turns out that some developers would never trade their high end connected desktop workstation for a Wifi laptop. Our C++ build can be pretty CPU and network intensive &hellip; I guess that means that a real Lego office might require one of the following :</p>

<ul>
<li>A technical floor with all the place required to bring any kind of cables to your machine</li>
<li>Powerful servers in a data center to do the grunt work for you</li>
<li>Single cable machines (Apple&rsquo;s USB-C is the only one I can think of right now)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Last minute question</h2>

<p>Thinking of it &hellip; could different remote offices such as your home, or a co-working space be considered as Lego blocks ?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Recipes For An Agile Workspace]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-17T06:40:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/recipes-for-an-agile-workspace</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nowadays, start-ups and tech companies seem to be competing for the most beautiful offices in order to attract top talents.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-02-17-recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/open-space.jpg" title="A nice modern and beautiful co-working space" ></p>

<p>Unfortunately, sometimes, it&rsquo;s just the good old office in disguise. At the opposite, some teams or companies actually think and decide how to organize their offices. For example, here is what <a href="https://twitter.com/kentbeck">Kent Beck</a> says about office setup in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0201616416/ref=sr_1_2?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1456177035&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=extreme+programming+embrace+change">XP embrace change</a></p>

<blockquote><p>If you don&rsquo;t have a reasonable place to work, your project won&rsquo;t be successful. The difference
between a good space for the team and a bad space for the team is immediate and dramatic.</p></blockquote>

<p>Joel Spolsky has been blogging a lot about the office setups at <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/BionicOffice.html">FogBugz</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/BionicOffice.html"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-02-17-recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/fog-bugz.jpg" title="The beautiful FogBugz office" ></a></p>

<p>While defining its agile culture, <a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/JoakimSunden/agile-at-spotify">Spotify too designed custom offices</a></p>

<p><a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/JoakimSunden/agile-at-spotify"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-02-17-recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/spotify.jpg" title="Spotify offices" ></a></p>

<h2>How does it work ?</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s review a few office design practices to understand how they work :</p>

<h3>The team room or space</h3>

<p>Having a delimited room helps to build a real team. First, by isolating from noises, it helps the team to focus on its work and current topics. Second, by providing a visual barrier to cross before anyone can disturb the team. Finally, it allows the team to organize its own visual management.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-02-17-recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/spotify-team-room.jpg" title="Team private work place at spotify" ></p>

<h3>Private team gathering area</h3>

<p>An area where the team (and only the team) can meet at any time is great to do on the spot meetings (without the hassle of finding a room). This area should be comfortable and provide a relaxed and creative atmosphere (which is very important to conduct efficient retrospectives). It can also be used to take breaks and lunches, fostering team spirit again.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-02-17-recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/spotify-gathering-area.jpg" title="Team gathering area with writable walls and a wall screen at spotify" ></p>

<h3>Writable walls</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s pretty easy to cover the walls with whiteboard stickers so that there is plenty of room for discussing design and otherwise keeping important things visible for everyone.</p>

<h3>Laptops, Wifi and movable desks</h3>

<p>Lean manufacturing favors simple, versatile and configurable machines over powerful specialised ones, which are often pretty long to setup. In software, we don&rsquo;t rely on machines as much as factories do, but there might be something to take here. Using laptops, a good Wifi and movable desks, it is pretty easy to reconfigure your office as it best fits the team at a particular moment. This way a team can easily adapt to personal preferences and turnover.</p>

<h3>Wall screens</h3>

<p>Agile and Lean thinkings both heavily use visual management. Having a lot of wall screens dedicated to displaying team relevant information in the team space brings a lot of value. To get the maximum benefit, these wall screens should be fully configurable and movable by the team.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-02-17-recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/wall-screens.jpg" title="Our own wall screens at work" ></p>

<h3>Team budget</h3>

<p>Eventually, in order to make sure the team can always work as efficiently as possible, it should have some money to spend for its workspace. It could be used to buy any of the upper, but also anything else that might help the team at a particular point in time. Without such a budget, teams have to make a request to the office department to get anything, often to no avail, or with extra long delays.</p>

<h2>Distributed teams</h2>

<p>Distributed teams bring their own challenges &hellip; and workplaces needs.</p>

<h3>Remote team space</h3>

<p>If your team is split between 2 places (as our team is at <a href="http://www.murex.com">Murex</a>) then obviously, each site should have its own delimited space, with its own gathering area.</p>

<h3>Constant visio connection</h3>

<p>Connecting gathering areas through visio is a great way to build the distributed team. It prevents loosing time when a meeting is required. It also builds the team by showing what&rsquo;s happening on the other side and by making it possible to take distributed lunches and breaks !</p>

<p><a href="http://www.infoq.com/presentations/distributed-team-agile"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-02-17-recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/distributed-lunch.jpg" title="A team sharing food remotely between offices" ></a></p>

<h3>Distributed whiteboards</h3>

<p>I never had the chance to work with one of these, but I often missed a whiteboard when working remotely &hellip; Any input on this subject would be welcome !</p>

<h2>Lego offices</h2>

<p>Here is another extract from Kent Beck&rsquo;s &ldquo;XP Embrace Change&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>The courage value finds its expression in the XP attitude toward facilities. If the corporate attitude
toward facilities is at odds with the team&rsquo;s attitude, the team wins. If the computers are in the
wrong place, they are moved. If the partitions are in the way, they are taken down. If the lights are
too bright, they are taken out. If the phones are too loud, one day, mysteriously, they are all found
to have cotton stuffed in the bells.</p></blockquote>

<p>Improving the office is a cheap way to make a software organization more efficient. For another reference, here is what Tom DeMarco &amp; Tim Lister wrote in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321934113/ref=s9_simh_gw_g14_i3_r?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;pf_rd_m=ATVPDKIKX0DER&amp;pf_rd_s=desktop-1&amp;pf_rd_r=1K2KEWBRQK6F1R26D5D2&amp;pf_rd_t=36701&amp;pf_rd_p=2079475242&amp;pf_rd_i=desktop">Peopleware</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Police-mentality planners design workplaces the way they would design prisons: optimized for containment at minimal cost. We have unthinkingly yielded to them on the subject of workplace
design, yet for most organizations with productivity problems, there is no more fruitful area for improvement than the workplace. As long as workers are crowded into noisy, sterile, disruptive space, it&rsquo;s not worth improving anything but the <strong>workplace</strong>.</p></blockquote>

<p>Instead of designing offices, furniture departments in companies could provide a constant stock of building blocks for office building. Teams could use a workplace budget to build the workspace that suits them most. A good Wifi, laptops, enough floor power plugs, extra screens, movable tables, movable walls and easy to fix wall monitors are all things that would make this possible.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-02-17-recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/lego-office.jpg" title="A miniature office in Legos" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How We Started Exploratory Testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-started-exploratory-testing/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-08T18:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-started-exploratory-testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Manual testing is important. Here is how we got to love exploratory testing.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-01-08-how-we-started-exploratory-testing/explore.jpg" title="A map and a telescope for exploration" ></p>

<h2>Initial situation</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.murex.com">At work</a> we are building a risk computation engine for the financial markets. It uses a DSL to describe the exact computations to estimate the risk on the data it knows. This in itself is already complex enough to justify the heavy investment in automated testing we did.</p>

<p>With 90% of automated test coverage, Cucumber scenarios to verify quality, everything should just work &hellip; shouldn&rsquo;t it ?</p>

<h2>First try at exploratory testing</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Art-Agile-Development-James-Shore/dp/0596527675/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1452279644&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+agile+development"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-01-08-how-we-started-exploratory-testing/art-of-agile-development.jpg" title="The cover of the Art Of Agile Development" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Art-Agile-Development-James-Shore/dp/0596527675/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1452279644&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+agile+development">The art of agile development</a>, James Shore details the practice of exploratory testing as a great way of both :</p>

<ul>
<li>improving the quality of the product by finding bugs</li>
<li>improving the process</li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s why we gave it a try. Here is the recipe for an exploratory session :</p>

<ol>
<li>Book 1 hour for the full team to do exploratory testing</li>
<li>Prepare a downloadable zip with all the material required to run and test your software</li>
<li>Ask everyone to pick a particular aspect of the system to test during this session</li>
<li>Record bugs when you find one</li>
<li>Spend 30 minutes just after the session to filter duplicate bugs and make sure they are well described</li>
</ol>


<p>Obviously, we also added our special sauce</p>

<ol>
<li>We were to do exploratory testing in pairs, as we do programming, to find more bugs</li>
<li>We gamified it by granting a price to the pair that finds the most bugs. Do you remember how I brought <a href="/how-to-setup-a-weekly-fruit-basket-in-no-time/">fruits for sale in the office</a> ? It turns out we are slowly earning money with the fruits &hellip; enough for the price to be 5 fruits each for the wining pair !</li>
</ol>


<p>This transformed developers into ferocious testers ! I guarantee that with such incentives you&rsquo;ll find bugs &hellip; as we did.</p>

<p><a href="/how-to-setup-a-weekly-fruit-basket-in-no-time/"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-01-08-how-we-started-exploratory-testing/fruits-basket.jpg" title="Our weekly fruit basket at work" ></a></p>

<h2>Doing it systematically</h2>

<p>We took some time to fix all these bugs during a few sprints. And did another exploratory testing session a few months after &hellip;</p>

<p>As we were still finding bugs in the second session, we decided to make them part of the every sprint. As we got better at testing, a lot of bugs started to get uncovered ! So much that we had to change something.</p>

<h2>Improving our process</h2>

<p>We meet in retrospective and here is what we decided :</p>

<ol>
<li>Fix all bugs before working on any other story (obviously, automated tests are added in the process)</li>
<li>Classify what exactly is a bug. For example, for us, a bug is something that used to work or silently returns bad results or corrupts the data</li>
<li>Add exploratory testing by another pair to our definition of done</li>
</ol>


<p>The number of bugs we find during exploratory testing sessions is starting to decrease. We hope that we&rsquo;ll soon be able to do exploratory testing on the fly, as part of our daily work and to completely remove the specific sessions.</p>

<h2>Benefits</h2>

<p>Exploratory testing brought us a lot.</p>

<ul>
<li>Obviously, the product is a lot more solid</li>
<li>We are surely saving time that would have been lost if the bugs had been uncovered by the users</li>
<li>Fixing the bugs forced us to fix some technical debt : bugs often came from areas of the code that we were not so proud or confident of</li>
</ul>


<p>Exploratory testing is a nobrainer. All teams should do it.</p>

<p>So, in the end, as in the old days, we are back to regular manual testing &hellip; but only for exploration.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Great Developers Are Free]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/great-developers-are-free/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-31T12:24:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/great-developers-are-free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For many reasons. But mostly because they are key to efficiently growing a software organization.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-12-31-great-developers-are-free/cat-codes-for-food.jpg" title="A funny picture sleeping on a keyboard, with the mention &lsquo;Will code for food&rsquo;" ></p>

<h2>A tale of 2 teams</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s have a look at 2 software teams in the world of corporate finance.</p>

<h3>The junior in-house team</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.lefigaro.fr/emploi/2013/12/07/09005-20131207ARTFIG00309-bruit-temperature-air8230-les-salaries-reserves-sur-l-open-space.php"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-12-31-great-developers-are-free/open-space.jpg" title="A big corporate open space" ></a></p>

<p>One is an in-house software development team in a large bank. The project already has a bad reputation among developers.The bank has difficulties to hire so the team is constituted of 10 rather junior developers. Unfortunately, without guidance and long term vision, the quality of the code suffers. It looks like an ad-hoc composition of various technolgies, glue code, and reinvented frameworks. The overall result is a barely good enough product that costs a small fortune in maintainance and support. The user experience is awful, which make it difficult to the the team leaders and the users to collaborate effectively. As a result of all this, the project is suffering from high turnover. Managing this project is really challenging &hellip; and kind of depressing.</p>

<h3>The experienced software team</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.personalized-software.ie/aboutus"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-12-31-great-developers-are-free/experienced-team.jpg" title="An experienced software team" ></a></p>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s imagine the same product developed at a software house. It&rsquo;s been on the market for a while now, but new features are regularly added to it at a good pace. The product is solid and the users are happy using it. The structure of the team is completely different : 5 developers, mainly experienced, coming from various backgrounds. As a result, the team builds on all their different expertises to build real competitive advantages. They tend to get into healthy debates about a lot of things, such as :</p>

<ul>
<li>Should we re-use or re-write ?</li>
<li>Is this gold plating or plain technical debt ?</li>
<li>Which technology should we use to build this ?</li>
</ul>


<p>In the end, that makes the product even better. The humane side of the team is also completely different. These experienced developers have all been exposed to the big picture during their careers, and they know things like :</p>

<ul>
<li>&lsquo;Business talk&rsquo; and so they can discuss product topics with the product managers</li>
<li>The best way to go through chores at work is to do them right now</li>
<li>Enough management, testing, ops to make the team self organized</li>
</ul>


<p>The single junior developer in the team tends to mimic this model, and has ease finding mentors, to teach him their trade and to give him career counsels.</p>

<p>As a result, the product and the team remain healthy, and keep providing benefits to all stakeholders.</p>

<h2>Benefits of experienced teams</h2>

<p>First, from a purely short term financial point of view, it&rsquo;s a no brainer ! Even if you pay experienced developers twice as much as juniors, the costs will still be on par. But the difference in created value is huge !</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s then have a look at the longer term, organizational aspect of things. Obviously, managing such teams requires a lot less work ! Both because of their size and because experienced developers tends to manage themselves very well &hellip; Promoting self-organized &amp; cross-functionnal teams is a great opportunity to reduce the management cost and friction, making the organization more reactive and cost efficient in the long run.</p>

<h2>What is an experienced developer ?</h2>

<p>Obviously, I&rsquo;ve worked with people that were experienced on paper, but not in practice. I <a href="http://www.jrothman.com/htp/interview/2004/12/whats-a-year-of-experience/">read</a> that repeating 10 times the same year of work only amounts to 1 year of experience.</p>

<p>If I was asked to give a definition, I&rsquo;d say that experienced developers have worked on different kind of systems (embeded, web, client, server &hellip;) using different technologies (Java, Ruby, C, Spring, Rails, Javascript &hellip;). Their experiences need not be professional, I&rsquo;ve seen a physics teacher that hacked himself into a great hacker through side projects and open source. Speaking of the subject, good developers always spent a lot of time learning, reading, doing side projects and contributing to open source. Some can be found in local user groups and online programming communities.</p>

<h2>So How do you get them ?</h2>

<p>I can only think of 3 obvious ways :</p>

<ul>
<li>train them</li>
<li>keep them</li>
<li>hire them</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m pretty sure training them will not be an issue if you already have enough of them. So that brings us to the 2 other points.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.prestashop.com/blog/en/guided-visit-prestashops-new-paris-headquarters/"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-12-31-great-developers-are-free/prestashop.jpg" title="The prestashop offices in Paris" ></a></p>

<p>Lot&rsquo;s of articles have been written about attracting and keeping the best developers. Some companies even made it <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/HighNotes.html">their differentiating point</a>. Here are a few links :</p>

<ul>
<li>In his post <a href="http://avc.com/2012/02/the-management-team-guest-post-from-joel-spolsky/">&ldquo;The Management Team&rdquo;</a> Joel Splosky details the inverted pyramid model</li>
<li>Joel Spolsky&rsquo;s (again) <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/DevelopmentAbstraction.html">Development Abstraction Layer</a> explains all the physical environment that makes programmers happy at work</li>
<li><a href="http://qz.com/169147/applications-have-doubled-to-the-company-that-discloses-its-salaries/">After disclosing employee salaries, Buffer was inundated with resumes</a> when <a href="http::/www.buffer.com">buffer.com</a> publicly disclosed <a href="https://open.buffer.com/introducing-open-salaries-at-buffer-including-our-transparent-formula-and-all-individual-salaries/">their salary formula</a>, the number of applications the company received doubled</li>
<li>Spotify organizes <a href="https://labs.spotify.com/2013/02/15/organizing-a-hack-week/">Hack Weeks</a> where  the company stops for a while to invent new things</li>
<li>Google summarizes it &ldquo;Do Cool Things That Matters&rdquo; in their long advertises <a href="http://www.google.com/about/careers/lifeatgoogle/">Life At Google</a></li>
</ul>


<p>These are just a few examples and are by no way the only things that motivate developers. To summarize, provide the best working conditions (careful, that not money), and communicate a lot about it.</p>

<h2>Hiring is too important to be left to HR</h2>

<p><a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/">Jurgen Appelo</a> said</p>

<blockquote><p>Management is too important to be left to managers.</p></blockquote>

<p>I guess the same thing can be said about hiring.</p>

<p>Engineers are absolutely required to take the main role when hiring other engineers. Companies that seriously want to have the best developers on board are spending substantial engineering time on hiring. Here are some well known examples :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.google.com/about/careers/lifeatgoogle/hiringprocess/">Google</a> is known to conduct around 9 interviews before hiring someone</li>
<li>In its <a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf">Handbook for New Employee</a> Valve explicitly states that hiring is your most important role</li>
</ul>


<h2>Endword</h2>

<p>As <a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Tom_DeMarco">Tom DeMarco</a> said about quality, in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Peopleware-Productive-Projects-Teams-3rd/dp/0321934113/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1451733851&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=peopleware">Peopleware</a> :</p>

<blockquote><p>Great developers are free, but only for those who are willing to pay for them</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to setup a weekly fruit basket in no time]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-setup-a-weekly-fruit-basket-in-no-time/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-17T07:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-setup-a-weekly-fruit-basket-in-no-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.groupe-patus.fr/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/07-Beautiful-Fruit-Wallpapers.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-12-17-how-to-setup-a-weekly-fruit-basket-in-no-time/fruit.jpg" title="&ldquo;A multi-fruit sandwich&rdquo;" ></a></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in agile software development, just read Kent Beck&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/B00CF6EJG8/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1417609208&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=embrace+change+1st+edition">Extreme Programming Explained : Embrace Change 1st edition</a>. It&rsquo;s only 200 pages, it was written in 1999, but it&rsquo;s still tremendously relevent, and it&rsquo;s got the highest ratio of information per page on the subject.</p>

<p>If you actually read it, you&rsquo;ll notice that Kent emphasizes about having food at the office. He claims that it improves the moral and builds team cohesion.</p>

<p>As my company already provides free drinks, my first attempt was to asked for weekly fresh fruits baskets. They are currently experimenting regular self service fruit baskets deliveries in some offices. Unfortunately not in ours yet. Let&rsquo;s hope it changes soon. Meanwhile, we decided to handle the thing ourselves.</p>

<h2>Here comes the fruit basket lean startup !</h2>

<h3>First, let&rsquo;s setup the simplest way it could possibly work</h3>

<ul>
<li>Invest 10€</li>
<li>Buy some fruits from the closest shop</li>
<li>Put them in a basket next to my desk</li>
<li>Let people buy them for 50c each</li>
<li>Leave a plastic cup next to the basket to receive the money</li>
<li>Hold the accounting public and visible in your wiki for example</li>
<li>Repeat every monday</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-12-17-how-to-setup-a-weekly-fruit-basket-in-no-time/fruits-basket.jpg" title="&ldquo;Our fruit basket at my desk&rdquo;" ></p>

<h3>Then, verify that it is sustainable</h3>

<p>It turns out it works fine !</p>

<h3>&hellip; Until someone started to steal some money !</h3>

<p>If we forgot to hide the money cup before we left in the evening, obvious isn&rsquo;t it ?
We tried the following, in that order :</p>

<ol>
<li>Setup an automatic reminder to hide the money before leaving &hellip; FAIL</li>
<li>Setup a fake webcam and a warning notice &hellip; FAIL</li>
<li>Only keep 1€ worth of change in the money cup, and repeatedly lock up the rest in a safe place &hellip; SUCCESS !</li>
</ol>


<p>With just a bit of time, anyone, anywhere can setup a fresh fruit basket at work. It does improve the moral and build the team.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
