<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jira | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/jira/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-24T06:28:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bye Bye Programmer's TODO List, Hello Personnal Kanban on Jira]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-17T05:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not long ago, I wrote that <a href="/real-programmers-have-todo-lists/">Real Programmers have TODO lists</a> &hellip; I was wrong, I now work without a TODO list ! So either I&rsquo;m not a real programmer anymore, or I&rsquo;m actually using TODO List v.2.0. Read on !</p>

<h2>Motivations</h2>

<p>My work has become quite varied lately. On top of programming and pairing, I am also doing quite some coaching within the team. For the whole Murex programmers community, I&rsquo;m organizing <a href="https://github.com/murex/murex-coding-dojo">Coding Dojos</a>, <a href="http://www.brownbaglunch.fr/">Brown Bag Lunches</a> and Technical Talk Video Sessions. Finaly, like all of us, I have to cope with my share of organization overhead.</p>

<p>Multitasking was starting to kill me. I was feeling exhausted at the end of the day, with the certainty that I was not getting much done &hellip;</p>

<h2>Personnal Kanban To The Rescue</h2>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban">Kanban</a> is a method to organize your work relying on <a href="http://www.personalkanban.com/pk/featured/why-limit-work-in-progress/#sthash.QFI0D8l5.dpbs">Work In Progress limits</a> : it minimizes multitasking and encourages prioritization.</p>

<p>As its name suggests it, <a href="http://personalkanban.com">Personal Kanban</a> is simply applying Kanban to your own tasks. It turns out that :</p>

<ul>
<li>My team tasks are already in <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira">JIRA</a></li>
<li>Some guys have already tried to <a href="https://jira.atlassian.com/browse/JRA-13472">use JIRA as a todo list</a></li>
<li>JIRA supports Kanban boards with WIP limits and all</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Kanban Board</h2>

<p>In our team, <a href="http://bilal.eltayara.net">TAYARA Bilal</a> had already experimented the approach and asked to JIRA admins to create us a custom project for our todo lists. I piggybacked on it and created my own kanban board. Here is what it looks like.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-08-17-bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/board.png" title="Screenshot of the full JIRA board" ></p>

<h3>Mixing Project Stories And Personnal Tasks</h3>

<p>JIRA allows creating a kanban board that spans many projects ! You can simply choose multiple projects when you setup the board for the first time, or you can edit your board filter like this :</p>

<p><code>sql
project in (POPIMDB, POPABTODO) ...
</code></p>

<p>This makes it possible to see <em>all</em> of my work at a glance on the same board.</p>

<h3>Work In Progress Limit</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-08-17-bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/wip.png" title="Zoom on the wip constraints of the JIRA column" ></p>

<p>JIRA allows WIP limits, warning me with a red background when I am multitasking or when I am getting late on my tasks</p>

<h3>Color Conventions</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-08-17-bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/color-cards.png" title="Different colors of JIRA cards" ></p>

<p>JIRA makes it possible to assign different colors to cards, for example</p>

<ul>
<li>Red for tasks that are due soon</li>
<li>orange for cards that are due some time</li>
<li>light brown for project stories</li>
<li>green for other programming tasks</li>
<li>blue for other tasks</li>
</ul>


<h3>Swimlanes</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-08-17-bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/swimlanes.png" title="Closup on a JIRA swimlane" ></p>

<p>JIRA has swimlanes, separating project from personal tasks</p>

<h3>Reports</h3>

<p>An extra bonus with JIRA Kanban board is that they have reports ! Here is my cumulative flow diagram for my first week of usage :</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-08-17-bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/cumulative-flow.png" title="A screenshot of the JIRA cumulative flow diagram" ></p>

<h3>Configuration</h3>

<p>Here is the JQL query I used to configure it this way.</p>

<p>```sql
&mdash; board filter
project in (POPIMDB, POPABTODO) AND (Assignee = pbourgau OR Co-Assignees in (pbourgau) OR mentors in (pbourgau)) AND (status != CLOSED OR updated >= -1d) ORDER BY Rank ASC</p>

<p>&mdash; Swimlanes
priority = &ldquo;1-Very High&rdquo; &mdash; Expedite
project in (&ldquo;POP IMDB&rdquo;) and (labels not in (SLACK) OR labels is EMPTY) &mdash; IMDB Stories
&mdash; and a blank filter for Other Tasks</p>

<p>&mdash; Card Colours
duedate &lt;= 7d or priority = &ldquo;1-Very High&rdquo; &mdash; red
duedate is not EMPTY &mdash; orange
labels in (SLACK) &mdash; green
type = Task &mdash; blue
&mdash; and an empty filter for light brown
```</p>

<h2>The End Result</h2>

<p>By setting a WIP limit of 3 on the &ldquo;In Progress&rdquo; column, the following naturally happened :</p>

<ul>
<li>Once I have started a programming task, I now defer any other activity in the TODO column until I am finished. (HINT: If you get invited to meetings all the time, lock your agenda with &lsquo;Unbookable&rsquo; days when you start programming)</li>
<li>It actually pushed me into finishing the <a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata">concurrency-kata</a> training I had started long ago.</li>
</ul>


<p>I also set a high WIP limit (around 10) on the TODO column, this way, I get a kind of warning that next time I finish a programming task, I should take some time off to prune the column.</p>

<p>The overall result is that I do lot less multitasking. I get the feeling of doing steadier, more efficient work.</p>

<p>If you are suffering from multitasking and decide to give it a try, I&rsquo;d love to read about your experience !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
