<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: first-improvement-kata-series | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/first-improvement-kata-series/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-15T07:00:21+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How we used the improvement kata to gain 25% of productivity - Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-12T09:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/">previous post</a>, I described the productivity issue our team was facing. How retrospectives did not work, and how I started looking at the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">improvement kata</a>.</p>

<p>We had gone through the first phase of the improvement kata : set the end goal.</p>

<blockquote><p>Generating enough profit for the business while sticking to a sustainable pace.</p></blockquote>

<p>Time to start the second phase : Understand.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/question-light.jpeg" alt="Drawing of a question mark transforming into a light bulb" /></p>

<h2>Understand</h2>

<p>Where we really slower ? Or was it an illusion ?</p>

<p>When trying to understand, you have to start with the data you have. You continue digging until you get a deeper understanding of the situation.</p>

<h3>Velocity</h3>

<p>We started with available data : story points and velocity. For sure this is a pretty bad measure of productivity. (Note : we should never use velocity for performance appraisal) In our case though, it felt like a good starting proxy measure.</p>

<p>Here is our velocity curve over 2 years.</p>

<p><a href="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity.jpg"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity-small.jpg" alt="Velocity vs Manpower graph" /></a></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s obvious that something changed. There are 2 parts to this graph. The velocity dropped between sprint 54 and 16.01. That&rsquo;s a clue that our gut feeling was not completely wrong. Our productivity did change.</p>

<h3>Man days</h3>

<p>Our first hypothesis was that team members turnover was the cause. As with any team, some people came, and some people left. Let&rsquo;s superpose the man days and velocity curves.</p>

<p><a href="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity-vs-manpower.jpg"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity-vs-manpower-small.jpg" alt="Velocity vs Manpower graph" /></a></p>

<p>That could only explain <em>part</em> of the problem !</p>

<p>We tried to fine tune the man days curve. We took people&rsquo;s involvement in tasks outside of programming into account. We used coefficients depending on the developers' experience. That did not provide a better explanation.</p>

<p>We had to find another explanation.</p>

<h3>Velocity computation</h3>

<p>As I said earlier, velocity is not a measure of productivity. Any change in the way we were computing velocity would impact this curve.</p>

<p>We had kept photos and Trello boards of our <a href="/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">retrospectives meetings</a>. We searched them through for anything that could impact velocity. Here is what we found :</p>

<ul>
<li>At sprint 55, we decided to ditch the <a href="https://www.scrum.org/resources/deadly-disease-focus-factor">focus-factor</a></li>
<li>At sprint 61, we started to do regular <a href="/how-we-started-exploratory-testing/">exploratory-testing</a>. Exploratory testing discovers more bugs on top of user reported bugs. This made us spend more time on fixing bugs.</li>
<li>At sprint 62, as we opted for a <a href="https://medium.com/quality-functions/the-zero-bug-policy-b0bd987be684">No Bug policy</a> we decided not to count story points for bugs</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>💡Keep Photos and Trello boards of Retrospectives as a log of your working agreements changes</p></blockquote>

<p>The timings almost perfectly matched what we had observed in the first place. The question that came to our minds was :</p>

<blockquote><p>Are we spending too much time on bugs ?</p></blockquote>

<h2>Halfway through understanding</h2>

<p>This is how we started to dig into our situation. It&rsquo;s a good time to give you a bit of feedback about how we felt at that point.</p>

<p>It was the first time we tried the improvement kata. More than that, we did not find any tutorial or guides about how to run it. The only instructions we had were theoretical descriptions or super concrete examples. We had to bridge the gap and come up with our own way.</p>

<p>To summarize, we felt a bit lost, we had gathered data from here and there, and we did not know what to look at next. On top of that, the quality of the data we were collecting was not great. We were wondering if we would get anything out of these investigations.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/First-20-Hours-Learn-Anything/dp/1591846943/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1483258282&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+first+20+hours"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/the-first-20-hours.jpg" alt="The cover of the book 'The First 20 Hours'" /></a></p>

<p>It felt a bit like when I did the <a href="/how-i-got-my-feet-wet-with-machine-learning-with-the-first-20-hours/">20 hours experiment to learn anything</a>. We did exactly what had worked with the learning experiment : we pushed through !</p>

<blockquote><p>💡If you feel lost when doing something for the first time. Push through !</p></blockquote>

<p>In next week&rsquo;s post, I&rsquo;ll continue to detail the &lsquo;understand&rsquo; phase. <a href="/blog/categories/first-improvement-kata-series/">The series</a> also gained an extra post, and will now be 5 posts long.</p>

<p>See you next week.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How we used the improvement kata to gain 25% of productivity - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-07T06:39:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are serious about continuous improvement, you should learn the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">improvement kata</a>.</p>

<p><a href="/blog/categories/retrospectives/">Retrospectives</a> are great to pick all the low hanging improvements. Once you&rsquo;ve caught up with the industry&rsquo;s best practices, retrospectives risk drying up. Untapped improvement opportunities likely still exist in your specific context. The improvement kata can find those.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-09-07-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/low-hanging-fruits.jpeg" alt="Low and high hangling fruits on a tree" /></p>

<p>Here is how we applied the improvement kata to gain 25% of productivity in my previous team.</p>

<h2>The Situation</h2>

<p>Thanks to repeated retrospectives, the team had been improving for 2 years. Retrospectives seemed like a silver bullet. We would discuss the current problems, grasp an underlying cause and pick a best practice. Most of the time, that fixed the problem.</p>

<p>Sometimes it did not work though. Even if the issue came back in a later retrospective, it would not survive a second scrutiny. In the previous two years, the team had transformed the way it worked. It adopted TDD, incremental refactoring, pair programming, remote work, automated performance testing and many others.</p>

<p>Lately though, things did not work so well. The team was struggling with productivity issues. The team was not slowing down, but the scope and complexity of the product had grown. Features were not getting out of the door as fast as they used to. We had the habit of prioritizing improvements and bug fixes over features. That used to improve the flow enough to get more and more feature done. It did not seem to work anymore.</p>

<p>We tried to tackle the issue in retrospectives. We would change the way we prioritized features &hellip; To be later bogged down by bugs, technical debt or bad tools. We would discuss that in retrospective, and decide to change the priorities again &hellip; The loop went on and on a few times.</p>

<p>We were getting nowhere.</p>

<h2>The improvement kata </h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s why I started to look for other ways to do continuous improvement. I stumbled upon a book called <a href="http://leanagilecamp.fr/">Small Lean Management Guide for Agile Teams</a>. The book is in french, but I wrote an <a href="/are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way/">english review</a>. I fell in love with the way the authors dug into the hard data of how they worked to understand and fix their problems.</p>

<p>To learn more about this technique, I read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Toyota-Kata-Managing-Improvement-Adaptiveness/dp/0071635238/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1504758735&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=toyota+kata">Toyota Kata</a>. It details two management tools used at Toyota : the improvement and coaching katas. Some say these are Toyota&rsquo;s special weapon. <em>The</em> thing that grew them from a small shop to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automotive_industry">largest car manufacturer in the world</a>.</p>

<p>They are katas because they are routines. They must be re-execute many times. The <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">improvement kata</a> should improve the flow of work. The <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Coaching_Kata.html">coaching kata</a> helps someone (or yourself) to learn the improvement kata. Every time we go through the kata, we also understand it better.</p>

<p>Here is how the improvement kata goes :</p>

<ol>
<li>Describe your end goal</li>
<li>Understand where you stand about this goal by measuring facts and data</li>
<li>Based on your end goal and the current situation, define where you&rsquo;d like to be in 3 months or less</li>
<li>Use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDCA">Plan-Do-Check-Act</a> to experiment your way to this new situation

<ol>
<li>Plan an experiment</li>
<li>Do this experiment</li>
<li>Check the results of this experiment</li>
<li>Act on these results. 

<ul>
<li>Either drop the experiment and plan a new one (go back to &lsquo;Plan&rsquo;).</li>
<li>Or spread the change at a larger scale.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>


<p><a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/Homepage.html"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-07-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/katapattern.jpg" alt="The Improvement Kata Pattern" /></a><div class="image-credits">Image from Mike Rother on <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/Homepage.html">Toyota Kata Website</a></div></p>

<p>The coaching kata is a way to coach someone into applying the improvement kata. The fun thing is that you can coach yourself ! The idea is to ask questions to the coachee to remind him of where he stands in his improvement kata.</p>

<p><a href="https://traccsolution.com/resources/coaching-infographic/"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-07-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/The-coaching-Kata-questions.jpg" alt="The Coaching Kata Questions" /></a></p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll find tons of details and material about these katas on the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/Homepage.html">Toyota Kata website</a>.</p>

<h2>Our end goal</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s how I started to apply the improvement kata in my team. I already had an idea of our end goal : to be more productive. To be more precise :</p>

<blockquote><p>Generating enough profit for the business while sticking to a sustainable pace.</p></blockquote>

<p>Retrospectives could not get us there. Would the improvement kata would succeed ?</p>

<p>This is the first part of a <a href="/blog/categories/first-improvement-kata-series/">series of 4 posts</a> relating our first use of the improvement kata. In the <a href="/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/">next post</a>, I&rsquo;ll explain what we did to understand the current situation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
