<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: refactoring | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/refactoring/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-05T05:57:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When the Boy Scout Rule Fails]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-02T05:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-02-when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/boy-scout-rule.jpg" title="An illustration of the boy scout rule" ></p>

<p>Here goes the <a href="http://programmer.97things.oreilly.com/wiki/index.php/The_Boy_Scout_Rule">boy scout rule</a> :</p>

<blockquote><p>Always check a module in cleaner than when you checked it out.</p></blockquote>

<p>Unfortunately, this alone does not guarantee to keep the technical debt under control. What can we do then ?</p>

<h2>Why the boy scout rule is not enough</h2>

<p>I can easily think of a few issues that are not covered by the boy scout rule.</p>

<h3>It only deals with local problems</h3>

<p>In it&rsquo;s statement, the boy scout rule is local and does not address large scale design or architecture issues. Applying the boy scout rule keeps files well written, using with clear and understandable code. From a larger perspective though, it does very little or slow improvement to the overall design.</p>

<p>These large scale refactorings are very difficult to deal with using the boy scout rule alone. It could be done but would require to share the refactoring goal with all the team, and then track its progress, while at the same time dealing with all the other subjects of the project. That&rsquo;s starting to sound like multitasking to me.</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;s skill dependent</h3>

<p>Another point about the boy scout rule (and to be fair, about any refactoring technique) is that programmers will be able to clean the code only as much as their skills allow them to !</p>

<p>Imagine what would happen when a new master developer arrives in a team of juniors, he&rsquo;d spot a lot of technical debt and would suggest improvements and ways to clean the code. Code that was thought of as very clean would suddenly be downgraded to junk !</p>

<p>The point here is that the boy scout rule cannot guarantee that you have no technical debt, because you don&rsquo;t know how much you have !</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s where the debt metaphor reaches its limits and flips to some productivity investment. By investing time to perform some newly discovered refactoring, you could get a productivity boost !</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470200818&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-02-when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/ddd.jpg" title="The cover of &ldquo;Domain Driven Design&rdquo;" ></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470200818&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design">Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software</a>, Eric Evans calls this knowledge distillation. He means that little by little, the team gains better understanding of the domain, sometimes going through what he calls a &lsquo;breakthrough&rsquo;. These breakthroughs often promote existing code to technical debt &hellip;</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;s context dependent</h3>

<p>Developers alone are not the only one responsible for creating technical debt. Changes to the environment also do.</p>

<p>For example, if the market conditions change, and that new expectations for the product are slowly becoming the norm, your old perfectly working system becomes legacy and technical debt. As an example, let&rsquo;s examine what happened to the capital markets software industry in response to the 2008 crisis.</p>

<ul>
<li>The sector became a lot more regulated</li>
<li>Risk control is moving from nightly batches to real time</li>
<li>The demand for complex (and risky) contracts decreased</li>
<li>As a consequence, trading on simpler contracts exploded</li>
</ul>


<p>All these elements combined invalidated existing architectures !</p>

<p>New technologies also create technical debt. Think the switch from mainframe to the web.</p>

<h2>What do we need then ?</h2>

<p>Should we stop using the boy scout rule ? Surely not, it would be a total non-sense. Submitting clean and readable code is a must.</p>

<p>But it is not enough. If you have spotted some large scale refactoring that could bring some improvement, we should do what a fund manager would do :</p>

<ol>
<li>Estimate the return on investment</li>
<li>If it is good enough, do it now</li>
</ol>


<p>Obviously, large refactorings should also be split into smaller <del>value adding</del> cost reducing items. But then what ?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nature-Software-Development-Simple-Valuable/dp/1941222374/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470290668&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+nature+of+software+development"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-02-when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/nature-of-software.jpg" title="The cover of &ldquo;The Nature of Software Development&rdquo;" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nature-Software-Development-Simple-Valuable/dp/1941222374/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470290668&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+nature+of+software+development">The Nature of Software Development</a> Ron Jefferies says that we need a unique value-based prioritization strategy for everything, including technical improvements. Once you&rsquo;ve got that, there&rsquo;s no sense in splitting and embedding your refactoring in other tasks, this will just increase your work in progress, reducing your throughput and cycle time.</p>

<p>Frankly, I think that&rsquo;s easier said than done. I can <em>think</em> of two ways :</p>

<ul>
<li>As Ron Jefferies tends to say, have a jelled-cross-functional team discuss and prioritize collectively</li>
<li>As <a href="http://reinertsenassociates.com/technical-debt-adding-math-metaphor/">Don Reintersen</a> advocates, use an <a href="/a-plan-for-technical-debt-lean-software-development-part-7/">economical framework</a> to estimate the return on investment</li>
</ul>


<p>At least that&rsquo;s a starting point !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Refactoring trick to insert a wrapper]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/refactoring-trick-to-insert-a-wrapper/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-30T08:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/refactoring-trick-to-insert-a-wrapper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week at work, we decided that we needed an <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/909264/ddd-anti-corruption-layer-how-to">Anticorruption Layer</a> between our code and another team&rsquo;s. They have been using our internal data structures as they needed to, in an ad hoc way. This turned out to be an issue when we want to refactor our code. The goals of this layer are :</p>

<ul>
<li>to provide an explicit API layer, controlling what is accessible from the outside</li>
<li>to allow us to improve our implementation independently of this API</li>
</ul>


<p>The first step all the team aggreed on is to provide direct wrappers around our classes. Unfortunately, some of these classes had more than a thousand references to it and our IDE does not provide any automated refactoring for this (introduce a wrapper class, and only use it in some part of the code). We found a trick ! Here it is :</p>

<ol>
<li>Make sure you have a clean SCC state</li>
<li>Rename the class to be wrapped (let&rsquo;s call it Foo) into FooWrapper</li>
<li>From SCC, revert the part of the code where you want to continue using Foo directly</li>
<li>In SCC, revert Foo and FooWrapper</li>
<li>Manually (re)create the FooWrapper class</li>
<li>Create FooWrapper.wrap(x) and FooWrapper.unwrap(x) methods</li>
<li>Fix all the compilation issues (mostly by calling wrap() and unwrap())</li>
<li>Run your tests and fix any remaining points</li>
</ol>


<p>That saved us a whole lot of time. If your layer contains several classes with references between them, they is an optimal order through which to introduce the wrappers. Any order will work, but some will require more temporary calls to wrap and unwrap (step 7.). At the end, wrap() and unwrap() methods should only be called from within the layer.</p>

<p>Often you&rsquo;ll find out that to complete the wrapping of a class, you&rsquo;ll first need to wrap another class, you can :</p>

<ul>
<li>Follow the mikado method strictly : upgrade your mikado graph, revert all your changes, and try to wrap this other class. It can seem slow, but it is completly incremental</li>
<li>Wrap the 2 classes at the same time : this is the best way when wrapping this other class is rather straightforward</li>
<li>Insert temporary calls to wrap() and unwrap() : they&rsquo;ll be removed when you&rsquo;ll later wrap the other class. This might be the only way if the classes have cyclic dependencies.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
