<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: business value | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/business-value/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-06-28T06:06:12+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Dream Lean Software Development Tool (Lean Software Development part 9)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-14T20:49:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Current software project tracking tools suck !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-12-14-my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9/it-sucks.jpg" title="A stamp that writes &ldquo;SUCKS&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>By writing <a href="/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/">this series of posts</a>, I realized that they should help us to prioritize rather than just serving as a nice GUIs on top of a ticket database.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take the story of developer Joe as an example. Joe is working for Megacorp, where he makes a good living, but feels like a small cog in the machine. He has lost the thrill of programming &hellip; He&rsquo;s still staying informed about latest trends in software world, but his job involves aging technologies. He knows that if he wants to remain in the course, he has to change gears. One day, he decides to do something <em>now</em>, and starts a side project in the hope of someday making a living out of it.</p>

<p>He does not have a large amount of money to invest in his project, so he decides to bootstrap his product using <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/">Lean Startup</a>. He reads and understands that there is a lot of different kind of activities to do if he wants to realize his dream : experiments, marketing, sales, design, coding &hellip;</p>

<p>Unfortunately, he&rsquo;s so tired of programming boring stuff that he contracted the developer bias : he starves to code cool things again ! He knows the rest is important, he tries to do some of it, but he just doesn&rsquo;t realize how <em>much</em> needs to be done. So, without realising it, he wastes a lot of time coding something that people eventually don&rsquo;t buy. After 1 or 2 years of hard work, a working product but no users, he eventually quits, quite depressed &hellip;</p>

<p>I guess you don&rsquo;t want to be Joe ! I know you&rsquo;ll think it won&rsquo;t happen to you &hellip; believe me, it can, <a href="rip-mes-courses-dot-fr/">I learned it the hard way</a> !</p>

<p>Now suppose you had a tool that estimates the expected values of all different tasks :</p>

<ul>
<li>By applying <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monte_Carlo_method">Monte Carlo simulations</a> to probabilistic value and size ranges, it could compute which features we should work on first. As a side effect, this could give us some release date estimates for a feature, depending on its position in the backlog.</li>
<li>By having explicit experiment tasks with target value or size ranges, it could compute the value of information and prioritize experiments versus other tasks.</li>
<li>Crossing informations from IDEs, VCS, Quality Trackers and CIs, it could detect technical debt items (aka. productivity opportunities), compute their values in the long run, and prioritize them with other tasks.</li>
<li>If we found a way to integrate marketing, sales and design tasks, any kind of activity could be stored in the backlog, valued and prioritized.</li>
</ul>


<p>Here is what the backlog could look like :</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-12-14-my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9/mockup.jpg" title="A mockup of the backlog view of such a product" ></p>

<p>All different kind of activities (developments, marketing, experiments, refactorings) would fit in the backlog. The system would estimate the value of every task for Joe, advising him what to work on first. It would make it obvious just how much market experiments are important when starting ! With such a tool, he is a lot more likely to build his new life.</p>

<p>The good thing with such a tool is that it could be built by feeding itself. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eating_your_own_dog_food">Eating its own dog&rsquo;s food</a> has always been the nice thing about writing software tools.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to know, what do you think of the idea ? Would you use such a tool ? Is it worth me spending my nights building it ?</p>

<p>This was 9th and last part of my <a href="/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/">suite of article about Lean Software Development</a>, Part 8 was <a href="/how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/">How I&rsquo;ll Measure the Lean Startup Value of Information in My Next Side Project</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I'll measure the lean startup value of information in my next side project (Lean Software Development Part 8)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-07T21:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There must be a way to know the real money value of <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/">Lean Startup</a> &lsquo;knowledge&rsquo;.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-12-07-how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/knowledge-money.jpg" title="A brain or some money ?" ></p>

<p>Lean Startup is about gathering &lsquo;knowledge&rsquo; through experiments instead of building things. <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Principles-Product-Development-Flow-Generation/dp/1935401009/ref=sr_1_3?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1450068976&amp;sr=8-3&amp;keywords=lean+product+development">Flow book</a> suggests that the value of an information is its expected impact on the bottom line. So by combining both, there should be a way to compute a quantitative value for the knowledge.</p>

<p>The overall plan would be :</p>

<ol>
<li>Start with a rough business plan, but assume that all that&rsquo;s in it has got 1 chance out of 10 of being right</li>
<li>Design experiments to precise the likelyhood of what&rsquo;s in the business plan</li>
<li>Compute the value of each experiment as the difference of the expected bottom line after and before running it (This should be possible if relying on the business plan for other parameters)</li>
<li>Work on the task with the highest expected value, be it an experiment, a development, a sales task, or whatever</li>
<li>Adapt you business plan with any new information</li>
<li>Repeat</li>
<li>If it becomes obvious that the expected final earnings are too low, pivot</li>
</ol>


<p>Flow explains that all the principles are pretty robust to bad inputs and errors. In short, the final estimations of earnings are still a lot better than without using any specific method. In the case of Lean Startup, it means that a false business plan is a good enough starting point.</p>

<h2>How to assess the likelyhood of a figure ?</h2>

<p>By default let&rsquo;s assume the value of a feature is somewhere between 0 and your highest estimate. As we&rsquo;ll go through experiments we&rsquo;ll be able to narrow this value range and have a more accurate estimate for the real value.</p>

<p>To keep things simple we could assume that the probability of value is uniformaly distributed within this range. From what I read in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Waltzing-Bears-Managing-Software-Projects/dp/0932633609/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1449901015&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=waltzing+with+bears">Waltzing With Bears</a>, here would be a more realistic probability distribution.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-12-07-how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/Demarco-probability.png" title="The curve of the probability of value according to DeMarco" ></p>

<h2>How to estimate the value of an experiment ?</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to go into the details here, because the logic is exactly the same as with technical experiments (which <a href="/measure-the-business-value-of-your-spikes-and-take-high-payoff-risks-lean-software-development-part-4/">I already wrote about</a>)</p>

<p>Since then though, I read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Waltzing-Bears-Managing-Software-Projects/dp/0932633609/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1449901015&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=waltzing+with+bears">Waltzing With Bears</a> which presents a way of doing Monte Carlo simulations in order to estimate risks on your project. I guess the same thing could be used for value, which would save us from a lot of complex math.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Waltzing-Bears-Managing-Software-Projects/dp/0932633609/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1449901015&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=waltzing+with+bears"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-12-07-how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/waltzing-with-bears.jpg" title="Cover of &lsquo;Waltzing With Bears&rsquo;" ></a></p>

<h2>When to stop doing experiments ?</h2>

<p>Isn&rsquo;t all this overkill ? One could argue that the point of Lean Startup should be to build just enough knowledge ! In fact, this value of information concept naturaly helps to find out when running the experiment is not worth it compared to actually doing the real thing.</p>

<p>BTW, a tool doing all this for your automaticaly would be great, wouldn&rsquo;t it ?</p>

<h2>What I&rsquo;ll do for my next bootstrap side project</h2>

<ol>
<li>Start with a target hourly earning rate.</li>
<li>Collect a list of projects I&rsquo;d be interested in.</li>
<li>Pick a project and write a business goal for it.</li>
<li>Assign likelyhoods and ranges on every figure in the business plan.</li>
<li>Design experiments to improve the figures.</li>
<li>Create tasks to actually build and sell the product.</li>
<li>Compute values for each of these tasks.</li>
<li>Work the most valueable first.</li>
<li>If the figures prove that I will not make my target wage with this project, I&rsquo;ll pivot, and restart from 2.</li>
<li>Otherwise, I&rsquo;ll repeat from 4.</li>
</ol>


<p>This was part 8 of my <a href="/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/">suite of article about Lean Software Development</a>, Part 7 was <a href="/a-plan-for-technical-debt-lean-software-development-part-7/">A Plan for Technical Debt</a>, Part 9 will be <a href="/my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9/">My Dream Lean Software Development Tool</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
