<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: business value | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/business-value/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-10-04T06:13:00+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making the business case for a large scale refactoring - Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-27T19:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>How to improve a factual business case for a refactoring to make it even more compelling to business people.</em> </p>

<p>In last post, I explained how to make a business case for a large scale refactoring using real numbers. Numbers are great, but they won&rsquo;t get us sponsorship by themselves. We need to understand them. We need to make sure they make sense. We need to make sure they are backing our refactoring up. In the end, we might need to improve them.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-09-18-making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-2/refactoring-trim-teaser.jpeg" alt="Drawing of a hammer removing the G from refactoring written with stones. Trimming a refactoring is an effective way to increase its value, and make the business case better." /></p>

<p>This is the thirteenth post in a <a href="/blog/categories/large-scale-refactoring-sponsorship-series/">series about how to get sponsorship for large scale refactorings</a>. If you haven&rsquo;t, I encourage you to start from <a href="/how-to-convince-your-business-to-sponsor-a-large-scale-refactoring/">the beginning</a>.</p>

<h2>What If Payback Period is too long?</h2>

<p>If payback period is close enough, then great, we can go out and pitch the refactoring. Most of the time though, large scale refactorings take quite some time to payback.</p>

<h3>Product Life Expectancy</h3>

<p>The first thing to do is to put this in the perspective of the company&rsquo;s or product&rsquo;s life expectancy. Imagine a product which is 10 years old and expected to cash-in for another 10 years. In this context, a refactoring that pays for itself in 1 year <em>is</em> a great opportunity!</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 The longer the life expectancy of your product, the more refactoring you should invest in!</p></blockquote>

<p>Picking the age of the product as its life expectancy is realistic most of the time. New products have low life expectancy, but legacy systems seem to last forever!</p>

<h3>Split the refactoring!</h3>

<p>A strategy to reduce the payback period is to split this large scale refactoring. Can we make it smaller, more focused, or find sub steps that pay for themselves faster? Here again, <a href="/blog/categories/incremental-software-development/">incremental refactoring techniques</a> will be critical.</p>

<h3>Did we do an error?</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s also possible that we did an error in the business case computation. Sampling and logging are error-prone techniques.</p>

<p>Is the iteration we took for sample is representative enough of the future work ? In doubt, we can re-do the sampling or the computation. Using better data leads to a better conclusion.</p>

<p>There are also other costs we did not take into account to be able to stick to man.hours. Let&rsquo;s have a look at these.</p>

<h2>Ideas for Improvements</h2>

<h3>Convert to Money</h3>

<p>If we have access to money numbers, we should be able to improve the figures with new costs.</p>

<p>First, we&rsquo;ll need the average wage of team members to convert our figures in real money.</p>

<p>If we have the figure, we can add the image cost of a bug to the non-refactoring cost.</p>

<p>Finally, if we have the revenue per feature, we can add the opportunity cost to the refactoring cost. Opportunity cost is the cost of not working on features !</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-09-18-making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-2/money.jpg" alt="Stacks of coins. If we have access to the good figures, it is possible to make the business case for large scale refactoring with real money instead of man.hours." /></p>

<h3>Use a similar refactoring</h3>

<p>Did someone do a similar refactoring in the past? If so, we can use it to improve your estimates about:</p>

<ul>
<li>Refactoring time</li>
<li>Productivity improvement</li>
<li>Time saved on bugs and support.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Is it a good idea in the end?</h3>

<p>Are the numbers still arguing against the refactoring? Maybe it&rsquo;s not such a great idea afterwards &hellip; We ought not to argue for something of dubious value, our credibility is at stake.</p>

<p>At this point, it might be a good idea to look for another improvement to do. Maybe there is other code to refactor or a new productivity tool to build.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Avoiding bad moves is a key benefit of making a business case for large scale refactoring!</p></blockquote>

<h2>Other References</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m fond of this way of prioritizing software. It&rsquo;s the way out of bickering about best practices, and towards sustainable pace. If you want to learn more about this, here are 2 helpful references :</p>

<ul>
<li>A blog post <a href="https://www.scrum.org/resources/blog/making-tech-debt-visible">Making Technical Debt Visible</a> . It explains how to use the scrum sprint backlog to display the cost of technical debt.</li>
<li>A PluralSight course <a href="https://www.pluralsight.com/courses/making-business-case-for-best-practices">Making the Business Case for Best Practices</a>. It&rsquo;s just great. It contains a ton of practices to help us to get realistic numbers and estimates.</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-09-18-making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-2/making-the-business-case.jpg"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-09-18-making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-2/making-the-business-case-small.jpg" alt="Visual notes from the Plural Sight course &quot;Making the Business Case for Best Practices&quot;. It contains many techniques that can be used for large scale refactoring" /></a><div class="image-credits">Visual notes from <a href="https://www.pluralsight.com/courses/making-business-case-for-best-practices">Making the Business Case for Best Practices</a></div><br></p>

<h2>Next post</h2>

<p>This is the thirteenth post in a <a href="/blog/categories/large-scale-refactoring-sponsorship-series/">series about how to get sponsorship for large scale refactorings</a>. We&rsquo;re reaching the end ! In <a href="/become-a-business-partner-and-stop-begging-for-refactoring/">next week&rsquo;s post</a>, I&rsquo;ll go over Business Partnership. There are some practices we can put in place once we have earned the trust from business people. Stay tuned !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making the business case for a large scale refactoring - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-20T08:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>With a bit of discipline, we can make a factual business case for a large scale refactoring that business people won&rsquo;t resist.</em></p>

<p>The <a href="/presenting-a-large-scale-refactoring-as-a-business-opportunity/">previous 2 articles</a> were about how to present large scale refactorings to business people. This might already get us a lot closer to having our large scale refactoring prioritized. Unfortunately, many times this won&rsquo;t be enough. Hopefully, we can add something to make the point to business people : numbers !</p>

<p>Business people love numbers. Presented well, they make decisions a lot easier to take. Making a business case is about estimating the costs of doing versus not doing a refactoring.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-09-17-making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-1/legacy-vs-refactoring.jpg" alt="Drawing of legacy and a refactoring plan in a balance. Making a business case for a large scale refactoring is all about estimating the costs of both options" /></p>

<p>This is the twelfth post in a <a href="/blog/categories/large-scale-refactoring-sponsorship-series/">series about how to get sponsorship for large scale refactorings</a>. If you haven&rsquo;t, I encourage you to start from <a href="/how-to-convince-your-business-to-sponsor-a-large-scale-refactoring/">the beginning</a>.</p>

<h2>Before anything</h2>

<p>Before we start any computation, we need to know what we are talking about. This means that as a team, we must agree and specify enough the refactoring we want to do. A small group design session might be useful at this point.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 We must detail precisely what refactoring we want before making a business case for it.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Refactoring Cost</h2>

<p>We pay for a refactoring only once, when we do it. The cost of the refactoring is the time it will take to do it. We can do a team estimate on the refactoring and see the numbers.</p>

<p>From my experience large scale refactoring estimates are pretty inaccurate. If the team is having a hard time agreeing on estimates, it&rsquo;s a warning! Recipes against this are :</p>

<ul>
<li>Do a bit more design to better define the refactoring</li>
<li>Take a safety margin for your estimation. Times 2 is not a bad ratio to start with (cf. the risk management section of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Art-Agile-Development-Pragmatic-Software/dp/0596527675/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1536837799&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+agile">The Art of Agile</a>)</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Art-Agile-Development-Pragmatic-Software/dp/0596527675/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1536837799&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+agile"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-09-17-making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-1/art-of-agile.jpg" alt="Cover of the book The Art of Agile Development. It contains a chapter about risk management which can be useful to make realistic long term estimates of a large scale refactoring" /></a></p>

<p>Eventually, be sure to convert your estimates in man.hours. If you don&rsquo;t, it will be difficult to compare this with the non-refactoring cost.</p>

<h2>Non-Refactoring Cost</h2>

<p>Contrary to the previous one, this cost is recurring. We&rsquo;ll only compute it for a single period of time, let&rsquo;s say an iteration. It also works fine with a month, a week or whatever.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 The cost of not doing a refactoring is the sum of all the waste work generated by the current code.</p></blockquote>

<p>The non-refactoring can be computed like:</p>

<p><code>
non-refactoring cost = Bug fix time + Support time + Lower productivity
</code></p>

<h3>Bug fixes &amp; Support time</h3>

<p>Bad code generates bugs and support time. By doing the refactoring well, we&rsquo;ll almost kill these wasteful activities.</p>

<p>We want to get the real amount of time the team is spending on bug fixes and support time related to our refactoring. Hopefully, our ticketing software might already contain enough time tracking data. That&rsquo;s what I used when we did <a href="/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-3/">our improvement kata</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-09-17-making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-1/types-of-tasks-small.jpg" alt="Distribution of the different kind of tasks over sprints that we extracted from Jira when we did the improvement kata. Finding where the time went is useful when making a business case for a large scale refactoring" /></p>

<p>If not, we&rsquo;ll unfortunately need to do a bit of manual time tracking for a while. It should be fine to cover a few days, and extrapolate for a longer period. Unbelievably, some people made time tracking fun by <a href="https://code.joejag.com/2018/lego-workstream-visualisation.html">using Lego Blocks</a>!</p>

<p><a href="https://code.joejag.com/2018/lego-workstream-visualisation.html"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-09-17-making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-1/lego_1.jpg" alt="Joe Wright's team has had success logging time with lego blocks. Logging is time is crucial to estimate the non-refactoring cost when making a business plan" /></a><div class="image-credits">By <a href="https://twitter.com/vanschoo">Nancy Van Schooenderwoert</a></div><br></p>

<h3>Lower productivity</h3>

<p>Bad code also makes us slow! By doing this large scale refactoring, we should get a productivity boost.</p>

<p>Here again, we are only going to measure for an iteration, and extrapolate for the future. If we are working with iterations, we should have an &lsquo;estimation&rsquo; meeting of some sort. At the end of it, we should have selected a list of &lsquo;task&rsquo; for next iteration.</p>

<p>Next time you go through this meeting, we&rsquo;ll need to estimate these tasks twice.</p>

<ol>
<li>Do a normal estimation</li>
<li>Now, imagine we did the refactoring. Re-estimate.</li>
</ol>


<p>The difference between the estimates is the non-refactoring productivity loss.</p>

<p><code>
productivity loss = normal estimation - estimation after refactoring
</code></p>

<h2>Payback Period</h2>

<p>We need to convert everything in man.hours. We should now have figures for both total refactoring and recurring non-refactoring cost.</p>

<p><code>
payback period = refactoring cost / non-refactoring cost
</code></p>

<p>The payback period is the refactoring cost divided by the non-refactoring cost. It&rsquo;s the time after which the refactoring will pay for itself.</p>

<h2>To be continued</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;re done with computations. <a href="/making-the-business-case-for-a-large-scale-refactoring-part-2/">Next week</a>, I&rsquo;ll go over what to do with these numbers. We want to make business case for this large scale refactoring an unmissable offer!</p>

<p>This is the twelfth post in <a href="/blog/categories/large-scale-refactoring-sponsorship-series/">a series about how to get sponsorship for large scale refactorings</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Dream Lean Software Development Tool (Lean Software Development part 9)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-14T20:49:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Current software project tracking tools suck !</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2015-12-14-my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9/it-sucks.jpg" alt="A stamp that writes &quot;SUCKS&quot;" /></p>

<p>By writing <a href="/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/">this series of posts</a>, I realized that they should help us to prioritize rather than just serving as a nice GUIs on top of a ticket database.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take the story of developer Joe as an example. Joe is working for Megacorp, where he makes a good living, but feels like a small cog in the machine. He has lost the thrill of programming &hellip; He&rsquo;s still staying informed about latest trends in software world, but his job involves aging technologies. He knows that if he wants to remain in the course, he has to change gears. One day, he decides to do something <em>now</em>, and starts a side project in the hope of someday making a living out of it.</p>

<p>He does not have a large amount of money to invest in his project, so he decides to bootstrap his product using <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/">Lean Startup</a>. He reads and understands that there is a lot of different kind of activities to do if he wants to realize his dream : experiments, marketing, sales, design, coding &hellip;</p>

<p>Unfortunately, he&rsquo;s so tired of programming boring stuff that he contracted the developer bias : he starves to code cool things again ! He knows the rest is important, he tries to do some of it, but he just doesn&rsquo;t realize how <em>much</em> needs to be done. So, without realising it, he wastes a lot of time coding something that people eventually don&rsquo;t buy. After 1 or 2 years of hard work, a working product but no users, he eventually quits, quite depressed &hellip;</p>

<p>I guess you don&rsquo;t want to be Joe ! I know you&rsquo;ll think it won&rsquo;t happen to you &hellip; believe me, it can, <a href="rip-mes-courses-dot-fr/">I learned it the hard way</a> !</p>

<p>Now suppose you had a tool that estimates the expected values of all different tasks :</p>

<ul>
<li>By applying <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monte_Carlo_method">Monte Carlo simulations</a> to probabilistic value and size ranges, it could compute which features we should work on first. As a side effect, this could give us some release date estimates for a feature, depending on its position in the backlog.</li>
<li>By having explicit experiment tasks with target value or size ranges, it could compute the value of information and prioritize experiments versus other tasks.</li>
<li>Crossing informations from IDEs, VCS, Quality Trackers and CIs, it could detect technical debt items (aka. productivity opportunities), compute their values in the long run, and prioritize them with other tasks.</li>
<li>If we found a way to integrate marketing, sales and design tasks, any kind of activity could be stored in the backlog, valued and prioritized.</li>
</ul>


<p>Here is what the backlog could look like :</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2015-12-14-my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9/mockup.jpg" alt="A mockup of the backlog view of such a product" /></p>

<p>All different kind of activities (developments, marketing, experiments, refactorings) would fit in the backlog. The system would estimate the value of every task for Joe, advising him what to work on first. It would make it obvious just how much market experiments are important when starting ! With such a tool, he is a lot more likely to build his new life.</p>

<p>The good thing with such a tool is that it could be built by feeding itself. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eating_your_own_dog_food">Eating its own dog&rsquo;s food</a> has always been the nice thing about writing software tools.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to know, what do you think of the idea ? Would you use such a tool ? Is it worth me spending my nights building it ?</p>

<p>This was 9th and last part of my <a href="/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/">suite of article about Lean Software Development</a>, Part 8 was <a href="/how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/">How I&rsquo;ll Measure the Lean Startup Value of Information in My Next Side Project</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I'll measure the lean startup value of information in my next side project (Lean Software Development Part 8)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-07T21:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There must be a way to know the real money value of <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/">Lean Startup</a> &lsquo;knowledge&rsquo;.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2015-12-07-how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/knowledge-money.jpg" alt="A brain or some money ?" /></p>

<p>Lean Startup is about gathering &lsquo;knowledge&rsquo; through experiments instead of building things. <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Principles-Product-Development-Flow-Generation/dp/1935401009/ref=sr_1_3?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1450068976&amp;sr=8-3&amp;keywords=lean+product+development">Flow book</a> suggests that the value of an information is its expected impact on the bottom line. So by combining both, there should be a way to compute a quantitative value for the knowledge.</p>

<p>The overall plan would be :</p>

<ol>
<li>Start with a rough business plan, but assume that all that&rsquo;s in it has got 1 chance out of 10 of being right</li>
<li>Design experiments to precise the likelyhood of what&rsquo;s in the business plan</li>
<li>Compute the value of each experiment as the difference of the expected bottom line after and before running it (This should be possible if relying on the business plan for other parameters)</li>
<li>Work on the task with the highest expected value, be it an experiment, a development, a sales task, or whatever</li>
<li>Adapt you business plan with any new information</li>
<li>Repeat</li>
<li>If it becomes obvious that the expected final earnings are too low, pivot</li>
</ol>


<p>Flow explains that all the principles are pretty robust to bad inputs and errors. In short, the final estimations of earnings are still a lot better than without using any specific method. In the case of Lean Startup, it means that a false business plan is a good enough starting point.</p>

<h2>How to assess the likelyhood of a figure ?</h2>

<p>By default let&rsquo;s assume the value of a feature is somewhere between 0 and your highest estimate. As we&rsquo;ll go through experiments we&rsquo;ll be able to narrow this value range and have a more accurate estimate for the real value.</p>

<p>To keep things simple we could assume that the probability of value is uniformaly distributed within this range. From what I read in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Waltzing-Bears-Managing-Software-Projects/dp/0932633609/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1449901015&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=waltzing+with+bears">Waltzing With Bears</a>, here would be a more realistic probability distribution.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2015-12-07-how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/Demarco-probability.png" alt="The curve of the probability of value according to DeMarco" /></p>

<h2>How to estimate the value of an experiment ?</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to go into the details here, because the logic is exactly the same as with technical experiments (which <a href="/measure-the-business-value-of-your-spikes-and-take-high-payoff-risks-lean-software-development-part-4/">I already wrote about</a>)</p>

<p>Since then though, I read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Waltzing-Bears-Managing-Software-Projects/dp/0932633609/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1449901015&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=waltzing+with+bears">Waltzing With Bears</a> which presents a way of doing Monte Carlo simulations in order to estimate risks on your project. I guess the same thing could be used for value, which would save us from a lot of complex math.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Waltzing-Bears-Managing-Software-Projects/dp/0932633609/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1449901015&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=waltzing+with+bears"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2015-12-07-how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/waltzing-with-bears.jpg" alt="Cover of 'Waltzing With Bears'" /></a></p>

<h2>When to stop doing experiments ?</h2>

<p>Isn&rsquo;t all this overkill ? One could argue that the point of Lean Startup should be to build just enough knowledge ! In fact, this value of information concept naturaly helps to find out when running the experiment is not worth it compared to actually doing the real thing.</p>

<p>BTW, a tool doing all this for your automaticaly would be great, wouldn&rsquo;t it ?</p>

<h2>What I&rsquo;ll do for my next bootstrap side project</h2>

<ol>
<li>Start with a target hourly earning rate.</li>
<li>Collect a list of projects I&rsquo;d be interested in.</li>
<li>Pick a project and write a business goal for it.</li>
<li>Assign likelyhoods and ranges on every figure in the business plan.</li>
<li>Design experiments to improve the figures.</li>
<li>Create tasks to actually build and sell the product.</li>
<li>Compute values for each of these tasks.</li>
<li>Work the most valueable first.</li>
<li>If the figures prove that I will not make my target wage with this project, I&rsquo;ll pivot, and restart from 2.</li>
<li>Otherwise, I&rsquo;ll repeat from 4.</li>
</ol>


<p>This was part 8 of my <a href="/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/">suite of article about Lean Software Development</a>, Part 7 was <a href="/a-plan-for-technical-debt-lean-software-development-part-7/">A Plan for Technical Debt</a>, Part 9 will be <a href="/my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9/">My Dream Lean Software Development Tool</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to measure your speed with your business value ? (Lean Software Development Part 3)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-measure-your-speed-with-your-business-value-lean-software-development-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-16T07:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-measure-your-speed-with-your-business-value-lean-software-development-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a french idiom that basicaly is</p>

<blockquote><p>No use to run, all that is needed is to start on time &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>an agile engineer would add</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip; and to go in the good direction</p></blockquote>

<p>Indeed, velocity or mean cycle time as speed measures have their shortcomings :</p>

<ul>
<li>Can be falsified by story point inflation !</li>
<li>Does not tell the team or its product owner whether they are working on the right thing.</li>
</ul>


<p>Wouldn&rsquo;t it be great if we could track the business value we are creating instead ? Wouldn&rsquo;t it be more motivating for developpers to know how they are contributing to the bottom line ? Wouldn&rsquo;t it help various people to align inside the organization ?</p>

<h2>How to track and prioritize based on your business value</h2>

<p>From <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Principles-Product-Development-Flow/dp/1935401009/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1413953773&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=product+development+flow">Reinertsen&rsquo;s Flow book</a>, we learned that the cost of delay is the main driver of the value creation : the faster you deliver a feature, less you spend the cost of delay of that feature, the more value you are creating for your company. <a href="http://scaledagileframework.com/wsjf/">This article</a> suggests that the cost of delay can be computed with the following formula :</p>

<blockquote><p>cost of delay = f(user business value) + g(time criticality) + h(risk reduction opportunity)</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/jchyip/estimating-cost-of-delay/27">This other article</a> suggests that they are different types of tasks that corresponds to the different terms of the formula above.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2014-10-16-how-to-measure-your-speed-with-your-business-value-lean-software-development-part-3/task-types.jpeg" alt="Different kind of tasks" /></p>

<p>Here is how we could link the 2 articles :</p>

<ul>
<li>Stories with deadlines : either through legal or market constraints, not doing this will put you out of business (&lsquo;time criticality&rsquo; in the formula)</li>
<li>Stories that influence the bottom line : by increasing the sales figures when delivered, or decreasing them when not delivered, which is kind of the same (&lsquo;user business value&rsquo; in the formula)</li>
<li>Risk reduction tasks : by mitigating risk or streamlining the process, these tasks actually improve the bottom line of other stories (&lsquo;risk reduction opportunity&rsquo; in the formula)</li>
</ul>


<p>The later type of task will be detailed in other articles. Let&rsquo;s focus on the two others.</p>

<h2>The case of the deadlined feature ?</h2>

<p>First, I&rsquo;d say its business value is 0, until it&rsquo;s too late. You should not be working on it too soon, but you should not be working on it too late neither !</p>

<p>In his book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Art-Agile-Development-James-Shore/dp/0596527675/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1413954965&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+agile+development">The Art of Agile Development</a> James Shore details in great details how an agile team can commit to deliverables (I really recommend this part, I might even write a post about it). He explains that in order to commit, teams should multiply their estimates by 4, or by 1.8 if they are very rigourous in their application of all the XP practices.</p>

<p>So a rule to handle such a task could be to</p>

<ul>
<li>estimate it</li>
<li>multiply that estimate by 4</li>
<li>substract this time from the deadline</li>
<li>prioritize it so that it can be started at that date, but not earlier</li>
<li>don&rsquo;t expect to be creating any value by completing these stories</li>
</ul>


<h2>What&rsquo;s the business value of other typical user stories</h2>

<p><a href="http://scaledagileframework.com/wsjf/">This article</a> suggests that in this case the cost of delay is equal to the business value of the feature for the user. But how can we have an idea of its actual user business value ?</p>

<p>Before actually selling and getting the money, it&rsquo;s just an estimation. With the good information, some people will make better estimates than others, never the less, it&rsquo;s still an estimate. Let&rsquo;s try a &ldquo;Business Value Poker&rdquo; ! Here are a few ideas about how to conduct this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Estimate business value at the same time as you estimate the complexity of a story</li>
<li>Create some business value $ poker estimate cards, write an app for this, or bring in some Poker Chips to estimate the value</li>
<li>Invite some business people (sales, marketting &hellip;) to the meeting to get real knowledge (being organized as a feature team will help)</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://gigaom.com/2012/05/16/social-gaming-to-gambling-states-inch-forward/poker-chips-by-sanzar-murzin/"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2014-10-16-how-to-measure-your-speed-with-your-business-value-lean-software-development-part-3/all-in.jpg" alt="Hands pushing poker chips for an all-in" /></a></p>

<p>At the end, when you have the estimated cost of delay and duration of every task, you can directly prioritize using the WSJF (Weighted Shortest Job First) :</p>

<blockquote><p>WSJF = Cost of Delay / Duration</p></blockquote>

<p>Just do the tasks by decreasing order of WSJF.</p>

<p>At the end of the sprint, just as we track the story points we completed with the velocity, we could track the business value we created, that would be our business value speed. If you have access to real sales numbers, it might be interesting to see if it&rsquo;s possible to correlate the figures.</p>

<h2>Afterthoughts</h2>

<p>The more I learn about Lean principles, the more I find our current Issues Tracking Systems (I&rsquo;m used to Jira) limited. They seem to be databases with a nice UI, whereas what we need are tools to help us to make better decisions out of the multitude of items &hellip; How come they do not provide something as simple as the WSJF ?</p>

<h2>Edit 12/09/2014</h2>

<p>I got some pretty positive feedback from practicing these business value pokers. Inviting the product owner forced him to explain in details why he believed some features were more valuable than others. On the opposite, it allowed the developpers to hightlight how some seemingly unimportant stories were critical to a long term goal. In the end, everyone, including the product owner, is asking for more. It&rsquo;s a good practice that helps introducing the business value / cost of delay concept.</p>

<p>This was part 3 of my <a href="/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/">suite of article about Lean Software Development</a>, Part 2 was <a href="/why-extreme-programming-works-lean-software-development-part-2/">Why eXtreme Programming works ?</a>, Part 4 will be <a href="/measure-the-business-value-of-your-spikes-and-take-high-payoff-risks-lean-software-development-part-4/">Measure the business value of your spikes and take high payoff risks</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
