<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mocking | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/mocking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-11-27T06:36:35+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How NOT to use mocks, my talk at Paris.rb]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-not-to-use-mocks-my-talk-at-paris-rb/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-13T04:03:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-not-to-use-mocks-my-talk-at-paris-rb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I already <a href="/blog/categories/mocking/">wrote about</a>, mocks can be trecherous &hellip; I gave a talk about how to avoid them last tuesday at <a href="http://www.meetup.com/fr-FR/parisrb/">Paris.rb meetup</a>. Here are the <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1OH3eBgjyMcpupUnGWsHXm7kQjkckFpnJStYYYqBL6Yk/edit?usp=sharing">slides</a>.</p>

<p>It talks about testing, mocking, but also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain-driven_design">Domain Driven Design</a> and <a href="https://wincent.com/blog/proxies-with-rr">test proxies à la RR</a> (but for rspec).</p>

<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1OH3eBgjyMcpupUnGWsHXm7kQjkckFpnJStYYYqBL6Yk/embed?start=false&loop=false&delayms=3000" frameborder="0" width="790" height="470" allowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" webkitallowfullscreen="true"></iframe>




<p><p/>
Check the speaker&rsquo;s comments for all the details.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RSpecProxies now supports .to receive(xxx)... syntax]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/rspecproxies-now-supports-to-receive-xxx-dot-dot-dot-syntax/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-23T04:47:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/rspecproxies-now-supports-to-receive-xxx-dot-dot-dot-syntax</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-23-rspecproxies-now-supports-to-receive-xxx-dot-dot-dot-syntax/test_probes.jpg" title="Hardware test probes" ></p>

<p>Pure mocks are dangerous. They let defect go through, give a false sense of security and are difficult to maintain.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve already talked about it <a href="/hitting-the-middle-ground-between-classicist-and-mockist-tdd/">before</a> but since then, <a href="http://david.heinemeierhansson.com/2014/tdd-is-dead-long-live-testing.html">DHH announced that he was quitting TDD</a>, the <a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/is-tdd-dead/">Is TDD Dead ?</a> debate took place, and the conclusion is that <a href="https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/mockists-are-dead-long-live-classicists">mockist are dead</a>.</p>

<p>They are still times when mocks feel much simpler than any other things. For example, imagine your process leaks and crashes after 10 hours, the fix is to pass an option to a thirdparty, how would you test this in a fast test ? That&rsquo;s exactly the kind of situation where using test proxies saves you from mocks. A test proxy defers everything to the real object but also features unintrusive hooks and probes that you can use in your test. If you want a code example, check <a href="https://github.com/philou/mes-courses/commit/2c9fce17f9b59d0b3828f309015c07b17cceddf4?diff=split">this commit</a>, where I refactored a rails controller test from mocks to a RSpecProxies (v0.1).</p>

<p>I created RSpecProxies <a href="/my-new-gem-for-creating-rspec-proxies/">a while ago</a>, a while ago, and it&rsquo;s syntax made it alien to the RSpec work, it needed an update. <a href="http://rspec.info">RSpec</a> now supports basic proxying with partial stubs, spies, the <code>and_call_original</code> and the <code>and_wrap_original</code> methods. <a href="https://github.com/philou/rspecproxies">RSpecProxies 1.0</a> is a collection of hooks built on top of these to make proxying easier, with a syntax that will be familiar to RSpec users.</p>

<h2>Before original hook</h2>

<p>This hook is triggered before a call a method. Suppose you want to simulate a bad connection :</p>

<p>```ruby
it &lsquo;can simulate unreliable connection&rsquo; do
  i = 0
  allow(Resource).to receive(:get).and_before_calling_original { |*args|</p>

<pre><code>i += 1
raise RuntimeError.new if i % 3 == 0
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  resources = Resource.get_at_least(10)</p>

<p>  expect(resources.size).to eq(10)
end
```</p>

<h2>After original hooks</h2>

<p>RSpecProxies provides the same kind of hook after the call :</p>

<p>``` ruby
it &lsquo;can check that the correct data is used (using and_after_calling_original&rsquo; do
  user = nil
  allow(User).to receive(:load).and_after_calling_original { |result| user = result }</p>

<p>  controller.login(&lsquo;joe&rsquo;, &lsquo;secret&rsquo;)</p>

<p>  expect(response).to include(user.created_at.to_s)
end
```</p>

<p>Here we are capturing the return value to use it later in the test. For this special purpose, RSpecProxies also provides 2 other helpers :</p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<h1>Store the latest result in @user of self</h1>

<p>allow(User).to receive(:load).and_capture_result_into(self, :user)</p>

<h1>Collect all results in the users array</h1>

<p>users = []
allow(User).to receive(:load).and_collect_results_into(users)
```</p>

<h2>Proxy chains</h2>

<p>RSpec mocks provides the <code>message_chain</code> feature to do build chains of stubs. RSpecProxy provides a very similar proxy chain concept. The main difference is that it creates proxies along the way, and not pure stubs. Pure stubs assume that you are mocking everything, but as our goal is to mock as little as possible, using proxies makes more sense.</p>

<p>When using a mockist approach, the message chain is a bad smell because it makes your tests very brittle by depending on a lot of implementation. In contrast, proxy chains are meant to be used where they are the simplest way to inject what you need, without creating havoc.</p>

<p>For example, suppose you want to display the progress of a very slow background task. You could mock a lot of your objects to have a fast test, of if you wanted to avoid all the bad side effects of mocking, you could run the background task in your test, and have a slow test &hellip; Or, you could use a chain of proxies :</p>

<p>``` ruby
it &lsquo;can override a deep getter&rsquo; do
  allow(RenderingTask).to proxy_message_chain(&ldquo;load.completion_ratio&rdquo;) { |e| e.and_return(0.2523) }</p>

<p>  controller.show</p>

<p>  expect(response).to include(&lsquo;25%&rsquo;)
end
```</p>

<p>Here the simplest thing to do is just to override a small getter, because from a functionnal point of view, that&rsquo;s exactly what we want to test.</p>

<h2>Last word</h2>

<p>The code is on <a href="https://github.com/philou/rspecproxies">github</a>, v1.0.0 is on <a href="https://rubygems.org/gems/rspecproxies/versions/0.1.0">rubygems</a>, it requires Ruby v2.2.5 and RSpec v3.5, the license is MIT, help in any form are welcome !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My new gem for creating rspec proxies]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-new-gem-for-creating-rspec-proxies/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-23T06:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-new-gem-for-creating-rspec-proxies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I already wrote a lot about test proxies (<a href="/how-to-stub-around-a-call-to-the-original-method-with-rspec/">here</a>, <a href="/hitting-the-middle-ground-between-classicist-and-mockist-tdd/">here</a> and <a href="/my-humble-advices-about-how-to-write-maintainable-tests/">here</a>).</p>

<p>I just took the time to transform my previous gist in a full fledged ruby gem. It&rsquo;s called &ldquo;rspecproxies&rdquo; and it can be found <a href="https://github.com/philou/rspecproxies">on github</a>. It&rsquo;s fully tested, documented and there&rsquo;s a usage section in the readme to help anyone get started.</p>

<p>Here are the pain points proxies try to fix :</p>

<ul>
<li>Without mocks, it is sometimes just awfully painfull to write the test (do you really want to start a background task just to get a completion ratio ?)</li>
<li>With classic stubs, you sometimes have to stub things you are not interested in in your test, you end up with unmaintainable extra long stub setup</li>
</ul>


<p>Let&rsquo;s have a look at a few examples of tests with proxies :</p>

<ul>
<li>Verify actual load count without interfering in any behaviour</li>
</ul>


<p>```ruby
it &lsquo;caches users&rsquo; do
  users = User.capture_results_from(:load)</p>

<p>  controller.login(&lsquo;joe&rsquo;, &lsquo;secret&rsquo;)
  controller.login(&lsquo;joe&rsquo;, &lsquo;secret&rsquo;)</p>

<p>  expect(users).to have_exactly(1).items
end
```</p>

<ul>
<li>Use proxies to stub an object that does not yet exist</li>
</ul>


<p>```ruby
it &lsquo;rounds the completion ratio&rsquo; do
   RenderingTask.proxy_chain(:load, :completion_ratio) {|s| s.and_return(0.2523) }</p>

<p>   renderingController.show</p>

<p>   expect(response).to include(&lsquo;25%&rsquo;)
end
```</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d really love to see more code tested with proxies, it makes the whole testing so much more natural. As with any testing techniques, we get more thorough testing from the ease of writing the test.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hitting the middle ground between classicist and mockist TDD]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/hitting-the-middle-ground-between-classicist-and-mockist-tdd/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-18T08:55:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/hitting-the-middle-ground-between-classicist-and-mockist-tdd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/mocksArentStubs.html">Martin Fowler&rsquo;s point of view</a>, I must have been a mockist. With using mocks extensively comes quite a few advantages :</p>

<ul>
<li>test failures often pinpoint the falsy code</li>
<li>easier test organisation mimicking that of the code</li>
<li>faster tests</li>
<li>simpler test initialization</li>
</ul>


<p>Mocks also have their own problems, but mostly :</p>

<ul>
<li>especialy with dynamicaly typed languages, a mock for class A might not implement the same methods than the real class A, but the test might be passing though ! This ampers refactoring with a longer feedback loop and mock setup rewriting</li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s what always bothered me. Eventually I tried a combinaison of techniques that seem to work well together and provides most of the best of both worlds.</p>

<ul>
<li>extensive use of factories (with <a href="https://github.com/thoughtbot/factory_girl">FactoryGirl</a>) to simplify setup</li>
<li>use of an <a href="http://www.sqlite.org/inmemorydb.html">in memory sqlite database</a> to get a fast full working db</li>
<li>implement fully functional fakes for some parts of the system</li>
<li>carefull use of mocks, inspired from <a href="http://blog.rubybestpractices.com/posts/gregory/052-issue-20-thoughts-on-mocking.html">Gregory Brown&rsquo;s thoughts on mocks</a>

<ul>
<li>when a test is too slow</li>
<li>to cut off a dependency to a subsystem that is not available in a unit test</li>
<li>to simplify overly long test data setup</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>use of test proxies (as in <a href="https://github.com/rr/rr">rr</a>) to inject specific behaviour or to perform specific checks without modifying the rest of the program.</li>
</ul>


<p>Here is how I implemented this with rspec :</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/philou/5894144.js"></script>


<p>With all this in place, it is most of the time possible to write straightforward tests. For example here, only real objects are used. @order gets its value when Order.create! is called.</p>

<p>```ruby
it &ldquo;should create an order with the cart&rdquo; do
  capture_result_from(Order, :create!, into: :order)</p>

<p>  check_in_cart</p>

<p>  @order.should_not be_nil
  @order.cart.should == @cart
end
```</p>

<p>Maybe I should swith to rr &hellip;</p>

<p><strong>EDIT 20/08/2014:</strong></p>

<p>I eventually moved this code into its own gem, it&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/philou/rspecproxies">on github</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[stub_model and mock_model]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/stubmodel-and-mockmodel/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/stubmodel-and-mockmodel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I decided to stop using stub_model and mock_model. I do not use them enough to get fluent with them. Everytime I have to deal with them, something breaks in an unexpected way. I just decided to stand with good old stubs.</p>


<p>I am also thinking of switching to RR (double ruby) and to use proxy objects to get simplify mocking even further. Did you try it ?</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
