<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: blogging | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/blogging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-19T04:23:32+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to use Hackernews and Reddit for blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-05T04:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I posted my latest article <a href="/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/">Is There Any Room for the Not-Passionate Developer ?</a> on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/">Hackernews</a> and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/programming/">Reddit Programming</a>. The post stayed on the fist page for a while, and I got a lot of traffic. If you are yourself blogging, you might be interested to know how it occurred, and what I learned in the process.</p>

<h2>How it started</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-05-how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging/soft-skills.jpg" title="The cover of &lsquo;Soft Skills, the software developer&rsquo;s life manual&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1473135683&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=soft+skills">Soft Skills, the software developer&rsquo;s life manual</a> John Somnez explains that posting your blog articles on HN or Reddit might bring you a ton of traffic, but that comments can be hard to swallow at time. Within a few hours of writing my blog post it had generated some positive activity on twitter (favorites and retweets) from my regular followers. That&rsquo;s a good sign that the post is good enough. As I had promised myself in such case, I submitted the post to both HN and Reddit.</p>

<h2>What happened ?</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-05-how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging/google-analytics.jpg" title="A Google Analytics screenshot, with the traffic spike" ></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know for sure on Reddit, but I know my post stayed on the first page of HN for a few hours, it even went up to the third place for a while. In the process I got a lot of traffic, a lot more than I am used to. I also got a ton of comments, on HN, Reddit and directly on my post. John Somnez had warned that comments on HN and Reddit can be very harsh, so I went through these quickly, took notes about the points that seemed interesting, but I only responded to comments on my website.</p>

<p>Overall, the comments were pretty interesting though, and brought a lot of valid points. I&rsquo;m planning to write a &lsquo;response&rsquo; article to take all these into perspective.</p>

<p>Most of the traffic was made in the day I submitted my post, but I had more traffic than usual for 2 or 3 days. Since then, the traffic has settled down, but I now get between 2 and 5 times more traffic than I typically had on a daily basis ! An online Taiwanese tech magazine also asked me the permission to translate <a href="http://www.inside.com.tw/2016/08/05/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer">my post in Chinese</a> !</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure about the performance of my website during the traffic spike. I&rsquo;m using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> to statically generated html on <a href="https://pages.github.com/">Github Pages</a>, so that should be fine. I am also using a custom domain, and I need to make sure my <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7738293">DNS is correctly configured</a> for this to perform well.</p>

<h2>Advice for bloggers</h2>

<p>So here is what I am going to do regarding HN and Reddit in the future :</p>

<ol>
<li>It can bring so much traffic and backlinks that I&rsquo;ll definitely continue to submit blog posts from time to time</li>
<li>For the moment, I&rsquo;ll stick to only submitting the articles from which I already received good feedbacks, I don&rsquo;t want to get a bad karma or reputation on these websites</li>
<li>I might submit old articles that gathered good reviews at the time I wrote them</li>
<li>Concerning comments, I&rsquo;ll try to grow an even thicker skin. Maybe at some point I&rsquo;ll try to answer on HN or Reddit</li>
</ol>


<p>Of course, depending how this works, I will adapt !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Years of Blogging About Software]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/5-years-of-blogging-about-software/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-27T04:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/5-years-of-blogging-about-software</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>5 years ago, I started blogging. I started really casually, my posts were personal reminders and notes rather than real well thought of articles. Nevertheless, it did me great good :</p>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve been invited to talk at meetups</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ve had the joy of seeing some articles being tweeted many times</li>
<li>I received interesting job offers from all over the world</li>
</ul>


<p>6 months ago, after reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1467000033&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=soft+skills">Soft Skills: The software developer&rsquo;s life manual</a>, I set up the practice of writing at least one article per week, and here is my (very encouraging) graph of sessions since then:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-27-5-years-of-blogging-about-software/analytics.jpg" title="The steadily increase curve of the sessions on my blog per month" ></p>

<h1>Excuses Why Not To Blog</h1>

<p>Here is a collection of the (bad) excuses you&rsquo;ll often hear people say for not blogging :</p>

<blockquote><p>I don&rsquo;t know how to write &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>Blogging regularly is actually a pretty good way to improve your writing skills. As usual, the key is to fake it until you make it.</p>

<blockquote><p>I&rsquo;m not into this social media stuff &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>You don&rsquo;t need to share anything personal on your software blog. In the end, your blog is a professional tool.</p>

<blockquote><p>I don&rsquo;t have anything interesting to say &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>They are others in the same situation as you who would like to see more posts about the kind of uninteresting things you just discovered. Wouldn’t you have liked someone to have written the newby article about « how to do XXX » you just spent 3 days to crack ?</p>

<blockquote><p>I don&rsquo;t have the time &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>Make it ! Time is never found, it is made. In the end, it’s just a matter of prioritization.</p>

<p>Obviously, there are other totally valid reasons why not to blog, but I&rsquo;ll assume you&rsquo;re able to recognize those.</p>

<h1>Why Would You Blog ?</h1>

<p>On the other side, if you jump into blogging, you can expect a lot of returns :</p>

<ul>
<li>First thing is that you&rsquo;ll obviously gain more visibility. I&rsquo;ve got readers from all over the world, and my articles are sometimes re-tweeted many times.</li>
<li>You&rsquo;ll improve your writing skills. Writing skills turn out to be unexpectedly important for <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9LfmrkyP81M">software writers</a> !</li>
<li>In order to lay down your ideas about something, you&rsquo;ll need to dig a bit more into. It is said to be the last step to learning.</li>
<li>It can act as a personal documentation. I used to write mine as a how-to notepad on which I could refer later on.</li>
<li>If you have a day job, you can re-post your articles there. You should gain extra visibility and expose the company to new ideas.</li>
</ul>


<h1>How to start</h1>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve decided that you want to blog, starting should not be an issue.</p>

<h2>Pick a platform</h2>

<p>There are a lot of blogging platforms out there. For programmers, I would recommend a few though :</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-27-5-years-of-blogging-about-software/platforms.jpg" title="Logos of my recommended blogging platforms" ></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Platform </th>
<th> Pros </th>
<th> Cons</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> </td>
<td> Free, Open Source, Github hosting, static HTML generation, markdown &amp; Git based, made for programmers </td>
<td> Theming can be rocky</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://medium.com/">Medium</a>    </td>
<td> Free, no setup, good looking, simple to use </td>
<td> It&rsquo;s a private company, so it could close some day ! It happened to <a href="http://www.posterous.com">postero.us</a> (I remember, I was there …)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://posthaven.com/">Posthaven</a> </td>
<td> Created by the founders of postero.us, sustainable, guarantees to keep it live for ever, can post by email ! </td>
<td> Nothing special for programmers, 5$ / month</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://logdown.com/">Logdown</a>   </td>
<td> Looks like a hosted version of Octopress, without the hassle ! </td>
<td> 50$/year</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Then, it&rsquo;s up to you !</p>

<h2>Start with how-to articles</h2>

<p>When I started my blog, it was mostly has a personal how-to reference. It allowed me to come back to it and find out how I did something last time. I thought that if it was important to me, it must be important to others as-well !</p>

<h2>Blog regularly</h2>

<p>Blogging every week made a huge difference to me. My traffic went from erratic to steadily increasing. I am currently observing a 11% traffic increase per month. This means that it nearly quadruples every year : I&rsquo;m not going to stop now !</p>

<h2>Integrate with the web</h2>

<p>This boils down to social networks and analytics. Obviously, you&rsquo;ll want to use Google Analytics to see how people are reading your content. I&rsquo;m using the venerable <a href="https://feedburner.google.com">Feedburner</a> to automatically post my new articles on <a href="https://twitter.com">twitter</a>. There&rsquo;s an option to use your post categories as hashtags, be sure to make it works, it brings a lot of traffic.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s all up to you now !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I fixed the unknown language Pygments error in Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-i-fixed-the-unknown-language-pygments-error-in-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-13T03:54:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-i-fixed-the-unknown-language-pygments-error-in-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last time I tried to insert a code snippet in my <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> blog, I was hurt by the following error :</p>

<p>```
vagrant@ae4a04cebb73:/vagrant$ bundle exec rake generate</p>

<h2>Generating Site with Jekyll</h2>

<p>unchanged sass/screen.scss
Configuration from /vagrant/_config.yml
Building site: source &ndash;> public
/vagrant/plugins/pygments_code.rb:27:in `rescue in pygments': Pygments can&rsquo;t parse unknown language: ruby. (RuntimeError)</p>

<pre><code>from /vagrant/plugins/pygments_code.rb:24:in `pygments'
from /vagrant/plugins/pygments_code.rb:14:in `highlight'
from /vagrant/plugins/backtick_code_block.rb:37:in `block in render_code_block'
from /vagrant/plugins/backtick_code_block.rb:13:in `gsub'
from /vagrant/plugins/backtick_code_block.rb:13:in `render_code_block'
from /vagrant/plugins/octopress_filters.rb:12:in `pre_filter'
from /vagrant/plugins/octopress_filters.rb:28:in `pre_render'
from /vagrant/plugins/post_filters.rb:112:in `block in pre_render'
from /vagrant/plugins/post_filters.rb:111:in `each'
from /vagrant/plugins/post_filters.rb:111:in `pre_render'
from /vagrant/plugins/post_filters.rb:166:in `do_layout'
from /vagrant/vendor/bundle/gems/jekyll-0.12.1/lib/jekyll/post.rb:195:in `render'
from /vagrant/vendor/bundle/gems/jekyll-0.12.1/lib/jekyll/site.rb:200:in `block in render'
from /vagrant/vendor/bundle/gems/jekyll-0.12.1/lib/jekyll/site.rb:199:in `each'
from /vagrant/vendor/bundle/gems/jekyll-0.12.1/lib/jekyll/site.rb:199:in `render'
from /vagrant/vendor/bundle/gems/jekyll-0.12.1/lib/jekyll/site.rb:41:in `process'
from /vagrant/vendor/bundle/gems/jekyll-0.12.1/bin/jekyll:264:in `&lt;top (required)&gt;'
from /vagrant/vendor/bundle/bin/jekyll:22:in `load'
from /vagrant/vendor/bundle/bin/jekyll:22:in `&lt;main&gt;'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>I had been switching to <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> in <a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a> to host my Octopress installation, but that did not seem related &hellip;</p>

<h2>Plan A : Upgrade Octopress</h2>

<p>It turned out it was related to my migration to Vagrant and Docker.xs This kind of nasty error often comes from obsolete environment. <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/issues/1173">Internet confirmed</a> confirmed it :</p>

<ul>
<li>Ubuntu now uses Python3 instead of Python2</li>
<li>Octopress2 uses an old version of Pygments</li>
<li>That version of Pygments requires Python2</li>
</ul>


<p>I thought that I did not want to play <a href="/ruby-thirdparties-best-practices/">this game</a> against open source libs, so I set out to update. Octopress 3 has been released. It&rsquo;s not yet documented yet, and there is no official upgrade guide, but some guys have done it :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://samwize.com/2015/09/30/migrating-octopress-2-to-octopress-3/">http://samwize.com/2015/09/30/migrating-octopress-2-to-octopress-3/</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2016/01/22/migrating-from-octopress-2-to-3/">http://dgmstuart.github.io/blog/2016/01/22/migrating-from-octopress-2-to-3/</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.justinrummel.com/migrating-from-octopress-2-to-octopress-3/">https://www.justinrummel.com/migrating-from-octopress-2-to-octopress-3/</a></li>
</ul>


<p>I tried it &hellip; but I stopped before the end. It&rsquo;s kind of working, but fundamental features like category archives required too much Jekylling for me at the time. And themes are still an issue &hellip; I mean, stock theme uses a clean and simple gem based update workflow, but most other themes rely on a tricky git clone-merge update workflow.</p>

<h2>Plan B : Find a hosted blog engine for hackers</h2>

<p>I found quite a few options :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://medium.com">Medium</a> Looks cool, but there is no simple migration tool, and I&rsquo;ve been burned by postero.us shutting down, I want to keep control on my content</li>
<li><a href="https://posthaven.com/">Posthaven</a> Having loved postero.us, this one seems cool, It&rsquo;s just I&rsquo;m not sure the guys are keeping the motivation to increase their feature list with their current business model</li>
<li><a href="http://ghost.org">Ghost</a> Looked great, but too expensive for me (19$ per month)</li>
<li><a href="http://codrspace.com">Codrspace</a> This is a special blogging platform for coders, but it seems it has not been updated for a long time</li>
<li><a href="https://logdown.com/">LogDown</a> This also is a special blogging platform for hackers. It seemed great and had everything I was looking for &hellip; I was ready to spend the 50$ per year for it as it could save me a lot of hassle. Unfortunately, I could not find a way to forward the categories of a post as <a href="https://twitter.com/pbourgau">Twitter</a> hashtags as I&rsquo;ve been doing with Octopress and <a href="https://feedburner.google.com">Feedburner</a></li>
</ul>


<p>In the end, I was rather disappointed by the alternatives, even though I was ready to pay for them.</p>

<h2>Plan C : Fix the error in Octopress 2</h2>

<p>Eventually, the fix was rather easy. People had fixed it by patching mentos.py file in the pygments.rb gem to run Python 2 instead of the stock Python. That&rsquo;s not great because it means that I&rsquo;d have to redo the patch every time I updated my gems, or rebuilt my workspace. Here is what I added to my Vagrantfile instead :</p>

<p><code>
sudo apt-get -y install python2.7
sudo ln -sf /usr/bin/python2.7 /usr/bin/python
</code>
<a href="https://github.com/philou/philou.github.com/commit/ae14c511b682295ed7fdcb3b1a818926f803dd3a">Here</a> is the commit on my Github repo.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m sticking with Octopress2 for the moment. Maybe I&rsquo;ll re-try to migrate to Octopress3 later on, when an official migration tool or <a href="http://octopress.org/2015/01/15/octopress-3.0-is-coming/">guide</a> is available. Meanwhile, I&rsquo;m still dreaming of my perfect blogging platform :</p>

<ul>
<li>Open source</li>
<li>Static HTML generation</li>
<li>Self or SAAS hosted</li>
<li>Great integration with social media and the web</li>
<li>Easy to maintain</li>
<li>Plugable themes</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m looking for my next side project at the moment, that could be a useful one ! Anyone interested ?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Retroactively add keywords for your existing Octopress posts]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/retroactively-add-keywords-for-your-existing-octopress-posts/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-11T06:54:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/retroactively-add-keywords-for-your-existing-octopress-posts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the moment, I am exploring the world of SEO, and so I thought I could start with my blog. I found <a href="http://xit0.org/2013/05/seo-for-octopress-websites/">SEO for Octopress websites</a> that I followed to add keywords and descriptions to this blog.</p>

<p>To fill actual keywords for all my existing posts, I had 2 options :</p>

<ul>
<li>edit around 60 posts by hand</li>
<li>write a script to parse Yaml post descriptions and extract and inject keywords</li>
</ul>


<p>Sorry, I chose the geeky solution &hellip;</p>

<p>
<script src="https://gist.github.com/philou/8929876.js"></script>
</p>


<p>Just add this code to your toplevel Rakefile, and run <code>bundle exec rake add_keywords</code> and keywords will be added to your existing posts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A useful link to find free pictures]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-nice-place-to-find-free-pictures-for-my-web/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-nice-place-to-find-free-pictures-for-my-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While I was looking for photos for an article on&nbsp; <a href="http://www.mes-courses.fr/blog">blog for mes-courses.fr</a>, I found this site : <a href="http://www.photo-libre.fr">http://www.photo-libre.fr</a>. There are a lot of pictures, both &euro; free and royalties free. All that is asked for is a backing to <a href="http://www.photo-libre.fr/">http://www.photo-libre.fr</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
