<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rss | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/rss/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-12-13T06:33:44+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I just replaced Feedburner with MailChimp]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/i-just-replaced-feedburner-with-mailchimp/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T06:36:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/i-just-replaced-feedburner-with-mailchimp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Until now, I had been using <a href="http://www.feedburner.com">Feedburner</a> to manage the email subscriptions to my <a href="https://www.mes-courses.fr/blog">blog on mes-courses.fr</a>. <del>It had been working fine</del> I thought it had been working fine until a friend of mine asked me if I was still working on it, since it had been a time since she did not receive any email !</p>

<p>It turned out that feedburner had not been forwarding emails for 6 months and that it had gone unnoticed &hellip; I had already had this issue before, and it was because my rss was not well formed according to feedburner (something related to unicode encoding I think). So to summarise :</p>

<ul>
<li>I lost trust in feedburner to forward my posts correctly</li>
<li>Feedburner is not maintained by Google anymore</li>
<li>They have been persistant rumors about Google shutting down Feedburner completly especially since the Reader shut down</li>
</ul>


<p>I started looking for alternatives. I tried <a href="http://www.nouri.sh">Nourish</a> and <a href="http://www.mailchimp.com">MailChimp</a> I did not manage to make Nourish work like I wanted, but I found MailChimp an intuitive and well documented product.</p>

<p>The setup with MailChimp was a lot longer than with Feedburner, but the result is great. I feed a lot more confident about these emails being delivered now.</p>

<p>There are a few points I still miss though :</p>

<ul>
<li>The social forward does not seem to work the same easy way, it looks like if MailChimp pushes the email content to your networks, but not a direct link to your blog</li>
<li>MailChimp does not track non-email subscribers to your rss. I&rsquo;ll have to check my analytics to see how to do it.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
