<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: remote | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/remote/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-07T04:31:15+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trello Templates to Boost Your Remote Retrospectives]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-11T20:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I already wrote how we started to use <a href="http://trello.com">Trello</a> to do our <a href="/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">remote retrospectives</a>. A while ago, my team mate <a href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/20/agile-retrospectives-using-trello/">Bilal Tayara</a> started to collect our activities into <a href="https://trello.com/agileretrospectives">trello templates</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-11-trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives/retrospective_meetings.jpg" title="&lsquo;Stop Doing&rsquo;, &lsquo;Continue Doing&rsquo; &amp; &lsquo;Start doing&rsquo; panels of a retrospective activity" ></p>

<h2>New activities</h2>

<p>I just imported new activities we have been using in the past months :</p>

<ul>
<li>SMART Goals</li>
<li>5 Whys</li>
<li>Circle of Questions</li>
<li>Communication</li>
<li>Engagement</li>
<li>ESVP</li>
<li>Fishbone</li>
<li>Focus On/Focus Off</li>
<li>Force Field Analysis</li>
<li>Gifts</li>
<li>Glad Sad Mad</li>
<li>Health Radar</li>
<li>HHH</li>
<li>Hot Air Balloon</li>
<li>How are you feeling today ?</li>
<li>Improvements Brainstorming</li>
<li>Learning Matrix</li>
<li>Note To Self</li>
<li>Plus / Delta</li>
<li>Problem &ndash;> Action</li>
<li>Punctual Paulo</li>
<li>Retrospective Planning Game</li>
<li>Risk Brainstorming</li>
<li>ROTI</li>
<li>Sail Boat</li>
<li>Satisfaction Histogram</li>
<li>Take Away</li>
<li>Team</li>
<li>Team Radar</li>
<li>Warmup Question</li>
<li>What happened since last retro ?</li>
</ul>


<h2>How to use these templates</h2>

<p>Clone the template to your organization every time you want to use it. There are instructions in the template to explain how to use it. For more detailed instructions, have a look at the original :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://pragprog.com/book/dlret/agile-retrospectives">Agile Retrospectives, Making Good Teams Great</a> by Esther Derby and Diana Larsen, Foreword by Ken Schwaber</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://pragprog.com/book/dlret/agile-retrospectives"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-11-trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives/AgileRetrospectives.jpg" title="The cover of Agile Retrospectives" ></a></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.infoq.com/minibooks/agile-retrospectives-value">Getting Value out of Agile Retrospectives, Second Edition</a> by Luis Gonçalves and Ben Linders</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.infoq.com/minibooks/agile-retrospectives-value"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-11-trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives/GettingAgileOutOfAgileRetrospectives.jpg" title="The cover of Getting Agile Out Of Agile Retrospectives" ></a></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://leanpub.com/funretrospectives">Fun Retrospectives</a> by Taina Caetano and Paulo Caroli</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://leanpub.com/funretrospectives"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-11-trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives/FunRetrospectives.jpg" title="The cover of Fun Retrospectives" ></a></p>

<p>One last thing : in order to improve this collection, we&rsquo;d like to have your feedback on existing activities, or your own new templates for other activities.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trellospectives : Remote Retrospectives with Trello]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-05T06:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a distributed team working from Paris and Beirut, after <a href="/from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/">pair programming</a>, it was time for our retrospectives to get remote !</p>

<p><a href="/imgs/2015-04-05-trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/setup.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-04-05-trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/setup-small.jpg" title="A remote retrospective meeting with Trello setup" ></a></p>

<h2>Initial setup</h2>

<p>At first we were using the visio conference system. The retrospective facilitator would connect with the remote participants through instant chat and forward theirs post-its. We also used an extra webcam connected to the laptop in order to show the whiteboard in the other room.</p>

<h4>Pros</h4>

<ul>
<li>Anyone can do it now</li>
<li>Kind of works</li>
</ul>


<h4>Cons</h4>

<ul>
<li>We often used to loose 5 minutes setting all the infrastructure up</li>
<li>The remote room cannot see the board clearly through the webcam</li>
<li>The animator has to spend his time forwarding the other room&rsquo;s points</li>
<li>There is a &lsquo;master&rsquo; and a &lsquo;slave&rsquo; room</li>
</ul>


<h2>Sensei Tool</h2>

<p>When Mohamad joined the team in Beirut, we thought that this was not going to scale &hellip; We decided to try something else. With the availability of the new conferencing system, we had the idea to use a web tool to run the retro. We found and tried <a href="http://senseitool.com/">senseitool.com</a>. After creating accounts for every member of the team and scheduling a retrospective through the tool, we could all equally participate using our smartphones. The retrospective follows a typical workflow that is fine for teams new to the practice.</p>

<h4>Pros</h4>

<ul>
<li>Even easier to setup</li>
<li>Works fine</li>
</ul>


<h4>Cons</h4>

<ul>
<li>The website was a bit slow</li>
<li>The retrospective was too guided for an experienced team, we did not get as good outputs as we used to</li>
<li>Everyone could participate as easily</li>
</ul>


<h2>Trello</h2>

<p><a href="/imgs/2015-04-05-trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/boat.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-04-05-trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/boat-small.jpg" title="The boat activity on Trello" ></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.google.fr/search?sourceid=chrome-psyapi2&amp;ion=1&amp;espv=2&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=remote%20retrospective">Asking Google</a>, we discovered that some teams were having success using <a href="https://trello.com/">Trello</a> for their remote retrospectives. We decided to give it a try. Ahmad from Beirut got to work on our first retrospective with it. He had to prepare it beforehand (as we always have been doing). In practice :</p>

<ul>
<li>Ahmad created an organization for our team</li>
<li>We all registered to Trello and joined the organization (we like joining (smile))</li>
<li>Ahmad created a custom board for each activity</li>
<li>During the meeting, we used the video conferencing system and the instant chat to have both visio and screen sharing</li>
<li>The animator used a laptop to manage the Trello boards</li>
<li>Everyone of us could add post-its through his smartphone app</li>
</ul>


<h4>Pros</h4>

<ul>
<li>The setup is easy</li>
<li>The retrospective worked well and delivered interesting output</li>
<li>We actually all see the board</li>
<li>The smartphone app works well</li>
<li>It is possible to vote directly through Trello</li>
<li>Everyone could participate as easily</li>
<li>We can classify post-its with labels</li>
<li>We can insert pictures and photos</li>
<li>There are a lot of chrome extensions to Trello (<a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/vertical-lists-for-trello/aldklnbenbdgfgfbflalmlddkkndgnlc?utm_source=chrome-app-launcher-info-dialog">Vertical Lists for Trello</a>), <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/card-color-titles-for-tre/hpmobkglehhleflhaefmfajhbdnjmgim?utm_source=chrome-app-launcher-info-dialog">Card Color Titles for Trello</a></li>
</ul>


<h4>Cons</h4>

<ul>
<li>There is nothing to &lsquo;group&rsquo; post its together</li>
<li>We need to prepare custom boards for every activity</li>
<li>We would need to pay for the gold version with custom backgrounds and stickers</li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p><a href="/imgs/2015-04-05-trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/roti.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-04-05-trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/roti-small.jpg" title="The Return On Time Invested activity on Trello" ></a></p>

<p>While missing a few features that would make it awesome, Trello is the best tool we found for remote retrospective, and is better than our initial physical setup. We&rsquo;re continuing to use it, and we now have to figure out</p>

<ul>
<li>If we could find a way to speed up the meeting preparation</li>
<li>How to handle &lsquo;graph oriented&rsquo; activities such as the &lsquo;5 whys&rsquo;</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="/imgs/2015-04-05-trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/5-whys.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-04-05-trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/5-whys-small.jpg" title="The 5 why activity on a physical whiteboard" ></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From Zero to Pair Programming Hero]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-27T06:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my team at <a href="http://www.murex.com">Murex</a>, we&rsquo;ve been doing Pair programming 75% of our time for the past 9 months now.</p>

<p><a href="/imgs/2015-01-27-from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/real-teamwork.JPG"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-01-27-from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/real-teamwork.resized.JPG" title="Photo of all the team doing pair programming" ></a></p>

<p>Before I explain how we got there, let&rsquo;s summarize our observations :</p>

<ul>
<li>No immediate productivity drop</li>
<li>Pair programming is really tiring</li>
<li>Quality expectations throughout the team soared up</li>
<li>As a result, the quality actually increased a lot</li>
<li>But existing technical debt suddenly became incompatible with the team&rsquo;s own quality criterion. We went on to pay it back, which slowed us down for a while</li>
<li>Productivity is regularly going up as the technical debt is reduced</li>
<li>It helped us to define shared coding conventions</li>
<li>Pair programming is not for everyone. It has likely precipitated the departure of one team member</li>
<li>It certainly helped the team to <a href="http://www.hans-eric.com/2007/08/13/is-your-team-jelled/">jell</a></li>
<li>Newcomers can submit code on day 1</li>
<li>The skills of everyone increase a lot quicker than before</li>
<li><em>Bonus</em> : it improves personal skills of all the team members</li>
</ul>


<p>If you are interested in how we got there, read on, here is our story :</p>

<h2>Best Effort Code Reviews</h2>

<p>At the beginning, only experienced team members were reviewing the submitted code, and making remarks for improvement over our default review system : <a href="http://smartbear.com/product/collaborator/overview/">Code Collaborator</a>.</p>

<p>This practice revealed tedious, especially with large change lists. As it was not systematic, reviewers constantly had to remind to the reviewees to act on the remarks, which hindered empowerment.</p>

<h2>Systematic Code Reviews</h2>

<p>Observing this during a <a href="/how-we-introduced-efficient-agile-retrospectives/">retrospective</a>, we decided to do add code review to our <a href="https://www.scrum.org/Resources/Scrum-Glossary/Definition-of-Done">Definition Of Done</a>. Inspired by <a href="http://producingoss.com/en/setting-tone.html#code-review">best practices in the Open Source world</a>, we created a ruby review script that automatically creates Code Collaborator reviews based on the <a href="www.perforce.com">Perforce</a> submits. Everyone was made observer of any code change, and everyone was to participate in the reviews.</p>

<p>At first, to make this practice stick, a few benevolent review champions had to comment all the submitted code; once the habit was taken, everyone participated in the reviews.</p>

<p>Code Collaborator spamming was certainly an issue, but using Code Collaborator System Tray App helped each of us to keep up to date with the remaining reviews to do.</p>

<p><em>Bonus</em> : As everyone was doing reviews, and that reviews of small changes are easier, submits became smaller.</p>

<p><a href="/imgs/2015-01-27-from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/code-collaborator.png"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-01-27-from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/code-collaborator.resized.png" title="A screenshot of our code collaborator installation" ></a></p>

<p>This was certainly an improvement, but it remained time consuming. We believed we could do better.</p>

<h2>Pair Programming</h2>

<p>After 1 or 2 months of systematic code reviews, during a retrospective (again) nearly all the team members decided to give <a href="http://blogs.sourceallies.com/2011/03/pair-programming-101/">pair programming</a> a try.</p>

<p>We felt the difference after the very first day : pair programming is intense, but the results are great. We never turned back.</p>

<p>With pair programming in place, we had to settle a pair switching frequency. We started with the full story, tried a one day rotation, and eventually settled on &ldquo;MIN(1 week, the story)&rdquo;.</p>

<p>This is not set in stone and is team dependent. It may vary depending on the learning curve required to work on a story. We might bring it down later maybe.</p>

<h2>Remote Pair Programming</h2>

<p>Ahmad, a Murex guy from Beirut joined the team a few months ago. We did not want to change our way of working, and decided to try remote pair programming.</p>

<h3>Initial Setup</h3>

<p>At the beginning, we were using <a href="http://products.office.com/en-us/Lync/lync-2013-video-conferencing-meeting-software">Lync</a> (Microsoft&rsquo;s chat system) with webcams, headphones and screen sharing. It works, but Lync&rsquo;s screen sharing does not allow seamless remote control between Paris and Beirut. Here is how we coped with this :</p>

<ul>
<li>Only exceptionally use Lync&rsquo;s &ldquo;Give Control&rdquo; feature : it lags too much</li>
<li>Do small submits, and switch control at submits</li>
<li>When you cannot submit soon, shelve the code on perforce (you would just pull your buddy&rsquo;s repo with git), and switch control</li>
</ul>


<p>As a result, Ahmad became productive a lot more quickly. We are not 2 sub teams focusing on their own area of expertise, but 1 single distributed team sharing everything.</p>

<p><a href="/imgs/2015-01-27-from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/remote-pairing-setup.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-01-27-from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/remote-pairing-setup.resized.jpg" title="My remote pair programming setup" ></a></p>

<h3>Improved Setup</h3>

<p>Remote pair programming as such is workable, but does not feel as easy as being collocated. Here are a few best practices we are now using to improve the experience :</p>

<ul>
<li>Keep your pair&rsquo;s video constantly visible : either on your laptop of in a corner of you main screen, but it&rsquo;s important to see his facial expression all the time</li>
<li>In order to allow eye contact, place your cam next to the window containing the video of your pair.</li>
<li>Using 2 cameras, <a href="http://download.manycam.com/">ManyCams</a> and a small whiteboard allows to share drawings !</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="/imgs/2015-01-27-from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/remote-pairing-screenshot.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-01-27-from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/remote-pairing-screenshot.resized.jpg" title="A screenshot of my pair programming environment" ></a></p>

<ul>
<li>We started using the <a href="http://pomodorotechnique.com/">Pomodoro technique</a> for control switching. <a href="http://www.marinaratimer.com/">MarinaraTimer</a> provides an online and shareable timer.</li>
<li>We also started maintaining a todo list with an online shareable editor such as <a href="http://collabedit.com/">CollabEdit</a> or <a href="https://docs.google.com/">Google Docs</a>.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Future Setup</h3>

<p>We are currently welcoming a new engineer in Beirut, and as we will be doing more remote pair programming, we&rsquo;ll need to make this more seamless. Control sharing and lag through Lync remain the main issues. We don&rsquo;t have a solution for that yet, but here are the fixes we are looking into</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.saros-project.org/">Saros</a> is an <a href="https://eclipse.org/">Eclipse</a> plugin for remote concurrent and real time editing of files. Many people can edit the files at the same time. We are waiting for the <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/idea/">Intellij</a> version that is still under development</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.saros-project.org/screenshots"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-01-27-from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/saros.resized.png" title="A screenshot from Eclipse with Saros plugin" ></a></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://floobits.com/">Floobits</a> is a commercial equivalent of saros. We tried it and it seems great. It&rsquo;s not cheap though, especially with in-house servers.</li>
<li><a href="https://screenhero.com/">Screenhero</a> is a commercial low-lag, multi cursor screen sharing tool. Unfortunately, it currently does not work behind a proxy, and so we were not able to evaluate it yet.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Final thoughts</h2>

<p>I believe that collocated, and remote, pair programming are becoming key skills for a modern software engineer.</p>

<p>I hope this will help teams envisioning pair programming. We&rsquo;d love to read about your best practices as well !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
