<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rspec | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/rspec/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-11T12:45:39+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RSpec matchers combinators]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/rspec-matchers-combinators/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-11T12:23:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/rspec-matchers-combinators</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://rubydoc.info/gems/rspec-expectations">Rspec matchers</a> are a lot like predicates. Predicates that can talk &hellip; The good thing about predicates, as anybody who has done a bit of functional programming will tell you, is that they are easy to combine together into bigger predicates. I was really suprised to see that rspec does not come with such simple combinators as &lsquo;and&rsquo; or &lsquo;or&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Here is a gist where I define simple combinators :</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/philou/6521797.js"></script>


<p>With this and the <a href="https://github.com/bmabey/email-spec">email_spec</a> matchers, it is possible to write something like this to find if an email was sent by rails :</p>

<p>```ruby
expect(all_emails).to have_any_that(and_(deliver_to(receiver),</p>

<pre><code>                                     have_subject(subject),
                                     have_body_text(body)))
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>It enables expressive test code and high reusability.</p>

<p>Using the &lsquo;all&rsquo; combinator it is possible to write things like that :</p>

<p><code>ruby
expect(sample_items_attributes).to all_ have_key(:price)
</code></p>

<p>I had to prepend &lsquo;all&rsquo; and &lsquo;and&rsquo; with an underscore because I would otherwise get conflicts&hellip; I&rsquo;m not overly satisfied with this, but it will do for the moment.</p>

<p>I was happily supprised by the readability of error messages when the mach fails. Rspec does a very good job about this. I think it would be possible to get even better error messages by explicity using the sub matchers messages though. If anyone is interested, help yourself !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spork alternative compatible with cucumber]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/spork-alternative-compatible-with-cucumber/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-03T08:51:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/spork-alternative-compatible-with-cucumber</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Version 1.3.0 of <a href="http://cukes.info/">Cucumber</a> droped spork support, so I had to find something else. I am using <a href="https://github.com/guard/guard">Guard</a> setup with <a href="http://rspec.info/">rspec</a> and Cucumber for my <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a> app.</p>

<p>I first tried <a href="https://github.com/burke/zeus">Zeus</a> with <a href="https://github.com/qnm/guard-zeus">guard-zeus</a>, it kind of worked, but it ruined my Guard console with the Zeus server status, and it left zombie processes on guard exit &hellip;</p>

<p>Eventually, I tried <a href="https://github.com/jonleighton/spring">Spring</a>, and once I made sure <a href="/simplest-way-to-speed-up-rspec-with-in-memory-sqlite-db/">rspec and cucumber both ran on the test environment</a>, it worked fine with minimal configuration. Here is what I had to do to get it working</p>

<ul>
<li>remove spork from your Gemfile</li>
<li>remove require &lsquo;spork&rsquo;, Spork.prefork and Spork.each_run calls from spec/spec_helper.rb and features/support/env.rb</li>
<li>install spring</li>
</ul>


<p><code>
gem install spring
</code></p>

<ul>
<li>add spring to your Gemfile ! Also <a href="https://github.com/jonleighton/spring/blob/master/README.md">they say it is not required</a> I later had an error complaining it wasn&rsquo;t.</li>
</ul>


<p><code>ruby
group :test, :development do
  ...
  gem 'spring'
  ...
group
</code></p>

<ul>
<li>update your Guardfile example :</li>
</ul>


<p>```ruby
guard :rspec, cli: &ldquo;&mdash;tag ~@slow&rdquo;, all_after_pass: true, all_on_start: false, keep_failed: true, spring: true, bundler: false do
  &hellip;
end</p>

<p>guard &lsquo;cucumber&rsquo;, all_on_start: false, cli: &lsquo;&mdash;format progress &mdash;no-profile&rsquo;, command_prefix: &lsquo;spring&rsquo;, bundler: false do
  &hellip;
end
```</p>

<ul>
<li>add a .spring.rb file to automaticaly restart Spring on main file changes. I think I&rsquo;ll have to update this file when I discover that a test failed because spring needs to be restarted</li>
</ul>


<p>```ruby
Spring.watch &ldquo;.spring.rb&rdquo;
Spring.watch &ldquo;spec/factories&rdquo;
Spring.watch &ldquo;features/env.rb&rdquo;</p>

<p>Spring.watch_method = :listen
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simplest way to speed up rspec with in memory sqlite db]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/simplest-way-to-speed-up-rspec-with-in-memory-sqlite-db/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-02T09:16:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/simplest-way-to-speed-up-rspec-with-in-memory-sqlite-db</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are already a lot of articles explaining how to setup an in memory <a href="http://www.sqlite.org/">SQLite</a> database to speed up <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a> specs or unit tests. Most of them explain how to change your database.yml and to run setup your schema before running the tests. It works fine.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a catch though : suppose you are using <a href="http://cukes.info/">cucumber</a>, it&rsquo;s likely you&rsquo;d rather run cucumber on a real database (<a href="http://www.postgresql.org/">PostgreSQL</a>, <a href="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> or whatever). Most gems expect cucumber and <a href="http://rspec.info/">rspec</a> to both run in the test environment &hellip; Every time I updated my bundle or that I wanted to use a new test gem, I would hit an issue about cucumber being run in its own &lsquo;cucumber&rsquo; environment : unexpected warnings and things not working out of the box.</p>

<p>Eventually, I ditched the cucumber env, setup a PostgreSQL db on the test env, and injected the in memory sqlite database right inside spec_helper.rb :</p>

<p>In database.yml :</p>

<p><code>yaml
test:
  adapter: postgresql
  database: mes_courses_test
  encoding: utf8
  pool: 5
  timeout: 5000
  username: mes_courses
  password: secret
  host: localhost
  port: 5433
</code></p>

<p>At the bottom of spec_helper.rb</p>

<p>```ruby
setup_sqlite_db = lambda do
  ActiveRecord::Base.establish_connection(adapter: &lsquo;sqlite3&rsquo;, database: &lsquo;:memory:&rsquo;)</p>

<p>  load &ldquo;#{Rails.root.to_s}/db/schema.rb&rdquo; # use db agnostic schema by default
  # ActiveRecord::Migrator.up(&lsquo;db/migrate&rsquo;) # use migrations
end
silence_stream(STDOUT, &amp;setup_sqlite_db)
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hitting the middle ground between classicist and mockist TDD]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/hitting-the-middle-ground-between-classicist-and-mockist-tdd/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-18T08:55:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/hitting-the-middle-ground-between-classicist-and-mockist-tdd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/mocksArentStubs.html">Martin Fowler&rsquo;s point of view</a>, I must have been a mockist. With using mocks extensively comes quite a few advantages :</p>

<ul>
<li>test failures often pinpoint the falsy code</li>
<li>easier test organisation mimicking that of the code</li>
<li>faster tests</li>
<li>simpler test initialization</li>
</ul>


<p>Mocks also have their own problems, but mostly :</p>

<ul>
<li>especialy with dynamicaly typed languages, a mock for class A might not implement the same methods than the real class A, but the test might be passing though ! This ampers refactoring with a longer feedback loop and mock setup rewriting</li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s what always bothered me. Eventually I tried a combinaison of techniques that seem to work well together and provides most of the best of both worlds.</p>

<ul>
<li>extensive use of factories (with <a href="https://github.com/thoughtbot/factory_girl">FactoryGirl</a>) to simplify setup</li>
<li>use of an <a href="http://www.sqlite.org/inmemorydb.html">in memory sqlite database</a> to get a fast full working db</li>
<li>implement fully functional fakes for some parts of the system</li>
<li>carefull use of mocks, inspired from <a href="http://blog.rubybestpractices.com/posts/gregory/052-issue-20-thoughts-on-mocking.html">Gregory Brown&rsquo;s thoughts on mocks</a>

<ul>
<li>when a test is too slow</li>
<li>to cut off a dependency to a subsystem that is not available in a unit test</li>
<li>to simplify overly long test data setup</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>use of test proxies (as in <a href="https://github.com/rr/rr">rr</a>) to inject specific behaviour or to perform specific checks without modifying the rest of the program.</li>
</ul>


<p>Here is how I implemented this with rspec :</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/philou/5894144.js"></script>


<p>With all this in place, it is most of the time possible to write straightforward tests. For example here, only real objects are used. @order gets its value when Order.create! is called.</p>

<p>```ruby
it &ldquo;should create an order with the cart&rdquo; do
  capture_result_from(Order, :create!, into: :order)</p>

<p>  check_in_cart</p>

<p>  @order.should_not be_nil
  @order.cart.should == @cart
end
```</p>

<p>Maybe I should swith to rr &hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Display full backtraces in rspec]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/display-full-backtraces-in-rspec/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-07T06:51:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/display-full-backtraces-in-rspec</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I use <a href="http://rspec.info/">rspec</a> a lot. I thinks it&rsquo;s a great testing framework.</p>

<p>In order to get shorter error output, rspec cleans backtraces from outside code. Here are all the patterns that are removed from the full backtrace :</p>

<p><code>ruby
DEFAULT_BACKTRACE_PATTERNS = [
  /\/lib\d*\/ruby\//,
  /org\/jruby\//,
  /bin\//,
  %r|/gems/|,
  /spec\/spec_helper\.rb/,
  /lib\/rspec\/(core|expectations|matchers|mocks)/
]
</code></p>

<p>Most of the time, that&rsquo;s great. Sometimes though, we get messages that seem completly unrelated to the code. Even worse, we might get misleading messages, such as &ldquo;method called with unexpected number of arguments&rdquo; that does not refer to the code in the backtrace, but to some other library code &hellip;</p>

<p>I thought it would be nice if we could switch this cleaning off sometimes. Here is how I did this :</p>

<p>```ruby
RSpec.configure do |config|</p>

<p>  # RSpec automatically cleans stuff out of backtraces;
  # sometimes this is annoying when trying to debug something e.g. a gem
  if ENV[&lsquo;FULLBACKTRACES&rsquo;] == &lsquo;true&rsquo;</p>

<pre><code>config.backtrace_clean_patterns = []
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  # some other configuration here</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>This way, it is still possible to call rspec as before to get the standard behaviour, but it is now possible to specify the FULLBACKTRACES variable to get full backtraces.</p>

<p><code>
FULLBACKTRACES=true bundle exec rspec spec
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
