<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: agile | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/agile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-14T06:39:07+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How we used the improvement kata to gain 25% of productivity - Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-12T09:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/">previous post</a>, I described the productivity issue our team was facing. How retrospectives did not work, and how I started looking at the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">improvement kata</a>.</p>

<p>We had gone through the first phase of the improvement kata : set the end goal.</p>

<blockquote><p>Generating enough profit for the business while sticking to a sustainable pace.</p></blockquote>

<p>Time to start the second phase : Understand.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/question-light.jpeg" alt="Drawing of a question mark transforming into a light bulb" /></p>

<h2>Understand</h2>

<p>Where we really slower ? Or was it an illusion ?</p>

<p>When trying to understand, you have to start with the data you have. You continue digging until you get a deeper understanding of the situation.</p>

<h3>Velocity</h3>

<p>We started with available data : story points and velocity. For sure this is a pretty bad measure of productivity. (Note : we should never use velocity for performance appraisal) In our case though, it felt like a good starting proxy measure.</p>

<p>Here is our velocity curve over 2 years.</p>

<p><a href="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity.jpg"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity-small.jpg" alt="Velocity graph" /></a></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s obvious that something changed. There are 2 parts to this graph. The velocity dropped between sprint 54 and 16.01. That&rsquo;s a clue that our gut feeling was not completely wrong. Our productivity did change.</p>

<h3>Man days</h3>

<p>Our first hypothesis was that team members turnover was the cause. As with any team, some people came, and some people left. Let&rsquo;s superpose the man days and velocity curves.</p>

<p><a href="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity-vs-manpower.jpg"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity-vs-manpower-small.jpg" alt="Velocity vs Manpower graph" /></a></p>

<p>That could only explain <em>part</em> of the problem !</p>

<p>We tried to fine tune the man days curve. We took people&rsquo;s involvement in tasks outside of programming into account. We used coefficients depending on the developers' experience. That did not provide a better explanation.</p>

<p>We had to find another explanation.</p>

<h3>Velocity computation</h3>

<p>As I said earlier, velocity is not a measure of productivity. Any change in the way we were computing velocity would impact this curve.</p>

<p>We had kept photos and Trello boards of our <a href="/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">retrospectives meetings</a>. We searched them through for anything that could impact velocity. Here is what we found :</p>

<ul>
<li>At sprint 55, we decided to ditch the <a href="https://www.scrum.org/resources/deadly-disease-focus-factor">focus-factor</a></li>
<li>At sprint 61, we started to do regular <a href="/how-we-started-exploratory-testing/">exploratory-testing</a>. Exploratory testing discovers more bugs on top of user reported bugs. This made us spend more time on fixing bugs.</li>
<li>At sprint 62, as we opted for a <a href="https://medium.com/quality-functions/the-zero-bug-policy-b0bd987be684">No Bug policy</a> we decided not to count story points for bugs</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>💡Keep Photos and Trello boards of Retrospectives as a log of your working agreements changes</p></blockquote>

<p>The timings almost perfectly matched what we had observed in the first place. The question that came to our minds was :</p>

<blockquote><p>Are we spending too much time on bugs ?</p></blockquote>

<h2>Halfway through understanding</h2>

<p>This is how we started to dig into our situation. It&rsquo;s a good time to give you a bit of feedback about how we felt at that point.</p>

<p>It was the first time we tried the improvement kata. More than that, we did not find any tutorial or guides about how to run it. The only instructions we had were theoretical descriptions or super concrete examples. We had to bridge the gap and come up with our own way.</p>

<p>To summarize, we felt a bit lost, we had gathered data from here and there, and we did not know what to look at next. On top of that, the quality of the data we were collecting was not great. We were wondering if we would get anything out of these investigations.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/First-20-Hours-Learn-Anything/dp/1591846943/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1483258282&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+first+20+hours"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/the-first-20-hours.jpg" alt="The cover of the book 'The First 20 Hours'" /></a></p>

<p>It felt a bit like when I did the <a href="/how-i-got-my-feet-wet-with-machine-learning-with-the-first-20-hours/">20 hours experiment to learn anything</a>. We did exactly what had worked with the learning experiment : we pushed through !</p>

<blockquote><p>💡If you feel lost when doing something for the first time. Push through !</p></blockquote>

<p>In <a href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-3/">next week&rsquo;s post</a>, I&rsquo;ll continue to detail the &lsquo;understand&rsquo; phase. <a href="/blog/categories/first-improvement-kata-series/">The series</a> also gained an extra post, and will now be 5 posts long.</p>

<p>See you next week.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How we used the improvement kata to gain 25% of productivity - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-07T06:39:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are serious about continuous improvement, you should learn the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">improvement kata</a>.</p>

<p><a href="/blog/categories/retrospectives/">Retrospectives</a> are great to pick all the low hanging improvements. Once you&rsquo;ve caught up with the industry&rsquo;s best practices, retrospectives risk drying up. Untapped improvement opportunities likely still exist in your specific context. The improvement kata can find those.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-09-07-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/low-hanging-fruits.jpeg" alt="Low and high hangling fruits on a tree" /></p>

<p>Here is how we applied the improvement kata to gain 25% of productivity in my previous team.</p>

<h2>The Situation</h2>

<p>Thanks to repeated retrospectives, the team had been improving for 2 years. Retrospectives seemed like a silver bullet. We would discuss the current problems, grasp an underlying cause and pick a best practice. Most of the time, that fixed the problem.</p>

<p>Sometimes it did not work though. Even if the issue came back in a later retrospective, it would not survive a second scrutiny. In the previous two years, the team had transformed the way it worked. It adopted TDD, incremental refactoring, pair programming, remote work, automated performance testing and many others.</p>

<p>Lately though, things did not work so well. The team was struggling with productivity issues. The team was not slowing down, but the scope and complexity of the product had grown. Features were not getting out of the door as fast as they used to. We had the habit of prioritizing improvements and bug fixes over features. That used to improve the flow enough to get more and more feature done. It did not seem to work anymore.</p>

<p>We tried to tackle the issue in retrospectives. We would change the way we prioritized features &hellip; To be later bogged down by bugs, technical debt or bad tools. We would discuss that in retrospective, and decide to change the priorities again &hellip; The loop went on and on a few times.</p>

<p>We were getting nowhere.</p>

<h2>The improvement kata </h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s why I started to look for other ways to do continuous improvement. I stumbled upon a book called <a href="http://leanagilecamp.fr/">Small Lean Management Guide for Agile Teams</a>. The book is in french, but I wrote an <a href="/are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way/">english review</a>. I fell in love with the way the authors dug into the hard data of how they worked to understand and fix their problems.</p>

<p>To learn more about this technique, I read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Toyota-Kata-Managing-Improvement-Adaptiveness/dp/0071635238/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1504758735&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=toyota+kata">Toyota Kata</a>. It details two management tools used at Toyota : the improvement and coaching katas. Some say these are Toyota&rsquo;s special weapon. <em>The</em> thing that grew them from a small shop to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automotive_industry">largest car manufacturer in the world</a>.</p>

<p>They are katas because they are routines. They must be re-execute many times. The <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">improvement kata</a> should improve the flow of work. The <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Coaching_Kata.html">coaching kata</a> helps someone (or yourself) to learn the improvement kata. Every time we go through the kata, we also understand it better.</p>

<p>Here is how the improvement kata goes :</p>

<ol>
<li>Describe your end goal</li>
<li>Understand where you stand about this goal by measuring facts and data</li>
<li>Based on your end goal and the current situation, define where you&rsquo;d like to be in 3 months or less</li>
<li>Use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDCA">Plan-Do-Check-Act</a> to experiment your way to this new situation

<ol>
<li>Plan an experiment</li>
<li>Do this experiment</li>
<li>Check the results of this experiment</li>
<li>Act on these results. 

<ul>
<li>Either drop the experiment and plan a new one (go back to &lsquo;Plan&rsquo;).</li>
<li>Or spread the change at a larger scale.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>


<p><a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/Homepage.html"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-07-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/katapattern.jpg" alt="The Improvement Kata Pattern" /></a><div class="image-credits">Image from Mike Rother on <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/Homepage.html">Toyota Kata Website</a></div></p>

<p>The coaching kata is a way to coach someone into applying the improvement kata. The fun thing is that you can coach yourself ! The idea is to ask questions to the coachee to remind him of where he stands in his improvement kata.</p>

<p><a href="https://traccsolution.com/resources/coaching-infographic/"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-07-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/The-coaching-Kata-questions.jpg" alt="The Coaching Kata Questions" /></a></p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll find tons of details and material about these katas on the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/Homepage.html">Toyota Kata website</a>.</p>

<h2>Our end goal</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s how I started to apply the improvement kata in my team. I already had an idea of our end goal : to be more productive. To be more precise :</p>

<blockquote><p>Generating enough profit for the business while sticking to a sustainable pace.</p></blockquote>

<p>Retrospectives could not get us there. Would the improvement kata would succeed ?</p>

<p>This is the first part of a <a href="/blog/categories/first-improvement-kata-series/">series of 4 posts</a> relating our first use of the improvement kata. In the <a href="/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/">next post</a>, I&rsquo;ll explain what we did to understand the current situation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[eXtreme eXtreme Programming (2017)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/extreme-extreme-programming-2017/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-25T07:01:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/extreme-extreme-programming-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What would <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/">XP</a> look like if it was invented today ?</p>

<p>A few days ago, I stumbled upon these two talks that got me thinking about this question.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cGuTmOUdFbo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>




<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/h62n09XtS-A" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>So I looked deeper into the question, while sticking to the same <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/values.html">values</a> and principles. Here is what I came up with.</p>

<h2>Practices</h2>

<h3>Continuous Deployment</h3>

<p>Why should we only deliver at every iteration in 2017 ? <a href="https://blog.newrelic.com/2016/02/04/data-culture-survey-results-faster-deployment/">Lot&rsquo;s of companies</a> demonstrated how to deploy every commit to safely production. Amazon for example, <a href="http://www.zdnet.com/article/how-amazon-handles-a-new-software-deployment-every-second/">deploys new software every second</a> !</p>

<h3><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DevOps">DevOps</a>++</h3>

<p>As a team starts doing continuous deployment, devs get more and more involved in ops. This privileged view on the users&rsquo;s behaviour can turn devs into product experts. Why not push the logic further and make them <em>the</em> product guys as well ?</p>

<h3>Test in prod</h3>

<p>Continuous deployement opens up many opportunities. Deploying safely requires bulletproof rollbacks. Once devs take care of product, code and ops they can shortcut testing and directly <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/info/developer-blog/2016/dec/05/testing-in-production-how-we-combined-tests-with-monitoring">test in prod</a> with some users ! Rollback remains an option at any time.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/no_bugs.html">#NoBugs</a></h3>

<p>That seems like wishful thinking. The idea is to fix bugs as soon as they appear, but also to prevent them in the first place. Continuous Deployment requires great engineering practices, which enable this way of working. A story cannot be &ldquo;finished&rdquo; until test in prod is over, and bugs fixed.</p>

<h3>Kanban</h3>

<p>At its core, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban">Kanban</a> is a way to limit the work in progress. It&rsquo;s almost a side effect of the previous practices. <a href="https://medium.com/quality-functions/the-zero-bug-policy-b0bd987be684">#noBugs almost kills interruptions for rework</a>. On top of that, devs have full control on their end to end work, so why would they multitask ?</p>

<h3>#NoBacklog</h3>

<p>In <a href="https://gettingreal.37signals.com/">Getting Real</a>, basecamp guys said that their <a href="https://gettingreal.37signals.com/ch05_Start_With_No.php">default answer to any new feature request was &ldquo;No&rdquo;</a>. Only after the same thing got asked many times would they start thinking of it. Maintaining a long backlog is a waste of time. Dumping backlog items but the current ones saves time. Important ideas will always come up again later.</p>

<h3>#NoEstimates</h3>

<p>This one is famous already. <a href="https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/how-estimating-story-counts-worked-us">Some teams</a> have saved time by using story count instead of story points. What&rsquo;s the point anyway if the team is already :</p>

<ul>
<li>working as best as it can</li>
<li>on the most important thing</li>
<li>and deploying as soon as possible</li>
</ul>


<h3>Data Driven</h3>

<p>This is how to drive the system evolution. Instead of relying on projects, backlogs and predictions, use data. Data from user logs and interviews proves if a new feature is worth building or dumping. Exploring logs of internal tools can help to continuous improve.</p>

<h3>Lean startup &amp; Hackathons</h3>

<p>Incremental improvements, in either product or organization, is not enough. As <a href="http://timharford.com/">Tim Hardford</a> explained in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1250007550/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1250007550&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=1f1a29f9454328c6606e12b40399eb06">Adapt</a>, survival requires testing completely new ideas. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lean_startup">Lean startup</a> &amp; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hackathon">hackathons</a> experiments can do just that.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1250007550/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1250007550&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=1f1a29f9454328c6606e12b40399eb06"><img src="../imgs/2017-08-25-extreme-extreme-programming-2017/adapt.jpg" alt="The cover of the Adapt book" /></a></p>

<h3><a href="/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/">Improvement kata</a></h3>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toyota_Kata#The_Improvement_Kata">Improvement kata</a> is a way to drive long term continuous improvement. It&rsquo;s the main tool for that at Toyota (read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0071635238/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0071635238&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=93a84b0867a3e0f3dd915d87cba78b90">Toyota Kata</a> to learn more). It provides more time to think of the problem than a retrospective. It also fits perfectly in a data driven environment.</p>

<h3>Mob programming</h3>

<p>Pair programming is great for code quality and knowledge sharing. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mob_programming#cite_note-8">Mob programming</a> is the more extreme version of pairing where <em>all</em> the team codes together.</p>

<h3><a href="/throwing-code-away-frequently/">Throw code away frequently</a></h3>

<p>An alternative to refactoring with unit tests is throwaway and rewrite once it gets too bad. Companies have been doing that for years. I worked at a bank that used to throwaway and rewrite individual apps that were part of a larger system. It can be a huge waste of money if these sub systems are too large. Scaling down to individual classes or microservices could make this cost effective.</p>

<h3>Remote</h3>

<p>With access to a wider pool of talents, <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/remote-or-co-located.html">remote teams usually perform better</a>. It also makes everybody&rsquo;s life easier. Finally, teams have reported that mob &amp; remote programming <a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/distributed-teams-remote-collaboration">work great together</a>.</p>

<h2>Afterthought</h2>

<p>What&rsquo;s striking from this list is that it&rsquo;s not that far from the original XP ! For example, continuous deployment and generalists have always been part of it. Another point is that is not science fiction ! I found many teams reporting success with these practices on the internet ! A well-oiled XP team might very well get there through continuous improvement.</p>

<p>The more I look at it, the more XP stands as a unique lighthouse in the foggy Agile landscape.</p>

<p>As for me, I&rsquo;m not sure I&rsquo;d dare to swap TDD &amp; refactoring for throwaway &amp; rewrite. I&rsquo;m particularly worried about the complex domain specific heart of systems. Nothing prevents from using both strategies for different modules though.</p>

<p>I should give it a try on a side project with a microservice friendly language, such as Erlang or Elixir.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Remote energizer tips that will make your remote retrospectives rock]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/5-remote-energizer-tips-that-will-make-your-remote-retrospectives-rock/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-18T09:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/5-remote-energizer-tips-that-will-make-your-remote-retrospectives-rock</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you remember how people who are not used to the phone tend to shout in it, for the message to get far ? Read on and I&rsquo;ll explain how this silly habit will make your remote retrospectives great !</p>

<p>A typical retrospective starts with an energizing activity, or <a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/category/energizer/">energizer</a>. It&rsquo;s important for two reasons. First, people who don&rsquo;t speak during the first 5 minutes of a meeting are more likely to remain silent until the end. Second, getting everyone to do an energizing and fun activity sets the tone for a peaceful and creative time.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-08-18-5-remote-energizer-tips-that-will-make-your-remote-retrospectives-rock/remote-plus-retro.jpg" alt="Remote control + magnifying glass" /></p>

<h2>Our experiences with remote energizers</h2>

<p>When we started to do retrospectives at work, all the team was co located in Paris. There are tons of activities available on the internet to run effective energizers. We could do games like Fizz Buzz, or drawing based activities like <a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/collaborative-face-drawing/">face drawing</a> and <a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/visual-phone/">visual phone</a>. It was easy and fun.</p>

<p>A few years ago, <a href="https://ahmadatwi.me/">Ahmad Atwi</a> joined our team from Beirut. Our catalog of energizer shrank to a few activities that we could run remotely. On top of that, going through the remote medium made it more challenging for energizers to &hellip; energize ! With time and trial, we managed to understand what works and how to pick the right energizer for a remote team.</p>

<h2>Principles for remote energizers</h2>

<p>We have an Agile <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_Interest_Group">Special Interest Group</a> at <a href="https://www.murex.com/">Murex</a>, where volunteers meet to share things they find interesting. A few weeks ago, during one of these sessions, we discussed remote energizers in a <a href="http://leancoffee.org/">Lean Coffee</a>.</p>

<p>Here are the points we came up with.</p>

<ul>
<li>Question activities work great through <a href="https://trello.com/agileretrospectives">Trello</a>. <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0977616649/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0977616649&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=2b51890b8e8909b6f2223ca69ec3b26f">Agile Retrospectives, making good teams great</a> details such a Check-In activity. The typical questions sound like &ldquo;Coming into this retrospective, if you were a car, what kind of car would you be ?&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0977616649/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0977616649&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=2b51890b8e8909b6f2223ca69ec3b26f"><img src="../imgs/2017-08-18-5-remote-energizer-tips-that-will-make-your-remote-retrospectives-rock/agile-retros.jpg" alt="The Agile Retrospectives, making good teams great book cover" /></a></p>

<ul>
<li>If they are enough teammates at every place, energizers that play in small groups will work well. For example, it would be easy to organize a <a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/the-balloon-battle/">balloon battle</a> or a <a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/back-to-back/">back to back</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/remote-or-co-located.html"><img src="../imgs/2017-08-18-5-remote-energizer-tips-that-will-make-your-remote-retrospectives-rock/multi-site-team.png" alt="The Agile Retrospectives, making good teams great book cover" /></a></p>

<ul>
<li>It&rsquo;s also easy to use variations on an activity that proved effective. For example, explore new kinds of questions. It&rsquo;s even ok to repeat verbatim an activity from time to time.</li>
<li>Replace energizing by team building. Team building is particularly important for remote teams. Instead of engaging activities, it&rsquo;s ok to have everyone share a personal anecdote. By knowing each other better, the team can build trust. For example, you could introduce such an activity with : &ldquo;What book would you bring on a desert island ? Why ?&rdquo;</li>
<li>One last thing we came up with my colleague <a href="https://twitter.com/mc_moe">Morgan Kobeissi</a> to energize a remote meeting is to YELL. The idea is to ask everyone to answer a question while standing and yelling. A question could be &ldquo;How long have you been working and what companies did you work for ?&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="../imgs/2017-08-18-5-remote-energizer-tips-that-will-make-your-remote-retrospectives-rock/yell.jpg" alt="Someone yelling in a kid's 'can-phone'" /></p>

<p>Remote work is here to stay. More and more teams are facing similar difficulties. We need to invent new work practices. If you discovered new ways to run remote energizer, please share them with a comment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't stick to TDD's Red-Green-Refactor loop to the letter]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/dont-stick-to-tdds-red-green-refactor-loop-to-the-letter/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-28T15:52:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/dont-stick-to-tdds-red-green-refactor-loop-to-the-letter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As long as you are writing your tests before your code and doing regular refactoring, you are doing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development">TDD</a> !</p>

<p>The Red &ndash; Green &ndash; Refactor loop is useful to introduce TDD to new developers. Different loops can be more effective in real world situation.</p>

<p>The Red &ndash; Green &ndash; Refactor loop is not a dogma !</p>

<p><a href="http://www.natpryce.com/"><img src="../imgs/2017-06-28-dont-stick-to-tdds-red-green-refactor-loop-to-the-letter/red-green-refactor.jpg" alt="The famous red, green, refactor TDD loop" /></a></p>

<h2>Refactor &ndash; Red &ndash; Green</h2>

<p>When I work on a story, I very often keep a TODO list next to my desk. I use it to keep track of the next steps, the edge cases to test, the code smells and refactorings to do.</p>

<p>When I get to the end of the story, all that remains of this list is a few refactorings. Very often, I don&rsquo;t do them !</p>

<p>With the feature working, doing these refactorings feels like violation of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it">YAGNI</a>. Next time we&rsquo;ll have to work on this part of the code, we&rsquo;ll have a story to serve as guide to which refactorings to do.</p>

<p>The same thing is effective at the unit test scale. It&rsquo;s easier to refactor when you know the test you want to add. Refactor to make this test easy to write !</p>

<p>Here is an example with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fizz_buzz">Fizz Buzz</a></p>

<p>```java
static int fizzBuzz(int number) {
   return number;
}</p>

<p>@Test public void
it_is_1_for_1() {
   assertThat(fizzBuzz(1)).isEqualTo(1);
}</p>

<p>@Test public void
it_is_2_for_2() {
   assertThat(fizzBuzz(2)).isEqualTo(2);
}
```</p>

<p>Here is the test I&rsquo;d like to add. </p>

<p><code>java
@Test public void
it_is_Fizz_for_3() {
   assertThat(fizzBuzz(3)).isEqualTo("Fizz");
}
</code></p>

<p>Unfortunately, fizzBuzz needs to return a String instead of an integer for it to compile. That&rsquo;s when I would refactor before adding the new test.</p>

<p>```java
static String fizzBuzz(int number) {
   return Integer.toString(number);
}</p>

<p>@Test public void
it_is_1_for_1() {
   assertThat(fizzBuzz(1)).isEqualTo(&ldquo;1&rdquo;);
}</p>

<p>@Test public void
it_is_2_for_2() {
   assertThat(fizzBuzz(2)).isEqualTo(&ldquo;2&rdquo;);
}
```</p>

<p>In the end, this loop is very like the classic TDD loop :</p>

<p><code>
red-green-refactor-red-green-refactor-red-green-refactor.............
..........refactor-red-green-refactor-red-green-refactor-red-green...
</code></p>

<p>A bit more YAGNI, that&rsquo;s all.</p>

<h2>Red &ndash; Better Red &ndash; Green &ndash; Refactor</h2>

<p>A few weeks ago, <a href="/speed-up-the-tdd-feedback-loop-with-better-assertion-messages/">I wrote about error messages in unit tests</a>. To summarize, extra work on error messages reduces the testing feedback loop.</p>

<p>We can translate this focus on error messages into an extra TDD step. Whatever the TDD loop you are using, you can add this step after the Red step.</p>

<h2><del>Red</del> &ndash; Green &ndash; Refactor &ndash; Red &ndash; Green</h2>

<p>Sometimes, it makes sense to refactor before fixing the test. The idea is to rely on the existing tests to prepare the code to fix the new test in one line.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take our Fizz Buzz example again. Imagine we finished the kata, when we decide to tweak the rules and try Fizz Buzz Bang. We should now print Bang on multiples of 7.</p>

<p>Here is our starting point :</p>

<p>```java
static String fizzBuzz(int number) {
   if (multipleOf(number, 3)) {
      return &ldquo;Fizz&rdquo;;
   }
   if (multipleOf(number, 5)) {
      return &ldquo;Buzz&rdquo;;
   }
   if (multipleOf(number, 3*5)) {
      return &ldquo;FizzBuzz&rdquo;;
   }   
   return Integer.toString(number);
}</p>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<p>@Test public void
it_is_Bang_for_7() {
   assertThat(fizzBuzz(7)).isEqualTo(&ldquo;Bang&rdquo;);
}
```</p>

<p>I could go through all the hoops, 7, 14, then 3<em>7, 5</em>7 and finally 3<em>5</em>7 &hellip; By now, I should know the music though !</p>

<p>What I would do in this case is :</p>

<ul>
<li>first to comment the new failing test to get back to green</li>
<li>refactor the code to prepare for the new code</li>
<li>uncomment the failing test</li>
<li>fix it</li>
</ul>


<p>In our example, here is the refactoring I would do</p>

<p>```java
static String fizzBuzz(int number) {
   String result = &ldquo;&rdquo;;
   result += multipleWord(number, 3, &ldquo;Fizz&rdquo;);
   result += multipleWord(number, 5, &ldquo;Buzz&rdquo;);
   if (result.isEmpty()) {
      result = Integer.toString(number);
   }
   return result;
}</p>

<p>private static String multipleWord(int number, int multiple, String word) {
   if (multipleOf(number, multiple)) {
      return word;
   }
   return &ldquo;&rdquo;;
}</p>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<p>//@Test public void
//it_is_Bang_for_7() {
//   assertThat(fizzBuzz(7)).isEqualTo(&ldquo;Bang&rdquo;);
//}
```</p>

<p>From there, fixing the test is dead simple.</p>

<p>In practice I find this loop very useful. At local scale as we saw but it&rsquo;s also a great way to refactor your architecture at larger scale.</p>

<p>One downsize is that if you are not careful, it might lead to over-engineering. Be warned, keep an eye on that !</p>

<p>Last caveat : not all TDD interviewers like this technique &hellip;</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t obsess</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not because you are not following the Red Green Refactor loop to the letter that you are not doing TDD.</p>

<p>An interesting point is that these variations to the TDD loop are combinable ! Experienced TDD practitioners can jump from one to the other without even noticing.</p>

<p><a href="https://blog.acolyer.org/2017/06/13/a-dissection-of-the-test-driven-development-process-does-it-really-matter-to-test-first-or-test-last/">This paper</a> argues that as long as you write the tests along (before or after) the code, you get the same benefit. That&rsquo;s not going to make me stop writing my tests first, but it is interesting. That would mean that even a Code &ndash; Test &ndash; Refactor loop would be ok if it is fast enough !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
