<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: software | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/software/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-03T20:15:22+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to use Hackernews and Reddit for blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-05T04:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I posted my latest article <a href="/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/">Is There Any Room for the Not-Passionate Developer ?</a> on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/">Hackernews</a> and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/programming/">Reddit Programming</a>. The post stayed on the fist page for a while, and I got a lot of traffic. If you are yourself blogging, you might be interested to know how it occurred, and what I learned in the process.</p>

<h2>How it started</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-05-how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging/soft-skills.jpg" title="The cover of &lsquo;Soft Skills, the software developer&rsquo;s life manual&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1473135683&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=soft+skills">Soft Skills, the software developer&rsquo;s life manual</a> John Somnez explains that posting your blog articles on HN or Reddit might bring you a ton of traffic, but that comments can be hard to swallow at time. Within a few hours of writing my blog post it had generated some positive activity on twitter (favorites and retweets) from my regular followers. That&rsquo;s a good sign that the post is good enough. As I had promised myself in such case, I submitted the post to both HN and Reddit.</p>

<h2>What happened ?</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-05-how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging/google-analytics.jpg" title="A Google Analytics screenshot, with the traffic spike" ></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know for sure on Reddit, but I know my post stayed on the first page of HN for a few hours, it even went up to the third place for a while. In the process I got a lot of traffic, a lot more than I am used to. I also got a ton of comments, on HN, Reddit and directly on my post. John Somnez had warned that comments on HN and Reddit can be very harsh, so I went through these quickly, took notes about the points that seemed interesting, but I only responded to comments on my website.</p>

<p>Overall, the comments were pretty interesting though, and brought a lot of valid points. I&rsquo;m planning to write a &lsquo;response&rsquo; article to take all these into perspective.</p>

<p>Most of the traffic was made in the day I submitted my post, but I had more traffic than usual for 2 or 3 days. Since then, the traffic has settled down, but I now get between 2 and 5 times more traffic than I typically had on a daily basis ! An online Taiwanese tech magazine also asked me the permission to translate <a href="http://www.inside.com.tw/2016/08/05/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer">my post in Chinese</a> !</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure about the performance of my website during the traffic spike. I&rsquo;m using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> to statically generated html on <a href="https://pages.github.com/">Github Pages</a>, so that should be fine. I am also using a custom domain, and I need to make sure my <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7738293">DNS is correctly configured</a> for this to perform well.</p>

<h2>Advice for bloggers</h2>

<p>So here is what I am going to do regarding HN and Reddit in the future :</p>

<ol>
<li>It can bring so much traffic and backlinks that I&rsquo;ll definitely continue to submit blog posts from time to time</li>
<li>For the moment, I&rsquo;ll stick to only submitting the articles from which I already received good feedbacks, I don&rsquo;t want to get a bad karma or reputation on these websites</li>
<li>I might submit old articles that gathered good reviews at the time I wrote them</li>
<li>Concerning comments, I&rsquo;ll try to grow an even thicker skin. Maybe at some point I&rsquo;ll try to answer on HN or Reddit</li>
</ol>


<p>Of course, depending how this works, I will adapt !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to prepare a new Ruby env in 3 minutes using Docker]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-prepare-a-new-ruby-env-in-3-minutes-using-docker/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-17T05:21:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-prepare-a-new-ruby-env-in-3-minutes-using-docker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One or two weeks ago, I registered to the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/fr-FR/Paris-Ruby-Workshop/">Paris Ruby Workshop Meetup</a> and needed a Ruby env. I have been using <a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a> quite a lot to isolate my different dev envs from each other and from my main machine. As I&rsquo;ve been digging more into <a href="http://www.docker.com">Docker</a> lately, I thought I&rsquo;d simply use Docker and Docker Compose instead.</p>

<p>I turned out to be dead simple. All that is needed is a <code>docker-compose.yml</code> file to define the container, record the shared volume and set a bundle path inside it :</p>

<p>```yaml
rubybox:
  image: ruby:2.3
  command: bash
  working_dir: /usr/src/app
  environment:</p>

<pre><code>BUNDLE_PATH: 'vendor/bundle'
</code></pre>

<p>  volumes:</p>

<pre><code>- '.:/usr/src/app'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Without the custom bundle path, bundled gems would be installed elsewhere in the container, and lost at every restart.</p>

<p>To use the Rubybox, just type <code>docker-compose run rubybox</code> and you&rsquo;ll get a shell from within your ruby machine, where you can do everything you want.</p>

<p>In fact, I found the thing so useful, that I created the <a href="https://github.com/philou/rubybox">Rubybox</a> git repo to simplify cloning and reusing. I&rsquo;ve already cloned it at least 3 times since then !</p>

<p><code>bash
git clone git@github.com:philou/rubybox.git
cd rubybox
docker-compose run rubybox
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When the Boy Scout Rule Fails]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-02T05:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-02-when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/boy-scout-rule.jpg" title="An illustration of the boy scout rule" ></p>

<p>Here goes the <a href="http://programmer.97things.oreilly.com/wiki/index.php/The_Boy_Scout_Rule">boy scout rule</a> :</p>

<blockquote><p>Always check a module in cleaner than when you checked it out.</p></blockquote>

<p>Unfortunately, this alone does not guarantee to keep the technical debt under control. What can we do then ?</p>

<h2>Why the boy scout rule is not enough</h2>

<p>I can easily think of a few issues that are not covered by the boy scout rule.</p>

<h3>It only deals with local problems</h3>

<p>In it&rsquo;s statement, the boy scout rule is local and does not address large scale design or architecture issues. Applying the boy scout rule keeps files well written, using with clear and understandable code. From a larger perspective though, it does very little or slow improvement to the overall design.</p>

<p>These large scale refactorings are very difficult to deal with using the boy scout rule alone. It could be done but would require to share the refactoring goal with all the team, and then track its progress, while at the same time dealing with all the other subjects of the project. That&rsquo;s starting to sound like multitasking to me.</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;s skill dependent</h3>

<p>Another point about the boy scout rule (and to be fair, about any refactoring technique) is that programmers will be able to clean the code only as much as their skills allow them to !</p>

<p>Imagine what would happen when a new master developer arrives in a team of juniors, he&rsquo;d spot a lot of technical debt and would suggest improvements and ways to clean the code. Code that was thought of as very clean would suddenly be downgraded to junk !</p>

<p>The point here is that the boy scout rule cannot guarantee that you have no technical debt, because you don&rsquo;t know how much you have !</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s where the debt metaphor reaches its limits and flips to some productivity investment. By investing time to perform some newly discovered refactoring, you could get a productivity boost !</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470200818&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-02-when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/ddd.jpg" title="The cover of &ldquo;Domain Driven Design&rdquo;" ></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470200818&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design">Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software</a>, Eric Evans calls this knowledge distillation. He means that little by little, the team gains better understanding of the domain, sometimes going through what he calls a &lsquo;breakthrough&rsquo;. These breakthroughs often promote existing code to technical debt &hellip;</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;s context dependent</h3>

<p>Developers alone are not the only one responsible for creating technical debt. Changes to the environment also do.</p>

<p>For example, if the market conditions change, and that new expectations for the product are slowly becoming the norm, your old perfectly working system becomes legacy and technical debt. As an example, let&rsquo;s examine what happened to the capital markets software industry in response to the 2008 crisis.</p>

<ul>
<li>The sector became a lot more regulated</li>
<li>Risk control is moving from nightly batches to real time</li>
<li>The demand for complex (and risky) contracts decreased</li>
<li>As a consequence, trading on simpler contracts exploded</li>
</ul>


<p>All these elements combined invalidated existing architectures !</p>

<p>New technologies also create technical debt. Think the switch from mainframe to the web.</p>

<h2>What do we need then ?</h2>

<p>Should we stop using the boy scout rule ? Surely not, it would be a total non-sense. Submitting clean and readable code is a must.</p>

<p>But it is not enough. If you have spotted some large scale refactoring that could bring some improvement, we should do what a fund manager would do :</p>

<ol>
<li>Estimate the return on investment</li>
<li>If it is good enough, do it now</li>
</ol>


<p>Obviously, large refactorings should also be split into smaller <del>value adding</del> cost reducing items. But then what ?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nature-Software-Development-Simple-Valuable/dp/1941222374/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470290668&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+nature+of+software+development"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-02-when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/nature-of-software.jpg" title="The cover of &ldquo;The Nature of Software Development&rdquo;" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nature-Software-Development-Simple-Valuable/dp/1941222374/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470290668&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+nature+of+software+development">The Nature of Software Development</a> Ron Jefferies says that we need a unique value-based prioritization strategy for everything, including technical improvements. Once you&rsquo;ve got that, there&rsquo;s no sense in splitting and embedding your refactoring in other tasks, this will just increase your work in progress, reducing your throughput and cycle time.</p>

<p>Frankly, I think that&rsquo;s easier said than done. I can <em>think</em> of two ways :</p>

<ul>
<li>As Ron Jefferies tends to say, have a jelled-cross-functional team discuss and prioritize collectively</li>
<li>As <a href="http://reinertsenassociates.com/technical-debt-adding-math-metaphor/">Don Reintersen</a> advocates, use an <a href="/a-plan-for-technical-debt-lean-software-development-part-7/">economical framework</a> to estimate the return on investment</li>
</ul>


<p>At least that&rsquo;s a starting point !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is There Any Room For The Not-Passionate Developer ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-26T06:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Passionate-Programmer-Remarkable-Development-Pragmatic-ebook/dp/B00AYQNR5U/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470025727&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+passionate+programmer"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-07-26-is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/passionate-programmer.jpg" title="The cover of The Passionate Programmer book" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Rework-Jason-Fried/dp/0307463745/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1469597091&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=rework">Rework</a>, <a href="https://basecamp.com/">Basecamp</a> guys David Heinemeier Hansson and Jason Fried advise to <a href="https://signalvnoise.com/posts/902-fire-the-workaholics">&ldquo;Fire the workaholics&rdquo;</a>, while in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Zero-One-Notes-Startups-Future/dp/0804139296/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1469801854&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=zero+to+one">Zero to One</a> Peter Thiel argues that great working conditions (as described within Google for example) result from 10x technological advantages, not the other way round.</p>

<p>Back in 1983, Bill Gates said :</p>

<blockquote><p>You have to think it’s a fun industry. You’ve got to go home at night and open your
mail and find computer magazines or else you’re not going to be on the same
wavelength as the people [at Microsoft].</p></blockquote>

<p>Where do we stand now ? Do you need to live and breath programming to remain a good developer ?</p>

<h2>What about the 40h per week rule ?</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-07-26-is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/productivity.jpg" title="A graph of the productivity when working overtime" ></p>

<p>Studies have repeatedly demonstrated that 40h per week is the most productive work load, but in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Outliers-Story-Success-Malcolm-Gladwell/dp/0316017930">Outliers, the Story of Success</a> Malcolm Gladwell explains that getting fast to the 10000 hours of practice is a required road to success. As my Aïkido professor says, the more you practice, the better you get &hellip;</p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1469801992&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=soft+skills+the+software+developer%27s+life+manual">Soft Skills: The software developer&rsquo;s life manual</a> John Somnez also makes the point for hard work, that while he long believed that smart work would be enough, it&rsquo;s only when he put more in that he managed to drastically change his career.</p>

<p>During an <a href="http://calacanis.com/2008/03/07/how-to-save-money-running-a-startup-17-really-good-tips/">argument</a>, DHH argued in favor of work life balance whereas Jason Calacanis said that working in a startup had to be an all-in activity. In the end, they agreed that what matters is passion.</p>

<p>From my own experience, whenever I work on something I am passionate about :</p>

<ul>
<li>I am more productive</li>
<li>I feel energized rather than dulled by the work</li>
</ul>


<p>When I look around me, all the great developers I know are passionate and putting in more than 40 hours per week in programming. I also noticed that passion and efforts have always been pretty good indicators of future skills.</p>

<p>But then, how do passionate people manage to remain productive when working more than 40 hours per week ?</p>

<h2>What about the under the shower idea ?</h2>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Thinking-Learning-Refactor-Programmers/dp/1934356050">Pragmatic Thinking and Learning: Refactor Your Wetware (Pragmatic Programmers)</a> (which is a great book BTW), Andy Hunt explains that our R-mode works in the background, and needs time away from the task at hand to come up with &ldquo;out of the box&rdquo; creative solutions.</p>

<p>XP argues for a <a href="http://www.sustainablepace.net/what-is-sustainable-pace">sustainable pace</a>, but at the same time, Uncle Bob says that we should put in 60 hours (40 for employer, and 20 for yourself) of work per week to become and remain &lsquo;professionals&rsquo; (I guess that&rsquo;s from <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Clean-Coder-Conduct-Professional-Programmers/dp/0137081073/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470026034&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=the+clean+code">The Clean Coder</a> if I remember correctly).</p>

<p>On my side, 6 to 8 solid hours of pair-programming on the same subject is the most I can do before becoming a <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?NetNegativeProducingProgrammer">Net Negative Producing Programmer</a>. But I can do more programming per day if I work on a side project at the same time though !</p>

<p>I guess that&rsquo;s how passionate people do it, they have different topics outside of their main work :</p>

<ul>
<li>they read books about programming</li>
<li>they have their own <a href="http://www.sideprojectbook.com/">side projects</a></li>
<li>they read articles about programming</li>
<li>they might maintain a programming blog</li>
<li>they might attend, organize or speak at meetup</li>
</ul>


<p>Most of the time, this does not make for more work, but rather for more learning. If I&rsquo;ve noticed that all the great programmers around me are passionate and strive to improve at their craft, I&rsquo;ve also noticed that overworked workaholics usually aren&rsquo;t very productive.</p>

<h2>Special challenges for mums and dads</h2>

<p>I think that Bill Gates 1983 statement still holds. If you are not passionate about programming, you&rsquo;ll have a hard time remaining and succeeding as a programmer in the long run.</p>

<p>The great thing about all this passion is that we can experience an energized work environment, always bubbling with change and novelty. On the flip side, keeping up with all is not always easy.</p>

<p>As we developers gain more experience, we tend to loose patience with everything that just feels as a pain in the ass, and will want :</p>

<ul>
<li>Powerful languages and technologies</li>
<li>An efficient working environment</li>
<li>Smart colleagues</li>
</ul>


<p>Unfortunately, that might also be the moment in your life when you become a parent, and you&rsquo;ll want  a stable income to sustain your family and some time to spend with your kids.</p>

<p>That is when things get tricky. Neither can you jump ship for the next cool and risky startup where you&rsquo;ll do great things, nor can you find enough time moonlighting to improve your skills &hellip; To add pain to injury, even with 10 years of experience in various languages and technologies, most companies won&rsquo;t look at your resume unless it contains good keywords &hellip; It looks like the developer&rsquo;s version of  <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Innovators-Dilemma-Revolutionary-Change-Business/dp/0062060244/ref=sr_1_sc_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470024448&amp;sr=8-1-spell&amp;keywords=the+innovator%27s+dilemns">The Innovator&rsquo;s Dilemna</a> !</p>

<p>Lack of passion and parenthood might partially explain why people stop being developers after a while. I can quickly think of 2 bad consequences of this :</p>

<ul>
<li>We tend to reinvent the wheel quite a lot (I&rsquo;m looking at you, .js frameworks &hellip;)</li>
<li>We might be meta ignoring (ignoring that we ignore) people skills that could make us all more efficient</li>
</ul>


<p><em><a href="http://www.inside.com.tw/2016/08/05/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer">Chinese translation</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Years of Blogging About Software]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/5-years-of-blogging-about-software/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-27T04:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/5-years-of-blogging-about-software</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>5 years ago, I started blogging. I started really casually, my posts were personal reminders and notes rather than real well thought of articles. Nevertheless, it did me great good :</p>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve been invited to talk at meetups</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ve had the joy of seeing some articles being tweeted many times</li>
<li>I received interesting job offers from all over the world</li>
</ul>


<p>6 months ago, after reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1467000033&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=soft+skills">Soft Skills: The software developer&rsquo;s life manual</a>, I set up the practice of writing at least one article per week, and here is my (very encouraging) graph of sessions since then:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-27-5-years-of-blogging-about-software/analytics.jpg" title="The steadily increase curve of the sessions on my blog per month" ></p>

<h1>Excuses Why Not To Blog</h1>

<p>Here is a collection of the (bad) excuses you&rsquo;ll often hear people say for not blogging :</p>

<blockquote><p>I don&rsquo;t know how to write &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>Blogging regularly is actually a pretty good way to improve your writing skills. As usual, the key is to fake it until you make it.</p>

<blockquote><p>I&rsquo;m not into this social media stuff &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>You don&rsquo;t need to share anything personal on your software blog. In the end, your blog is a professional tool.</p>

<blockquote><p>I don&rsquo;t have anything interesting to say &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>They are others in the same situation as you who would like to see more posts about the kind of uninteresting things you just discovered. Wouldn’t you have liked someone to have written the newby article about « how to do XXX » you just spent 3 days to crack ?</p>

<blockquote><p>I don&rsquo;t have the time &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>Make it ! Time is never found, it is made. In the end, it’s just a matter of prioritization.</p>

<p>Obviously, there are other totally valid reasons why not to blog, but I&rsquo;ll assume you&rsquo;re able to recognize those.</p>

<h1>Why Would You Blog ?</h1>

<p>On the other side, if you jump into blogging, you can expect a lot of returns :</p>

<ul>
<li>First thing is that you&rsquo;ll obviously gain more visibility. I&rsquo;ve got readers from all over the world, and my articles are sometimes re-tweeted many times.</li>
<li>You&rsquo;ll improve your writing skills. Writing skills turn out to be unexpectedly important for <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9LfmrkyP81M">software writers</a> !</li>
<li>In order to lay down your ideas about something, you&rsquo;ll need to dig a bit more into. It is said to be the last step to learning.</li>
<li>It can act as a personal documentation. I used to write mine as a how-to notepad on which I could refer later on.</li>
<li>If you have a day job, you can re-post your articles there. You should gain extra visibility and expose the company to new ideas.</li>
</ul>


<h1>How to start</h1>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve decided that you want to blog, starting should not be an issue.</p>

<h2>Pick a platform</h2>

<p>There are a lot of blogging platforms out there. For programmers, I would recommend a few though :</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-06-27-5-years-of-blogging-about-software/platforms.jpg" title="Logos of my recommended blogging platforms" ></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Platform </th>
<th> Pros </th>
<th> Cons</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> </td>
<td> Free, Open Source, Github hosting, static HTML generation, markdown &amp; Git based, made for programmers </td>
<td> Theming can be rocky</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://medium.com/">Medium</a>    </td>
<td> Free, no setup, good looking, simple to use </td>
<td> It&rsquo;s a private company, so it could close some day ! It happened to <a href="http://www.posterous.com">postero.us</a> (I remember, I was there …)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://posthaven.com/">Posthaven</a> </td>
<td> Created by the founders of postero.us, sustainable, guarantees to keep it live for ever, can post by email ! </td>
<td> Nothing special for programmers, 5$ / month</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://logdown.com/">Logdown</a>   </td>
<td> Looks like a hosted version of Octopress, without the hassle ! </td>
<td> 50$/year</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Then, it&rsquo;s up to you !</p>

<h2>Start with how-to articles</h2>

<p>When I started my blog, it was mostly has a personal how-to reference. It allowed me to come back to it and find out how I did something last time. I thought that if it was important to me, it must be important to others as-well !</p>

<h2>Blog regularly</h2>

<p>Blogging every week made a huge difference to me. My traffic went from erratic to steadily increasing. I am currently observing a 11% traffic increase per month. This means that it nearly quadruples every year : I&rsquo;m not going to stop now !</p>

<h2>Integrate with the web</h2>

<p>This boils down to social networks and analytics. Obviously, you&rsquo;ll want to use Google Analytics to see how people are reading your content. I&rsquo;m using the venerable <a href="https://feedburner.google.com">Feedburner</a> to automatically post my new articles on <a href="https://twitter.com">twitter</a>. There&rsquo;s an option to use your post categories as hashtags, be sure to make it works, it brings a lot of traffic.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s all up to you now !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
