<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: software | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/software/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-05-31T07:16:20+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speed up the TDD feedback loop with better assertion messages]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/speed-up-the-tdd-feedback-loop-with-better-assertion-messages/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-29T06:37:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/speed-up-the-tdd-feedback-loop-with-better-assertion-messages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a rather widespread <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development">TDD</a> practice to have a <a href="https://softwareengineering.stackexchange.com/questions/7823/is-it-ok-to-have-multiple-asserts-in-a-single-unit-test">single assertion per test</a>. The goal is to have faster feedback loop while coding. When a test fails, it can be for a single reason, making the diagnostic faster.</p>

<p>The same goes with the test names. When a test fails, a readable test name in the report simplifies the diagnostic. Some testing frameworks allow the use of plain strings as test names. In others, people use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naming_convention_(programming">underscores</a>#Multiple-word_identifiers) instead of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camel_case">CamelCase</a> in test names.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-05-29-speed-up-the-tdd-feedback-loop-with-better-assertion-messages/rubymine.jpg" alt="RubyMine test report" /></p>

<h2>A 4th step in TDD: Fail, <em>Fail better</em>, Pass, Refactor</h2>

<h3>First, make it fail</h3>

<p>Everyone knows that Test Driven Development starts by making the test fail. Let me illustrate why.</p>

<p>A few years ago, I was working on a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_Sharp_%28programming_language%29">C#</a> project. We were using TDD and <a href="https://github.com/nunit/nunit">NUnit</a>. At some point, while working on a story, I forgot to make my latest test fail. I wrote some code to pass this test, I ran the tests, and they were green. When I was almost done, I tried to plug all the parts together, but nothing was working. I had to start the debugger to understand what was going wrong. At first, I could not understand why the exact thing I had unit tested earlier was now broken. After more investigation I discovered that I had forgotten to make my test public. NUnit only runs public tests &hellip;</p>

<p>If I had made sure my test was failing, I would have spotted straightaway that it was not ran.</p>

<h3>Then make it fail &hellip; better !</h3>

<p>I lived the same kind of story with wrong failures many times. The test fails, but for a bad reason. I move on to implement the code to fix it &hellip; but it still does not pass ! Only then do I check the error message and discover the real thing to fix. Again, it&rsquo;s a transgression to baby steps and to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it">YAGNI</a> principle. If the tests is small, that might not be too much of an issue. But it can be if the test is big, or if the real fix deprecates all the premature work.</p>

<h3>Strive for explicit error message</h3>

<p>The idea is to make sure to have good enough error messages before moving on to the &ldquo;pass&rdquo; step.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Growing-Object-Oriented-Software-Guided-Tests/dp/0321503627/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1495080583&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=growing+object-oriented+software+guided+by+tests"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-29-speed-up-the-tdd-feedback-loop-with-better-assertion-messages/growing.jpg" alt="Cover of GOOSGT" /></a></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s nothing groundbreaking about this practice. It&rsquo;s not a step as explicit as the other 3 steps of TDD. The first place I read about this idea was in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Growing-Object-Oriented-Software-Guided-Tests/dp/0321503627/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1495080583&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=growing+object-oriented+software+guided+by+tests">Growing Object Oriented Software Guided By Tests</a>.</p>

<h2>How to improve your messages</h2>

<h3>Readable code</h3>

<p>Some test frameworks print out the failed assertion code to the test failure report. Others, especially in dynamic languages, use the assertion code itself to deduce an error message. If your test code is readable enough, your error messages might be as well !</p>

<p>For example, with <a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org">Ruby</a> <a href="http://rspec.info/">RSpec</a> testing framework :</p>

<p><code>ruby
it "must have an ending" do
  expect(Vote.new(team: @daltons)).to be_valid
end
</code></p>

<p>Yield the following error :</p>

<p>```
expected #<Vote ...> to be valid, but got errors: Ending can&rsquo;t be blank</p>

<p>```</p>

<h3>Pass in a message argument</h3>

<p>Sometimes, readable code is not enough to provide good messages. All testing frameworks I know provide some way to pass in a custom error message. That&rsquo;s often a cheap and straightforward way to clarify your test reports.</p>

<p>```ruby
  it &ldquo;should not render anything&rdquo; do</p>

<pre><code>post_create
expect(response.code).to eq(HTTP::Status::OK.to_s),
                         "expected the post to succeed, but got http status #{response.code}"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
```</p>

<p>Yields</p>

<p><code>
expected the post to succeed, but got http status 204
</code></p>

<h3>Define your own matchers</h3>

<p>The drawback with explicit error message is that they harm code readability. If this becomes too much of an issue, one last solution is the use of <a href="https://objectpartners.com/2013/09/18/the-benefits-of-using-assertthat-over-other-assert-methods-in-unit-tests/">test matchers</a>. A test matcher is a class encapsulating assertion code. The test framework provides a fluent api to bind a matcher with the actual and expected values. Almost all test framework support some flavor of these. If not, or if you want more, there are libraries that do :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://joel-costigliola.github.io/assertj/index.html">AssertJ</a> is a fluent assertion library for Java. You can easily extend it with your own assertions (ie. matchers)</li>
<li><a href="http://n-fluent.net/">NFluent</a> is the same thing for .Net.</li>
</ul>


<p>As an example, in a past side project, I defined an <a href="https://github.com/philou/mes-courses/blob/master/spec/support/include_all_matcher.rb">include_all</a> rspec matcher that verifies that many elements are present in a collection. It can be used that way :</p>

<p><code>ruby
expect(items).to include_all(["Tomatoes", "Bananas", "Potatoes"])
</code></p>

<p>It yields error messages like</p>

<p><code>
["Bananas", "Potatoes"] are missing
</code></p>

<p>A custom matcher is more work, but it provides both readable code and clean error messages.</p>

<h2>Other good points of matchers</h2>

<p>Like any of these 3 tactics, matchers provide better error messages. Explicit error messages, in turn, speed up the diagnostic on regression. In the end, faster diagnostic means easier maintenance.</p>

<p>But there&rsquo;s more awesomness in custom test matchers !</p>

<h3>Adaptive error messages</h3>

<p>In a custom matcher, you have to write code to generate the error message. This means we can add logic there ! It&rsquo;s an opportunity to build more detailed error messages.</p>

<p>This can be particularly useful when testing recursive (tree-like) structures. A few years ago, I wrote an rspec matcher library called <a href="https://github.com/philou/xpath-specs">xpath-specs</a>. It checks html views for the presence of recursive XPath. Instead of printing</p>

<p><code>
Could not find //table[@id="grades"]//span[text()='Joe'] in ...
</code></p>

<p>It will print</p>

<p><code>
Could find //table[@id="grades"] but not //table[@id="grades"]//span[text()='Joe'] in ...
</code></p>

<p>(BTW, I&rsquo;m still wondering if testing views this way is a good idea &hellip;)</p>

<h3>Test code reuse</h3>

<p>One of the purpose of custom test matchers is to be reusable. That&rsquo;s a good place to factorize assertion code. It is both more readable and more organized than extracting an assertion method.</p>

<h3>Better coverage</h3>

<p>I noticed that custom matcher have a psychological effect on test coverage ! A matcher is a place to share assertion code. Adding thorough assertions seems legitimate, contrary to repeating them inline.</p>

<h3>Avoids mocking</h3>

<p>We often resort to mocks instead of side effect tests because it&rsquo;s a lot shorter. A custom matcher encapsulates the assertion code. It makes it OK to use a few assertions to test for side effects, which is usually preferable to mocking.</p>

<p>For example, here is a matcher that checks that our remote service API received the correct calls, without doing any mocking.</p>

<p>```ruby
RSpec::Matchers.define :have_received_order do |cart, credentials|
  match do |api|</p>

<pre><code>not api.nil? and
api.login == credentials.email and
api.password == credentials.password and
cart.lines.all? do |cart_line|
  cart.content.include?(cart_line.item.remote_id)
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  failure_message do |api|</p>

<pre><code>"expected #{api.inspect} to have received order #{cart.inspect} from #{credentials}"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<h2>Care about error messages</h2>

<p>Providing good error messages is a small effort compared to unit testing in general. At the same time, it speeds up the feedback loop, both while coding and during later maintenance. Imagine how easier it would be to analyze and fix regressions if they all had clear error messages !</p>

<p>Spread the word ! Leave comments in code reviews, demo the practice to your pair buddy. Prepare a team coding dojo about custom assertion matchers. Discuss the issue in a retro !</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-05-29-speed-up-the-tdd-feedback-loop-with-better-assertion-messages/just-do-it.jpg" alt="'Just Do It' written on a board" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[20 Bad Excuses For Not Writing Unit Tests]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/20-bad-excuses-for-not-writing-unit-tests/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-23T06:08:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/20-bad-excuses-for-not-writing-unit-tests</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>I guess we always find excuses to keep on with our bad habits, don&rsquo;t we ? <em><a href="http://www.goodreads.com/quotes/797048-i-guess-we-always-find-excuses-to-keep-on-with">Stephen King</a></em></p></blockquote>

<ol>
<li>I don&rsquo;t have the time. <em>But you&rsquo;ll have the time to fix the bugs &hellip;</em></li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t know how to write tests. <em>No problem, anyone can <a href="/from-apprentice-to-master-how-to-learn-tdd-test-driven-development/">learn</a>.</em></li>
<li>I&rsquo;m sure the code is working now. <em><a href="https://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/quotes/e/edsgerdijk204340.html">The competent programmer is fully aware of the limited size of his own skull &hellip;</a></em></li>
<li>This code is not testable. <em>Learn or refactor.</em></li>
<li>It&rsquo;s (UI|DB) code, we don&rsquo;t test it. <em>Because it never crashes ?</em></li>
<li>Because I need to refactor first &hellip; and I need tests to refactor ! <em>Damn, you&rsquo;ve fallen into the test deadlock !</em></li>
<li>It&rsquo;s multithreaded code, it&rsquo;s impossible to test. <em>Because it&rsquo;s fully tederministic ?</em></li>
<li>The QA department is already testing the code. <em>Is that working well ?</em></li>
<li>I should not test my own code, I&rsquo;ll be biased. <em>Start testing other people&rsquo;s code right now then !</em></li>
<li>I&rsquo;m a programmer, not a tester. <em><a href="https://softwareengineering.stackexchange.com/questions/159572/as-a-professional-developer-is-it-acceptable-to-not-write-unit-tests">Professional programmers write tests</a>.</em></li>
</ol>


<p><img src="../imgs/2017-05-23-20-bad-excuses-for-not-writing-unit-tests/stronger_than_excuses_quote.jpg" alt="A quote 'Be Stronger Than Your Excuses'" /><div class="image-credits">From <a href="https://todayiwillbefit.com/2013/10/30/excuses-suck-top-10-bad-excuses-to-not-exercise/">todayiwillbefit.com</a></div></p>

<ol>
<li>I&rsquo;m using a REPL, it replaces unit tests. <em>Sure, and you&rsquo;re running your REPL buffers on the CI ? and keeping your them for the next time someone modifies your code.</em></li>
<li>My type system is strong enough to replace tests. <em>Does it detect when you use &lsquo;+&rsquo; instead of &lsquo;*&rsquo; ?</em></li>
<li>We don&rsquo;t have the tooling to write unit tests. <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_unit_testing_frameworks">Get one</a>.</em></li>
<li>Tests aren&rsquo;t run automatically anyway. <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_continuous_integration_software">Install a Continuous Integration Server</a>.</em></li>
<li>I&rsquo;m domain expert developer, writing tests is not my job. <em>Creating bugs isn&rsquo;t either !</em></li>
<li>We&rsquo;d rather switch to the <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/avg.html">Blub language</a> first ! <em>You&rsquo;re right, let&rsquo;s do neither then !</em></li>
<li>We don&rsquo;t test legacy code. <em>Specifically because it is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legacy_code">legacy code</a>.</em></li>
<li>Adding tests for every production code we write is insane ! <em>As shipping untested code is unprofessional.</em></li>
<li>I find more issues doing manual testing. <em><a href="/how-we-started-exploratory-testing/">Exploratory Testing</a> is a valuable testing, even more so on top of automated tests.</em></li>
<li>Because my teammates don&rsquo;t run them. <em>Time for a <a href="/most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/">retrospective</a>.</em></li>
</ol>


<p><img src="../imgs/2017-05-23-20-bad-excuses-for-not-writing-unit-tests/just-do-it.jpg" alt="'Just Do It' written on a board" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From apprentice to master, how to learn TDD (Test Driven Development)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/from-apprentice-to-master-how-to-learn-tdd-test-driven-development/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-15T06:53:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/from-apprentice-to-master-how-to-learn-tdd-test-driven-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started to learn <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development">Test Driven Development</a> a long time ago. Since then, even though I&rsquo;m still not a master, it&rsquo;s been my most useful programming skill, by far. TDD is the first trick every new programmer should learn. It made my whole career as a developer easier.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been working as a professional software engineer for more than 15 years, including around 10 years in the trading industry. Only once did I need to work on week ends or late into the night to fix emergency issues. I believe I largely owe this work-life balance to the high test coverage that TDD ensures by design.</p>

<p>TDD also enables safe refactoring. Refactoring enables <a href="/incremental-architecture-a-cure-against-architecture-astronauts/">incremental design</a> which lets you decide late. Deciding late is how you make your customers happy by accepting late changes. Deciding late is how take up-front design easy, and improve your code as you go. Deciding late is how you build trustful and harmonious relationships with the stakeholders of your project.</p>

<p>Finally, writing tests before the code is both easier and more fun. Among compilation errors and never ending customer demands, the recurring green barre tastes like pure candy to the poor programmer !</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-05-15-from-apprentice-to-master-how-to-learn-tdd-test-driven-development/road.jpg" alt="A long winding road" /><div class="image-credits">From <a href="https://fr.pinterest.com/explore/winding-road/">Pinterest winding road catalog</a></div></p>

<h2>The TDD Road</h2>

<p>Here are the steps I took to learn TDD.</p>

<h3>Learn the principles</h3>

<p>The principles of Test Driven Development are fairly basic. 5 minutes is enough to know them forever :</p>

<ol>
<li>Write a failing test</li>
<li>Make it pass by doing the simplest thing possible</li>
<li>Refactor your code while keeping the tests passing</li>
<li>Repeat until your acceptance test is green</li>
</ol>


<p>TDD newbies might ask a few questions like :</p>

<ul>
<li>Is making the code compile in step 1 or 2 ? Honestly, that does not matter. Write the test as if you had the code, then make it compile, make sure it fails, and continue.</li>
<li>How much should I refactor ? It often takes a good amount of experimentation to find your good balance. If you don&rsquo;t refactor enough, you going to drown in dirty code. If you refactor too much, you&rsquo;re going to waste your time (<a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/Yagni.html">YAGNI</a>). As a rule of thumb, <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/BeckDesignRules.html">Kent Beck&rsquo;s</a> rules on simple design are a very good starting point :</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/BeckDesignRules.html"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-15-from-apprentice-to-master-how-to-learn-tdd-test-driven-development/beck-rules.jpg" alt="A visual graph of Kent Beck's rules of simple design" /></a><div class="image-credits"><a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/BeckDesignRules.html">From Martin Fowler : Beck Design Rules</a></div></p>

<h3>Find your tools</h3>

<p>Back in 2003, after reading <a href="TODO">Martin Fowler</a>&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1495080119&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=martin+fowler+refactoring">Refactoring: Improving the Design of Existing Code</a> book, I decided to give TDD a serious try. I was using C++ at work but we did not even have a nightly build. I had to download and setup <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CppUnit">CppUnit</a> on my own. As solo endeavor, this was a required step to get into TDD.</p>

<p>Find and setup a tool. Which one should be rather obvious, if your team already uses a unit test framework, stick to it, otherwise, pick the most standard for your language, ex : <a href="http://junit.org/">JUnit</a> for <a href="https://www.java.com">Java</a> (you might as well start searching for a new job where they use a unit testing tool).</p>

<h3>Train at a TDD coding dojo</h3>

<p><a href="http://codingdojo.org/">Coding dojos</a> were first invented as a tool to <a href="http://www.peterprovost.org/blog/2012/05/02/kata-the-only-way-to-learn-tdd/">learn TDD</a>. They were started by two french eXtreme Programmers <a href="https://ut7.fr/">Emmanuel Gaillot</a> and <a href="http://institut-agile.fr/">Laurent Bossavit</a>. It happens that I live in Paris, and that Emmanuel came to work as a contractor at the same company I was. I learned that he was organizing a weekly coding dojo open to any developer. That&rsquo;s how I started attending coding dojos. Looking back, the TDD skills I learned at the coding dojo are just enormous !</p>

<p>If you are serious about learning TDD, attend coding dojos. Whether you find one in your city (ask <a href="https://www.meetup.com/">meetup.com</a>) or in your company does not really matter. If you cannot find any, just start one at work ! Send a public call for interested people (use wiki, mail, posters or whatever), book a room and start hacking ! <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Coding-Dojo-Handbook-Emily-Bache/dp/919811803X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494908749&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=coding+dojo">Emily Bache&rsquo;s Coding Dojo Handbook</a> seems a very good reference about how to start a coding dojo (Disclaimer : I did not read the book, I only know it by reputation.)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Coding-Dojo-Handbook-Emily-Bache/dp/919811803X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494908749&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=coding+dojo"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-15-from-apprentice-to-master-how-to-learn-tdd-test-driven-development/coding-dojo.jpg" alt="Cover of The Coding Dojo Handbook" /></a></p>

<h3>Use it</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;re a professional programmer, you must be spending most of your time writing code. Take this opportunity to use TDD. You&rsquo;ll be slowed down a bit at the beginning, but as both your code and your skills improve, you&rsquo;ll get your time back manyfold.</p>

<p>I remember one of my first professional use of TDD was to write a small parser. A few weeks later I was asked to make it faster. Having tests around it made it easy to optimize it without breaking it.</p>

<h3>Deliberate practice</h3>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/First-20-Hours-Learn-Anything/dp/1591846943/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494910468&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+first+20+hours">The first 20 hours</a>, Josh Kaufman explains that deliberately practicing specific topics is a more time effective way of learning than simply crunching hours of practice.</p>

<p>My friend <a href="https://twitter.com/tpierrain">Thomas Pierrain</a> is used to regularly practice short 30 minutes katas to sharpen his programming skills. Katas can be found at <a href="http://codingdojo.org/KataCatalogue/">codingdojo.org</a>, at <a href="http://cyber-dojo.org/">cyber-dojo.org</a> or in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Coding-Dojo-Handbook-Emily-Bache/dp/919811803X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494908749&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=coding+dojo">The Coding Dojo Handbook</a>.</p>

<h3>Read</h3>

<p>Meanwhile I was doing all this, I also spent a lot of time reading on the subject. At the time, there was a lot of things about TDD in the <a href="http://wiki.c2.com/">C2 Wiki</a>, so I spent a lot of time there. Since then, I stumbled upon a few books that helped me to understand some aspects of TDD :</p>

<ul>
<li>Kent Beck&rsquo;s classic <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Test-Driven-Development-Kent-Beck/dp/0321146530/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1495080564&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=tdd+by+example">TDD by example</a> remains a great reference for beginners</li>
<li>I got very useful advices from <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Test-Driven-Development-Practical-Guide/dp/0131016490/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494911486&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=test+driven+practical+guide">TDD, a practical guide</a> especially the section about UI testing, which really saved me at some point</li>
<li>Finally, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Growing-Object-Oriented-Software-Guided-Tests/dp/0321503627/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1495080583&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=growing+object-oriented+software+guided+by+tests">Growing Object Oriented Software Guided By Tests</a> is now a classic about what is called &ldquo;The London school of testing&rdquo;, which uses mocks as a design tool. Definitely a must read.</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Growing-Object-Oriented-Software-Guided-Tests/dp/0321503627/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1495080583&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=growing+object-oriented+software+guided+by+tests"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-15-from-apprentice-to-master-how-to-learn-tdd-test-driven-development/growing.jpg" alt="Cover of GOOSGT" /></a></p>

<h3>Practice advanced topics</h3>

<p>The TDD road goes on forever, testing has a lot of tricky topics. Once you&rsquo;ve mastered the basics, it&rsquo;s quite interesting to explore and practice more complex subjects. Here are a few things worth trying out :</p>

<ul>
<li>Use automated IDE refactorings to keep the code compiling all the way through a kata</li>
<li>Do the same kata twice, using <a href="/flavours-of-tdd/">top-down and bottom-up</a> styles</li>
<li>Do refactoring katas to learn how to work with legacy code</li>
<li>Do UI katas, to learn how to test the UI</li>
<li>Learn how to deal with DB</li>
<li>Learn how to handle remote services</li>
</ul>


<p>If needed, invent your own katas to deliberately practice these topics and others.</p>

<h2>The pitfalls</h2>

<p>As any road worth walking, the TDD path is not linear and smooth. Before fully mastering TDD, you&rsquo;ll regularly wonder if you&rsquo;re on the right track. As any practice, TDD has pitfalls. I&rsquo;ve fell into some quite a few times. I guess that&rsquo;s part of the learning process.</p>

<h3>Emerging Design</h3>

<p>There&rsquo;s always been a lot of misunderstanding around this topic.</p>

<p>Bad smells in your code make your tests harder to write. If adding a test is painful, that&rsquo;s an indication that something could be improved in your design. It&rsquo;s then up to you to know what. Once you&rsquo;ve figured out what you want to change, use your existing tests to refactor your design first. Only then, add this new test.</p>

<p>As you can see, the tests will give you more feedback about the design of your code, but they won&rsquo;t tell you what to do. That&rsquo;s where your coding skills will help. This is particularly true about algorithms. Don&rsquo;t expect a good algorithm to magically appear as you do the simplest-thing-that-could-possibly-work &hellip;</p>

<p>As with any rules, there are exceptions. At times, you&rsquo;ll walk into a problem which emerging design is great. For example, I&rsquo;ve done the <a href="http://agilekatas.co.uk/katas/RomanNumerals-Kata">Arab to Romans</a> kata many times, and that repeatedly doing the simplest-thing-that-could-possibly-work yields a good solution.</p>

<h3>Mocks</h3>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mock_object">Mocks</a> are useful at times, but be careful not to overuse them. I already <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/mocking/">wrote about mocks</a>. Too much mocking makes your test suite brittle, ineffective and difficult to maintain ! I&rsquo;ve been bitten hard by this one on a personal <a href="https://github.com/philou/mes-courses">side project</a>, the day I decided to get rid of all the mocks, I shrank the test code size by 25%. Since then I learned about alternate techniques such as :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.natpryce.com/articles/000714.html">Test data builders</a> which allow to easily build test data</li>
<li><a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/ValueObject.html">Value objects</a> that are immutable and don&rsquo;t need mocking</li>
<li><a href="/my-new-gem-for-creating-rspec-proxies/">test spies and proxies</a> as a way to mock and track calls while still calling the real code</li>
<li><a href="http://localhost:4000/hitting-the-middle-ground-between-classicist-and-mockist-tdd/">in-memory fake implementations</a> which make the tests independent and fast without unmaintainable proliferation of mock setup</li>
</ul>


<p>As an indicator, less than 5% of my tests use mocks.</p>

<h3>Metrics</h3>

<p>In his <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9LfmrkyP81M">keynote at RailsConf 2014</a> DHH explains the danger of testing metrics.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9LfmrkyP81M"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-15-from-apprentice-to-master-how-to-learn-tdd-test-driven-development/dhh.jpg" alt="DHH's keynote at RailsConf 2014" /></a></p>

<p>By using TDD correctly, you should get a high code coverage as a side effect. If you get below 80%, you must be doing something wrong. The other metric you should keep an eye on is the total build time. Original <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/">eXtreme Programming</a> had the <a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/ten_minute_build.html">10 minutes build rule</a> which states that if your build + tests takes more than 10 minutes, you should refactor it.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it ! Things like 100% test coverage or test ratio are complete nonsense.</p>

<h2>Pushing it even further</h2>

<p>My promise, at the beginning of this post, was that Test Driven Development would make your life as a developer easier. Now let&rsquo;s imagine that your whole team or company was using TDD. It&rsquo;s a foundation on which to build a sustainable agile organization.</p>

<p>The mastery of automated testing at organization scale is a key element to continuous delivery, making releasing software a non-event, and as stress-free as possible.</p>

<p>Full adoption of TDD can yield to <a href="/incremental-architecture-a-cure-against-architecture-astronauts/">incremental architecture</a> which delivers features faster, by skipping the conflictual arguments about supposed future needs.</p>

<p>Finally, TDD can simplify your processes and tooling. Team-wide TDD results in a steady flow of features on top of which it is easier to create simple and effective processes and tools.</p>

<p>The road is long, sinuous and at times rocky, but so are the rewards.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Incremental architecture, a cure against architecture astronauts]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/incremental-architecture-a-cure-against-architecture-astronauts/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-24T06:52:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/incremental-architecture-a-cure-against-architecture-astronauts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in 2001, when I started to code for a living, fresh out of school, I was mainly doing a form of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cowboy_coding">cowboy coding</a>. After a few months of maintaining my own mess, I started to recall my university lessons : we should be doing design before coding &hellip;</p>

<p>When I was asked to re-engineer the &lsquo;wizards UI&rsquo;, I paused my coding to design something clean from scratch. It worked quite well at first : the overall code was a lot simpler and contained a lot less duplication than before. Seeing this new shiny UI, product people asked for new features. Unfortunately, I hadn&rsquo;t thought of them when designing this little framework. I was almost back at my initial situation.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how I started to look for another way to design software. At about the same time the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0201616416/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1493096057&amp;sr=8-3&amp;keywords=extreme+programming">eXtreme Programming book</a> fell into my hands. That&rsquo;s where I discovered the idea of incremental design and architecture.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0201616416/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1493096057&amp;sr=8-3&amp;keywords=extreme+programming"><img src="../imgs/2017-04-24-incremental-architecture-a-cure-against-architecture-astronauts/xp-1ed.jpg" alt="Front cover of the first edition of the XP book" /></a></p>

<h2>What is Incremental Archi</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start with the antithesis of incremental architecture :</p>

<h3>Astronaut Architecture</h3>

<p>The term &ldquo;Architecture Astronaut&rdquo; was coined by <a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com">Joel Spolsky</a> back in 2001. If you haven&rsquo;t read this <a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2001/04/21/dont-let-architecture-astronauts-scare-you/">classic post</a> yet, I strongly encourage you to do so. Basically, he explains that we should not be impressed by architects going over their heads talking about too abstract stuff.</p>

<p>Incremental is the exact opposite of astronaut architecture</p>

<h3>Two Schools to Software Architecture</h3>

<p>Traditional architecture is about taking up-front choices that will be difficult to change. Incremental architecture is about preparing for non-stop change and taking decisions as late as possible.</p>

<p>The idea in incremental architecture is really simple : keep your code simple, clean and automatically tested in order to be able to simply adapt your code and architecture when definitely needed.</p>

<h3>Pros and Cons of incremental architecture</h3>

<p>The first reaction of most software engineers (me included, remember how my story started) is that it can only work on trivial stuff. After practicing it for about a decade, I am now convinced it works most of the time. I&rsquo;m not alone, <a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/incremental_design.html">James Shore</a> (who wrote the more on the subject) also shares my view:</p>

<blockquote><p>Common thought is that distributed processing, persistence, internationalization, security, and transaction structure are so complex that you must consider them from the start of your project. I disagree; I&rsquo;ve dealt with all of them incrementally.</p>

<p>Two issues that remain difficult to change are choice of programming language and platform. I wouldn&rsquo;t want to make those decisions incrementally!</p></blockquote>

<p>I would add published APIs to this list.</p>

<p>Granted, there are situations that incremental architecture alone cannot handle, what about its good points then ?</p>

<p>In all the other cases (and that means most of the time), here is what you get :</p>

<ul>
<li>As you won&rsquo;t need to deal with future use cases, you&rsquo;ll do less work</li>
<li>That in turn, will keep your code simpler, decreasing time to release new features</li>
<li>As change is built-in, you&rsquo;ll be able to improve your architecture in ways you could not have imagined from the start !</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Art-Agile-Development-Pragmatic-Software/dp/0596527675/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1493096137&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+agile+development"><img src="../imgs/2017-04-24-incremental-architecture-a-cure-against-architecture-astronauts/art-of-agile.jpg" alt="Front cover of the Art of Agile Software Development book" /></a></p>

<p>If you cannot see how this could possibly work ? Read on !</p>

<h2>How to do it</h2>

<h3>eXtreme Programming</h3>

<p>As I said earlier, incremental architecture emerged from eXtreme Programming. It won&rsquo;t come as a surprise that in order to work well incremental architecture requires the XP practices to be in place. In particular, the code base should be automatically tested, the continuous integration cycle should take less than 10 minutes, the design should be simple. The team should be good at doing refactoring.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t expect to be able to do incremental architecture without these practices in place. But this alone might be enough already !</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1493096197&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=fowler+refactoring"><img src="../imgs/2017-04-24-incremental-architecture-a-cure-against-architecture-astronauts/refactoring.jpg" alt="Front cover of the Martin Fowler's refactoring book" /></a></p>

<h3>Architecture Vision</h3>

<p>At work, where our team consists of 9 developers, it&rsquo;s not always that simple to coordinate and all pull in the same direction. That&rsquo;s why we find it useful to share a very long term architecture vision (<a href="https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/enabling-incremental-design-and-evolutionary-architecture">Enabling Incremental Design and Evolutionary Architecture</a>). This will help people to make coherent decisions when hesitating between 2 alternate designs.</p>

<p>The vision can be the result of the work of a pair, or a mob brainstorming or whatever. Building this vision is typically an activity where experienced programmers can contribute a lot of value.</p>

<p>Once this vision is shared and understood by the team, every time a pair has to work on a story, they can orient the design towards it. But always as little as possible to finish the work at hand, remember the XP motos <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KISS_principle">KISS (Keep It Simple &amp; Stupid)</a> &amp; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it">YAGNI (You Ain&rsquo;t Gonna Need It</a>.</p>

<p>One final word &hellip; a vision is just that : a vision ! It might turn out true, or false, be ready to change it as circumstances change.</p>

<h3>Spikes</h3>

<p>At times, even with a story in your hands and a long term architecture sketch on the whiteboard, you might have difficulties to know how to change your design to fulfill both.</p>

<p>As always in XP, in case of uncertainty, use <a href="http://agiledictionary.com/209/spike/">Spikes</a> ! Spikes are short time-boxed experiments of throwaway code, which goal is to answer a specific design question.</p>

<h3>How to mitigate the risks</h3>

<p>What about these topics that don&rsquo;t yield to incremental architecture ? What if you discover late that you need to change your platform ? Or your API ?</p>

<p>Obviously, you should think about these questions up-front. Hopefully, there are usually not that difficult to answer. But, over time, Non-Functional-Requirements and technologies change. Large and long living systems are particularly likely to need to change to a new platform someday.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_philosophy">Unix had the answer</a> : build your system out of small tools, that do only one thing well, and that communicate through a standard protocol. Systems built that way can be re-written one piece at a time.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_philosophy"><img src="../imgs/2017-04-24-incremental-architecture-a-cure-against-architecture-astronauts/Ken_n_dennis.jpg" alt="Ken Thompson and Dennis Ritchie, the creators of Unix" /></a><div class="image-credits">Photo from <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ken_n_dennis.jpg">WikiMedia</a></div></p>

<p>The modern version of this is the micro-services architecture. Incremental architecture allows you to start with a monolith, split it when you need to, and replace micro-services as needed.   With the safety of simple code and a great automated test harness. Interestingly, successful software systems that were architectured up-front also take this road &hellip; without the safety !</p>

<h3>The Architect</h3>

<p>Good news : no more PowerPoints and a lot more coding with the team ! Here is what&rsquo;s expected from an incremental architect :</p>

<ul>
<li>To code with the team. As Bertrand Meyer once said &ldquo;<a href="http://stal.blogspot.fr/2008/08/architect-always-implements.html">Bubbles (aka. diagrams) don&rsquo;t crash</a>&rdquo;, it&rsquo;s plain too easy, and wrong, to mandate architecture without living with the consequences</li>
<li>To come up with more ideas when drafting the long term vision</li>
<li>To keep an eye on the &lsquo;long term&rsquo; while being the navigator in pair programming</li>
<li>In the second edition of the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0321278658/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1493096057&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=extreme+programming">XP book</a> Kent Beck suggests that the architect should write large scale tests to stress the system and demonstrate architecture issues to the team</li>
<li>To delegate as much as possible to the team. However smart the architect, the team as a whole is smarter ! Delegating architecture increases motivation and the quality of the outcome.</li>
</ul>


<h2>End of the story</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been practicing incremental architecture and design for a long time now. It made my life a lot simpler ! Most architecture questions become backlog items to prioritize.</p>

<p>One last advice : be prepared to re-read <a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2001/04/21/dont-let-architecture-astronauts-scare-you/">Joel Spolsky&rsquo;s article</a> whenever you get caught up in architecture meetings &hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developer ! Are you losing your rat race ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/developer-are-you-losing-your-rat-race/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-09T05:37:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/developer-are-you-losing-your-rat-race</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>A rat race is an endless, self-defeating, or pointless pursuit. It conjures up the image of the futile efforts of a lab rat trying to escape while running around a maze or in a wheel.</p></blockquote>

<p>Are we building our own <del>maze</del> self defeating landscape by our exacerbated focus on technology ? Let me explain.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2017-02-09-developer-are-you-losing-your-rat-race/rat-maze.jpg" title="A rat in a maze" ></p>

<h2>The context</h2>

<p>As <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marc_Andreessen">Marc Andreessen</a> famously said &ldquo;Software is eating the world&rdquo;, which means that there is more and more demand for software. At the same time, giant countries like China, India, Russia or Brazil are producing more and more master&rsquo;s degrees every year. This also means more and more software engineers. The consequence is that there has never been so many new technologies emerging than these days. The software landscape his huge, growing and complex.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s great for progress, but it&rsquo;s a puzzle for hiring. In this chaotic environment, years of experience with a particular technology is something that remains easy to measure, that&rsquo;s why employers (and developers) tend to use keywords to cast for a job.</p>

<h2>The effects</h2>

<p>As a result, developers tend to pick a few technologies to become masters at, to put them on their CV and get job offers. There&rsquo;s a danger with specializing on a particular technology : eventually, it will become deprecated, in this keyword driven world, it&rsquo;s almost like if you&rsquo;ll have to start from zero again. Even if a specialization is wide enough now, as time goes on and more and more technologies are created, any area of expertise will become a tiny spot in all the landscape. One might think this is only an issue for old guys that did not stay up to date &hellip; I strongly believe this is wrong, it happened to all past technologies, I don&rsquo;t see why today&rsquo;s latest .js framework wouldn&rsquo;t be legacy stuff one day.</p>

<p>One could think that sticking to a good employer is a good fix against that. It is &hellip; for some time ! Sticking to an company actually means <em>betting</em> on this company. What would happen if it went out of business, or through difficult times and you&rsquo;re asked to leave ? When you reach the job market after so long with a single employer, you&rsquo;ll be a de-facto specialist, on proprietary stuff that no one is interested about.</p>

<p>Finally, you might work hard not to specialize, but it&rsquo;s going to be a lot more difficult to get a job as a generalist, only a few shops actually hire this way.</p>

<p>To summarize, we are forced into specialization, which is great in the short term, but risky in the long run.</p>

<h2>1€ advice</h2>

<p>So what can we do about this ? Obviously, we cannot change the world &hellip; The only ones we can act on are ourselves !</p>

<h3>Learning</h3>

<p>In our fast moving tech world, learning remains key ! But instead of trying to keep up with all the cool new techs that are invented every day, we should study fundamental skills, and only learn just enough specific skills to get the job done. To me fundamental skills are all the things you&rsquo;ll apply whatever the language and technology you are using, for example :</p>

<ul>
<li>design</li>
<li>architecture (whatever that is &hellip;)</li>
<li>clean code</li>
<li>refactoring</li>
<li>legacy code</li>
<li>testing</li>
<li>tooling</li>
<li>mentoring &amp; coaching</li>
<li>programming paradigms (functional, dynamic, static, imperative, OO, concurrent &hellip;)</li>
<li>process flow</li>
<li>communication</li>
<li>product definition</li>
<li>concurrency</li>
<li>performance</li>
</ul>


<p>I wrote <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/">this post</a> that explains how I did learn some of these skills (by no mean would I say that this is the only way). Good mastery of these skills should be enough to quickly get up to speed in any project you are involved. This other article <a href="https://blog.bradfieldcs.com/in-2017-learn-every-language-59b11f68eee#.l2n6kouuz">In 2017, learn <em>every</em> language</a>, which I found through the excellent <a href="http://www.hackernewsletter.com/">hackernewsletter</a>, explains how this is possible.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, knowing is not enough &hellip;</p>

<h3>Selling</h3>

<p>How do you convince others that you are up to the job in a particular technology ? Unfortunately, I don&rsquo;t have a definitive answer yet &hellip;</p>

<p>Regularly, people try to coin a word to describe the competent generalist developer : polyglot, full stack, craftsman &hellip; If it&rsquo;s good enough, it usually gets taken over quite fast by the industry and just becomes yet another buzzword (the only exception being eXtreme Programming, but who would like to hire and eXtreme Programmer ?).</p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1473135683&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=soft+skills">Soft Skills</a>, John Somnez says the trick is to explain to people that you might not have experience in a technology &lsquo;yet&rsquo;. This might work, if your resume gets through, which is not sure.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s my try : the next time I&rsquo;ll polish my resume, I&rsquo;ll try to put forward my fundamental skills first, for example with 5 stars self-assessments. Only after will I add something like &ldquo;By the way, I could work with tech X Y Z &hellip;&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Independence</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Jobs-Meaning-9-5/dp/1619613352/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1486713381&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+end+of+jobs"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2017-02-09-developer-are-you-losing-your-rat-race/the-end-of-jobs.jpg" title="Cover of the book &lsquo;The End of Jobs&rsquo;" ></a></p>

<p>Being your own boss could be a solution in the long term. I recently listened to <a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Jobs-Meaning-9-5/dp/1619613352/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1486713381&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+end+of+jobs">The End of Jobs</a> in which the author explains that entrepreneurship is an accessible alternative these days, and that like any skill, it&rsquo;s learnable. The catch is that there are no schools, no diplomas, and that it seems a lot riskier in the short run. Despite that, he makes the point that the skills you&rsquo;ll learn makes it quite safe in the long run !</p>

<h2>Questions</h2>

<p>I feel like my post asks more questions than it provides answers :&ndash;). Honestly, I&rsquo;d really love to read other people&rsquo;s opinions and ideas. What are your tricks to market yourself on new technologies ? As a community, what could we do to fight our planned obsolescence ? Do you think I&rsquo;m totally wrong and that the problem does not exist ? What do you think ?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
