<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: software | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/software/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-02T05:24:18+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I got my feet wet with machine learning with 'The First 20 Hours']]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-i-got-my-feet-wet-with-machine-learning-with-the-first-20-hours/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-29T21:09:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-i-got-my-feet-wet-with-machine-learning-with-the-first-20-hours</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m currently wrapping up an alpha of a unit testing <a href="https://github.com/philou/complexity-assert">ruby gem</a> that allows to assert the complexity of a piece of code. It&rsquo;s the result of an experiment to learn some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machine_learning">Machine Learning</a> skills in 20 hours &hellip; not bad for a first a try at Data Science ! This is the story of this experiment.</p>

<h2>How it all started ?</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/First-20-Hours-Learn-Anything/dp/1591846943/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1483258282&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+first+20+hours"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-12-29-how-i-got-my-feet-wet-with-machine-learning-with-the-first-20-hours/book-cover.jpg" title="The cover of the book &lsquo;The First 20 Hours&rsquo;" ></a></p>

<p>A few months ago, I read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/First-20-Hours-Learn-Anything/dp/1591846943/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1483258282&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+first+20+hours">The First 20 Hours</a>. The book describes a technique to get up to speed and learn some practical skills on any particular subject in only 20 hours. As examples, the author details how he managed to teach himself a pretty decent level of Yoga, Ukulele, Wind Surfing, Programming, Go and touch typing.</p>

<p>I decided to give it a try. In order to get a boost, I found a few motivated people at work to do it with me. I started by presenting them the technique described in the book, and asked everyone what they wanted to learn. After a quick vote, we set out to learn more about Machine Learning.</p>

<h2>The technique</h2>

<p>The method is meant to allow anyone to learn necessary skills to accomplish a specific task in about 20 hours. I my case, I could expect to get a basic understanding of the Machine Learning concepts, as well as some practical skills to do something involving Machine Learning. Here are the details of the technique :</p>

<ol>
<li>H0 : Deep dive in the main concepts and theory of machine learning</li>
<li>H6 : Define an ambitious and practical goal or skill level to achieve by the end, and an outline of how to get there</li>
<li>H6 to H20 : Learn by doing</li>
</ol>


<p>As you see, the technique is pretty simple !</p>

<h2>How did it work ?</h2>

<h3>For the group</h3>

<p>The plan for the group was :</p>

<ul>
<li>to meet weekly for 2 hours</li>
<li>to share what we learned at the end of every session</li>
<li>to bound by similar goals</li>
</ul>


<p>At first, people were enthusiastic about learning something like machine learning. After a while, I started to get the following remarks :</p>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t really see the point of doing this together rather than independently&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;I&rsquo;m feeling a bit lost by not having a concrete goal and a plan from H0&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;I picked up a target that&rsquo;s too large for me&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>The learning curve must have proven too steep, because as time went by, a lot of people droped out, and we ended up being only 2 !</p>

<h3>For me</h3>

<p>The first phase was the toughest. As the author had warned in his book, &ldquo;You&rsquo;ll get deep above your head in theory and concepts you don&rsquo;t know&rdquo;, &ldquo;You&rsquo;ll feel lost&rdquo;. He had some reassuring words though : &ldquo;The steeper the learning curve, the more you&rsquo;ll be learning !&rdquo; I actually like this feeling of unknown things to learn, and that&rsquo;s why I stuck to it.</p>

<p>I took me 8 hours, and not 6 to get a good overall grasp of Machine Learning techniques. The theory was just too wide and interesting and I could not cut the learning after just 6 hours :&ndash;). I studied <a href="https://xyclade.github.io/MachineLearning/#cross-validation">Machine Learning for developers</a> plus a few other pages for details on specific points. I took and kept notes about what I learned. I chose my subject &ldquo;unit testing algorithm complexity&rdquo; for the following reasons :</p>

<ul>
<li>I could imagine some utility</li>
<li>I had been writing benchmarks at work for 3 years, and I knew the practice well enough</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s pretty easy to generate data for this subject : just run your algorithm !</li>
<li>It seems a good first step, doable with basic Machine Learning techniques like linear regression</li>
<li>It seems small enough to get something working in 12 hours</li>
<li>I could use ruby, which I find both fast and pleasant to program</li>
</ul>


<p>This is the plan I set out :</p>

<ol>
<li>Generate data with a linear algorithm (O(n))</li>
<li>Run linear regression on the data</li>
<li>Compute the the <a href="https://xyclade.github.io/MachineLearning/#root-mean-squared-error-rmse">RMSE</a> of the model</li>
<li>Deal with Garbage Collection in order to make reduce its noise</li>
<li>Deal with interpreter warm-up for the same reason</li>
<li>Generate data for a constant (O(1)) algorithm and build a model for it</li>
<li>Find a way to identify if an algorithm is constant or linear from it&rsquo;s execution timings</li>
<li>Generate data for a quadratic (O(2)) algorithm and build a model for it</li>
<li>Identify if an algorithm is constant, linear or quadratic</li>
<li>Package all this in an <a href="http://rspec.info/">RSpec</a> library</li>
</ol>


<p>It started well, and I made good progress. Unfortunately, as people dropped out of the group and I got more urgent things to do at work, I had to pause my project for a while. It&rsquo;s only been since last week that I got some time during my holidays to finish this off. I&rsquo;m currently at H18, and I&rsquo;ve completed all steps from 1 to 9.</p>

<p>As I said the project is still in early alpha. They is a lot of points in which it could be improved (more complexities, faster, more reliable &hellip;). Even though I did not tackle the more advanced machine learning techniques, I now understand the overall process of ML : explore to get an intuitive grasp of the data, try out a model, see what happens, and repeat &hellip; I feel that learning these more advanced techniques would be easier now.</p>

<h2>My opinion on the method</h2>

<p>Overall, I found the experiment really effective, it&rsquo;s possible to learn quite a lot by focusing on it for 20 hours. A word of warning though : you need to be really motivated and ready to stick through difficulties.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also been very pleasant. I&rsquo;ve always loved to learn new things, so I might be a little biased on that aspect. I liked the first part when I felt that there was a lot to learn in a large subject I knew almost nothing about. I loved the second part too, although this might be more related to machine learning, because I felt like exploring an unknown (data set) and trying to understand it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve never been afraid to learn something, doing this experiment taught me I can learn anything fast ! I&rsquo;ll definitely re-use it again.</p>

<p>One last word about doing this in group. My own experiment did not work very well. Most people were not comfortable with the first &lsquo;explore&rsquo; phase. I guess one could make it work better by starting 6 or 8 hours before the rest of the group, enough to grasp the basic concepts and come up with a few end goals. Having concrete targets from day 1 should help people to stick through and to collaborate. The &lsquo;guide&rsquo; could also help the others through the first phase.</p>

<p>Stay tuned, I&rsquo;ll present my gem in a following post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Overclocking a Scrum Team to 12]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/overclocking-a-scrum-team-to-12/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-21T04:57:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/overclocking-a-scrum-team-to-12</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>From <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overclocking">Wikipedia</a> :</em></p>

<blockquote><p>Overclocking is configuration of computer hardware components to operate faster than certified by the original manufacturer &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>It is said that Scrum teams work best at 7 people, and that they break at about 10. The trouble is that sometimes there is just too much work for 7 people, but no enough for a full Scrum of Scrums. What if there was a simple way to hack this number up to 12 ?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-12-21-overclocking-a-scrum-team-to-12/overclocking.jpg" title="An overclocked motherboard working with extra fans and cellar tape" ></p>

<h2>An Idea</h2>

<h3>The Surgical Team</h3>

<p>In his classic <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mythical-Man-Month-Software-Engineering-Anniversary/dp/0201835959/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1482298579&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+mythical+man+month">The Mythical Man Month</a> Fred Brooks presents an idea to organize software development the way surgeons work. The master performs the surgery while the rest of his team (intern or junior surgeon and the nurses) are there to support him. Fred Brook imagined an organization where master developers could be the only ones with access to the production code, while other more junior developers would have the task to provide them with tools and technical libraries.</p>

<p>I admit that this idea sounds out-of-fashion in contrast with modern agile teams of generalists &hellip; Still &hellip;</p>

<h3>Tools</h3>

<p>At work, we are working on a pretty technical and complex product which requires some time getting into both the code and the domain. We took a few interns during the past years, and a bit like Fred Brooks, we came to the conclusion that internships yield more results when focused on building supporting tools rather than joining the team and working on production code.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve also been doing <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-introduced-efficient-agile-retrospectives/">retrospectives</a> for 3 years now, we&rsquo;ve stolen a lot of best practices from the industry and the team is working a lot better than it used to. The pending side of this is that nowadays, the opportunities for improvement that we discover are a lot more specific, and they often need us to take some time to build new tools to support our work.</p>

<h3>The Agile Surgical Team</h3>

<p>Agile method such as Scrum or XP are all about creating real teams instead of a collection of individual. That means that if we wanted to adopt the surgical team idea, we could use teams instead of individuals : a team of experts, and a tooling team of apprentice developers !</p>

<p>Why not, there&rsquo;s not nothing really new here, but the challenge is to run such a tooling team efficiently !</p>

<ul>
<li>3 people or less : there&rsquo;s <a href="http://pm.stackexchange.com/a/10075">evidence in the industry</a> that micro teams can self organize in an ad-hoc manner</li>
<li>Mandate ScrumBan, Continuous Delivery and Devops : on site customer makes this possible, it should reduce project management overhead to almost nothing, and enforce quality</li>
<li>A sandbox for junior developers : there&rsquo;s no risk of messing up production code here, the domain (tools for software developers) is straightforward and the fast feedback provides a great environment for learning</li>
</ul>


<p>Obviously, for this to work, you&rsquo;ll also need to have enough tooling work to do for a 3 people team. That&rsquo;s usually the case, the CI alone can take quite some time (see Jez Humble&rsquo;s talk <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2zYxWEZ0gYg">Why Agile Doesn&rsquo;t Work</a>) and any team will have its own custom tools to do. For example, in our team, we built our own benchmark framework and we could benefit a lot from <a href="http://www.saros-project.org/">Saros</a> on IntelliJ.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2zYxWEZ0gYg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-12-21-overclocking-a-scrum-team-to-12/why-agile-doesnt-work.jpg" title="The slide in Jez Humble&rsquo;s Why Agile Doesn&rsquo;t Work about the time taken for CI" ></a></p>

<h2>Not quite there yet</h2>

<p>I promised to scale up to 12. Let&rsquo;s do the maths :</p>

<ul>
<li>3 people in the tooling team</li>
<li>8 people in the product team if we push Scrum a bit</li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s only 11, 1 is missing. This one is more specific to each team&rsquo;s context.</p>

<p>As I said earlier, the product we are building is pretty technical and complex. Sometimes, we simply don&rsquo;t know how we are going to do something. We need to try different ways before finding out the good one. The typical agile way of doing that is by conducting time-boxed <a href="http://agiledictionary.com/209/spike/">spikes</a>. Spikes are fine for code and design related issues but way too short to deal with hard R&amp;D problems. These need a lot of uninterrupted time for research and experiments, so it&rsquo;s not really possible to split them in backlog stories that any one can work on either &hellip;</p>

<h3>The R&amp;D Role</h3>

<p>Here is what you want : some uninterrupted time to learn and experiment different ways to do something difficult.</p>

<p>Here is what you don&rsquo;t want :</p>

<ul>
<li>specialists in the team</li>
<li>people out of sync with the daily production constraints</li>
<li>a never ending &lsquo;research&rsquo; topic</li>
</ul>


<p>Here is a simple solution in the context I describe : add someone in the product team, and do some 2 month round robin on hard subjects. This should leave plenty of time to study something different, but not so much time that one looses connection with the rest of the team. Plus it brings a bit of diversity in every one&rsquo;s daily work. One issue I can think of is that working on isolation might leave someone on a bad track, regularly presenting what was done to the rest of the team might alleviate this concern.</p>

<h2>A final word</h2>

<p>Obviously, this has a smell of specialization, we&rsquo;re bending Scrum principles a bit. So take it for what it is : just like overclocking, it&rsquo;s a hack to get a bit of extra juice before investing in something a lot more expensive (<a href="https://www.agilealliance.org/glossary/scrum-of-scrums/">Scrum of Scrums</a>, <a href="http://less.works/">Less</a> or whatever).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to use Hackernews and Reddit for blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-05T04:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I posted my latest article <a href="/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/">Is There Any Room for the Not-Passionate Developer ?</a> on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/">Hackernews</a> and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/programming/">Reddit Programming</a>. The post stayed on the fist page for a while, and I got a lot of traffic. If you are yourself blogging, you might be interested to know how it occurred, and what I learned in the process.</p>

<h2>How it started</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-05-how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging/soft-skills.jpg" title="The cover of &lsquo;Soft Skills, the software developer&rsquo;s life manual&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1473135683&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=soft+skills">Soft Skills, the software developer&rsquo;s life manual</a> John Somnez explains that posting your blog articles on HN or Reddit might bring you a ton of traffic, but that comments can be hard to swallow at time. Within a few hours of writing my blog post it had generated some positive activity on twitter (favorites and retweets) from my regular followers. That&rsquo;s a good sign that the post is good enough. As I had promised myself in such case, I submitted the post to both HN and Reddit.</p>

<h2>What happened ?</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-09-05-how-to-use-hackernews-and-reddit-for-blogging/google-analytics.jpg" title="A Google Analytics screenshot, with the traffic spike" ></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know for sure on Reddit, but I know my post stayed on the first page of HN for a few hours, it even went up to the third place for a while. In the process I got a lot of traffic, a lot more than I am used to. I also got a ton of comments, on HN, Reddit and directly on my post. John Somnez had warned that comments on HN and Reddit can be very harsh, so I went through these quickly, took notes about the points that seemed interesting, but I only responded to comments on my website.</p>

<p>Overall, the comments were pretty interesting though, and brought a lot of valid points. I&rsquo;m planning to write a &lsquo;response&rsquo; article to take all these into perspective.</p>

<p>Most of the traffic was made in the day I submitted my post, but I had more traffic than usual for 2 or 3 days. Since then, the traffic has settled down, but I now get between 2 and 5 times more traffic than I typically had on a daily basis ! An online Taiwanese tech magazine also asked me the permission to translate <a href="http://www.inside.com.tw/2016/08/05/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer">my post in Chinese</a> !</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure about the performance of my website during the traffic spike. I&rsquo;m using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> to statically generated html on <a href="https://pages.github.com/">Github Pages</a>, so that should be fine. I am also using a custom domain, and I need to make sure my <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7738293">DNS is correctly configured</a> for this to perform well.</p>

<h2>Advice for bloggers</h2>

<p>So here is what I am going to do regarding HN and Reddit in the future :</p>

<ol>
<li>It can bring so much traffic and backlinks that I&rsquo;ll definitely continue to submit blog posts from time to time</li>
<li>For the moment, I&rsquo;ll stick to only submitting the articles from which I already received good feedbacks, I don&rsquo;t want to get a bad karma or reputation on these websites</li>
<li>I might submit old articles that gathered good reviews at the time I wrote them</li>
<li>Concerning comments, I&rsquo;ll try to grow an even thicker skin. Maybe at some point I&rsquo;ll try to answer on HN or Reddit</li>
</ol>


<p>Of course, depending how this works, I will adapt !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to prepare a new Ruby env in 3 minutes using Docker]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-prepare-a-new-ruby-env-in-3-minutes-using-docker/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-17T05:21:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-prepare-a-new-ruby-env-in-3-minutes-using-docker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One or two weeks ago, I registered to the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/fr-FR/Paris-Ruby-Workshop/">Paris Ruby Workshop Meetup</a> and needed a Ruby env. I have been using <a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a> quite a lot to isolate my different dev envs from each other and from my main machine. As I&rsquo;ve been digging more into <a href="http://www.docker.com">Docker</a> lately, I thought I&rsquo;d simply use Docker and Docker Compose instead.</p>

<p>I turned out to be dead simple. All that is needed is a <code>docker-compose.yml</code> file to define the container, record the shared volume and set a bundle path inside it :</p>

<p>```yaml
rubybox:
  image: ruby:2.3
  command: bash
  working_dir: /usr/src/app
  environment:</p>

<pre><code>BUNDLE_PATH: 'vendor/bundle'
</code></pre>

<p>  volumes:</p>

<pre><code>- '.:/usr/src/app'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Without the custom bundle path, bundled gems would be installed elsewhere in the container, and lost at every restart.</p>

<p>To use the Rubybox, just type <code>docker-compose run rubybox</code> and you&rsquo;ll get a shell from within your ruby machine, where you can do everything you want.</p>

<p>In fact, I found the thing so useful, that I created the <a href="https://github.com/philou/rubybox">Rubybox</a> git repo to simplify cloning and reusing. I&rsquo;ve already cloned it at least 3 times since then !</p>

<p><code>bash
git clone git@github.com:philou/rubybox.git
cd rubybox
docker-compose run rubybox
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When the Boy Scout Rule Fails]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-02T05:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-02-when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/boy-scout-rule.jpg" title="An illustration of the boy scout rule" ></p>

<p>Here goes the <a href="http://programmer.97things.oreilly.com/wiki/index.php/The_Boy_Scout_Rule">boy scout rule</a> :</p>

<blockquote><p>Always check a module in cleaner than when you checked it out.</p></blockquote>

<p>Unfortunately, this alone does not guarantee to keep the technical debt under control. What can we do then ?</p>

<h2>Why the boy scout rule is not enough</h2>

<p>I can easily think of a few issues that are not covered by the boy scout rule.</p>

<h3>It only deals with local problems</h3>

<p>In it&rsquo;s statement, the boy scout rule is local and does not address large scale design or architecture issues. Applying the boy scout rule keeps files well written, using with clear and understandable code. From a larger perspective though, it does very little or slow improvement to the overall design.</p>

<p>These large scale refactorings are very difficult to deal with using the boy scout rule alone. It could be done but would require to share the refactoring goal with all the team, and then track its progress, while at the same time dealing with all the other subjects of the project. That&rsquo;s starting to sound like multitasking to me.</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;s skill dependent</h3>

<p>Another point about the boy scout rule (and to be fair, about any refactoring technique) is that programmers will be able to clean the code only as much as their skills allow them to !</p>

<p>Imagine what would happen when a new master developer arrives in a team of juniors, he&rsquo;d spot a lot of technical debt and would suggest improvements and ways to clean the code. Code that was thought of as very clean would suddenly be downgraded to junk !</p>

<p>The point here is that the boy scout rule cannot guarantee that you have no technical debt, because you don&rsquo;t know how much you have !</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s where the debt metaphor reaches its limits and flips to some productivity investment. By investing time to perform some newly discovered refactoring, you could get a productivity boost !</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470200818&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-02-when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/ddd.jpg" title="The cover of &ldquo;Domain Driven Design&rdquo;" ></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470200818&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design">Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software</a>, Eric Evans calls this knowledge distillation. He means that little by little, the team gains better understanding of the domain, sometimes going through what he calls a &lsquo;breakthrough&rsquo;. These breakthroughs often promote existing code to technical debt &hellip;</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;s context dependent</h3>

<p>Developers alone are not the only one responsible for creating technical debt. Changes to the environment also do.</p>

<p>For example, if the market conditions change, and that new expectations for the product are slowly becoming the norm, your old perfectly working system becomes legacy and technical debt. As an example, let&rsquo;s examine what happened to the capital markets software industry in response to the 2008 crisis.</p>

<ul>
<li>The sector became a lot more regulated</li>
<li>Risk control is moving from nightly batches to real time</li>
<li>The demand for complex (and risky) contracts decreased</li>
<li>As a consequence, trading on simpler contracts exploded</li>
</ul>


<p>All these elements combined invalidated existing architectures !</p>

<p>New technologies also create technical debt. Think the switch from mainframe to the web.</p>

<h2>What do we need then ?</h2>

<p>Should we stop using the boy scout rule ? Surely not, it would be a total non-sense. Submitting clean and readable code is a must.</p>

<p>But it is not enough. If you have spotted some large scale refactoring that could bring some improvement, we should do what a fund manager would do :</p>

<ol>
<li>Estimate the return on investment</li>
<li>If it is good enough, do it now</li>
</ol>


<p>Obviously, large refactorings should also be split into smaller <del>value adding</del> cost reducing items. But then what ?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nature-Software-Development-Simple-Valuable/dp/1941222374/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470290668&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+nature+of+software+development"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-02-when-the-boy-scout-rule-fails/nature-of-software.jpg" title="The cover of &ldquo;The Nature of Software Development&rdquo;" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nature-Software-Development-Simple-Valuable/dp/1941222374/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1470290668&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+nature+of+software+development">The Nature of Software Development</a> Ron Jefferies says that we need a unique value-based prioritization strategy for everything, including technical improvements. Once you&rsquo;ve got that, there&rsquo;s no sense in splitting and embedding your refactoring in other tasks, this will just increase your work in progress, reducing your throughput and cycle time.</p>

<p>Frankly, I think that&rsquo;s easier said than done. I can <em>think</em> of two ways :</p>

<ul>
<li>As Ron Jefferies tends to say, have a jelled-cross-functional team discuss and prioritize collectively</li>
<li>As <a href="http://reinertsenassociates.com/technical-debt-adding-math-metaphor/">Don Reintersen</a> advocates, use an <a href="/a-plan-for-technical-debt-lean-software-development-part-7/">economical framework</a> to estimate the return on investment</li>
</ul>


<p>At least that&rsquo;s a starting point !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
