<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mikado-method-organization-series | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/mikado-method-organization-series/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-02-15T06:10:55+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reducing the risks of large organization changes with the Mikado Method - part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-15T06:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the <a href="/reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-1/">previous post</a>, I presented both large scale code and organization changes. I highlighted how they face similar difficulties of huge <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Work_in_process">Work In Progress</a>. Let&rsquo;s see how programmers deal with these problems.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2018-01-22-reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-2/mind-your-wip.jpg" alt="A drawing of a wipe, with the text &quot;Mind your WIP&quot;" /></p>

<h2>The mikado method algorithm</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://mikadomethod.wordpress.com/">mikado method</a> is a programming technique to perform large <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_refactoring">code refactoring</a> one step at a time. It fixes the problematic situation we raised at the beginning of these posts. It enables developers to integrate their work with their teammates' continuously. It allows to build features and do the refactoring in parallel. Developers can also pause a mikado refactoring for a while if needed. On top of all this, it makes it easier for the full team to collaborate on the same refactoring.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Developers can pause a Mikado Method refactoring for a while if needed.</p></blockquote>

<p>Here is how it goes, but you can get a more detailed (and technical) description <a href="/10-things-to-know-that-will-make-you-great-at-refactoring-legacy-code/">here</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li>Try to do the change you want</li>
<li>If it the tests pass, great, you&rsquo;re done</li>
<li>Otherwise, add a node for the change you wanted to do in your mikado graph</li>
<li>Write down the errors you faced</li>
<li>Revert your change</li>
<li>Recurse from 1 for every error</li>
<li>Draw a dependency arrow from the nodes of errors to the node of your initial change</li>
</ol>


<p>The catch is that developers should revert the work they could not finish to move on !</p>

<h2>How to apply it to an organization change</h2>

<p>In some way, the Mikado Method is very similar to the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">improvement kata</a>. The flow of the Improvement kata goes on like that :</p>

<ol>
<li>Determine a target condition</li>
<li>Try to work with the target condition in place</li>
<li>If it works, you&rsquo;re done</li>
<li>Otherwise, understand the main impediment, and revert to the old way of doing things</li>
<li>Work to remove the impediment</li>
<li>Start again from step 2</li>
</ol>


<p>Have a look at <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/">these blog posts</a> for a more practical presentation of the improvement kata.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 The Mikado Method and the Improvement Kata are more than similar.</p></blockquote>

<p>Granted, the Mikado method and the improvement kata look similar. They are in fact more than similar. The improvement kata does not prescribe how you should fix your impediments. What&rsquo;s not explicit is that we can use it recursively to fix impediments ! That makes it almost identical to the Mikado Method, but for organization instead of code. It won&rsquo;t be a surprise to know that some companies have used the improvement kata for that. For example, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Practical-Approach-Large-Scale-Agile-Development/dp/0321821726?pd_rd_wg=UdZ7n&amp;pd_rd_r=ea4d5912-c825-432a-b633-ac6822a475f4&amp;pd_rd_w=rQ1LZ&amp;ref_=pd_gw_psimh&amp;pf_rd_r=0N5KT332R3TD0DWK8FM0&amp;pf_rd_p=a1e8e44e-a6a8-5785-afd0-7f174f0d74f9">HP used it to drive its Laser Jet team transformation</a>. Others have already used the <a href="http://nomad8.com/organisational-change-with-mikado/">Mikado Method for organization transformation</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://nomad8.com/organisational-change-with-mikado/"><img src="../imgs/2018-01-22-reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-2/orga-mikado-post-its.jpg" alt="Extract of the orga mikado graph used by the Sandy Mamoli" /></a><div class="image-credits"><a href="http://nomad8.com/organisational-change-with-mikado/">Original Post</a> by Sandy Mamoli</div></p>

<p>Suppose your organization wants to move to full Continuous Integration(TODO). It could start by trying to integrate all their devs in 10 minutes on a small group of teams. If it works, fine, other large teams can try it as well. Let&rsquo;s see what to do if it fails though. Thanks to a <a href="/blog/categories/retrospectives/">retrospective</a> teams understand that they need to master CI themselves first. In this case, they could revert large scale CI, and have one of the teams try to do continuous integration. If it works, fine, another team can try it too. If it does not, they&rsquo;ll do a post-mortem of some sort to understand the root issue, and work on it. For example, here the main impediment could be a coupled architecture. The fun thing would be to apply the Mikado Method to do this refactoring 😉.</p>

<p>As with the Mikado Method, it is possible to draw an organization change Mikado graph along the way :</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2018-01-22-reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-2/sample-mikado.png" alt="The mikado graph for the story above" /></p>

<p>The graph is a living artifact. As we try and revert new experiments, we should expand and collapse the graph. This creates a global and shared view of the state of the change. Needless to say that this is great for collaboration.</p>

<h2>To be continued (again)</h2>

<p>This was part 2 of a <a href="/blog/categories/mikado-method-organization-series/">series on applying the Mikado Method to organization changes</a>. I&rsquo;ll end this series up with next post, where I&rsquo;ll go through the pros and cons of the approach. <a href="https://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=PhilippeBourgau&amp;loc=en_US">Subscribe</a> to be notified as soon as next post is ready.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reducing the risks of large organization changes with the Mikado Method - part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-08T11:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Large scale agile transformations are often painful, stressful and &hellip; failed ! Mixing the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">Improvement Kata</a> and the <a href="https://mikadomethod.wordpress.com/">Mikado Method</a> can make them more successful.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2018-01-21-reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-1/mikado.jpg" alt="A drawing of entangled mikado sticks" /></p>

<p>The Mikado Method is a programming technique to reduce the risks of large code changes. Let&rsquo;s see how to apply it to organization changes.</p>

<h2><a href="https://dzone.com/articles/if-it-aint-broke-dont-fix-it">&ldquo;If it&rsquo;s not broke, don&rsquo;t touch it !&rdquo;</a></h2>

<p>A lot of programmers have learned this maxim the hard way. Here is how it goes.</p>

<p>It all starts with a shitty piece of code that gets into everyone&rsquo;s way as soon as they have to deal with it. It&rsquo;s badly written, difficult to understand, and very difficult to change. One day, a brave programmer suggests to rewrite or revamp it so that it gets easy to work with. This is not a small task, but after some discussion and negotiation, he gets a &lsquo;go&rsquo; from his team.</p>

<p>A few hours in this refactoring, he discovers that he needs to adapt other pieces of the code before he moves on. He leaves his work in progress as it is, and starts to change these pre-requisites. Unfortunately, these too have pre-requisite. Little by little, he builds up <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Work_in_process">work in progress</a>(WIP) on different parts of the code. He still has nothing working though ! He&rsquo;s beginning to have troubles keeping track of all his WIP. On top of that, he&rsquo;s wasting time integrating the work done by his colleagues with his WIP. As days pass by with nothing to show, his team begins to doubt that he&rsquo;ll be able to bring this to its end ! The situation as a whole accumulates an awful lot of stress on the developer. In the end, it is pretty likely that the team will abandon the whole thing.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 By never changing the code, programmers make it even harder to change</p></blockquote>

<p>The problem with this maxim is that by never changing the code, programmers make it even harder to change. In the end, this makes new features too expensive to build, which is pretty bad for the business.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s see how this related to large organization changes.</p>

<h2>The typical large scale agile transformation</h2>

<p>It all starts when a leader decides that Agile is the way to go. It could be because everyone is doing it or that he got convinced by someone. It could also be because consultants sold him a 10% productivity increase. The reason does not matter. What matters is that in a few months, all the company should switch to an Agile method. Large groups of people will have to switch to <a href="https://www.agilealliance.org/glossary/scrum-of-scrums/">Scrum of Scrum</a>, <a href="https://less.works/">LeSS</a>, <a href="http://www.scaledagileframework.com/">SAFe</a> or any other framework. Even if the transformation is split in product teams, these will still be big.</p>

<p>One great thing about these frameworks is that they show problems. After a few sprints people discover that they have troubles delivering incrementally. After analysis, they understand another deeper problem. Examples : bad management, legacy code, outdated tooling, bad underlying processes &hellip; As Agile is the new <a href="https://sourcemaking.com/antipatterns/golden-hammer">Golden Hammer</a>, the teams responsible of these problems in turn jump to Agile X method. Unfortunately, these too might fall into deeper problems &hellip; and the pattern repeats itself. Meanwhile, the top down transformation team sticks its own objectives. It continues to onboard new product teams to Agile, fueling the mess that is spreading.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2018-01-21-reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-1/hammer.jpg" alt="A golden hammer" /></p>

<p>At any moment, a very large proportion of the people in the company are in a state of transformation. This is pretty bad for productivity. What is even worse is that they are all facing the same root problems. They are all blocked in a sub-optimal state, impeded by the root problems. Following agile principles, they all start similar initiatives to workaround these issues ! They then need to coordinate with other teams, to avoid duplicate efforts. On top of that, as agile newbies, all these teams need coaches to help them at the same time.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Large scale Agile transformations are too often stressful for everyone &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>Needless to say that this situation is pretty stressful for everyone. It costs a lot, in productivity and consulting, for results yet to come. Despite reassurance that things will get better, the leader&rsquo;s trust is eroding.</p>

<p>The story ends bad when it goes on for too long. When the leader loses faith in the initiative, he cancels it, and goes back to the old ways. That&rsquo;s what we call the <a href="https://www.google.fr/search?q=agile+hangover">Agile hangover</a> : &ldquo;We tried it, but it was a mess. It does not work for us.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>To be continued</h2>

<p>As you can see, the two situations have a lot in common. Programmers have invented the Mikado Method to deal with large scale code changes. This was the first post of a <a href="/blog/categories/mikado-method-organization-series/">series about the Mikado Method and large scale organization changes</a>. In <a href="/reducing-the-risks-of-large-organization-changes-with-the-mikado-method-part-2/">next post</a>, we&rsquo;ll detail this technique, and see how to apply it on organization changes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
