<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: management30 | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/management30/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-07-12T06:04:26+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Agile transformations usually don't work - part 4 - Transparency]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-4-transparency/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-01T09:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-4-transparency</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the fourth and last post in a <a href="/blog/categories/agile-transformations-fail-series/">series about making large organizations more agile</a>. I encourage you to <a href="/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-1-the-situation/">start with the beginning</a>.</p>

<p>In the previous posts, I presented why large scale &ldquo;Agile&rdquo; transformation usually fail. Part of the solution is about giving people the time to learn and a safe environment. That&rsquo;s not enough though.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-01-11-why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-4-transparency/squirrel-with-helmet.jpg" alt="A squirrel with a helmet" /></p>

<h2>Provide the data</h2>

<p>I explained how <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Management_by_objectives">Management by Objectives</a> harms experimentation. I presented alternatives like Salary Formula, Badge Based Compensation and Merit Money.</p>

<p>An interesting commonality between these compensation practices is that they are transparent. When all this is public, people know what to do if they want to increase their income. For example : get a badge by learning something new, or collaborate with others to get monkey money. That&rsquo;s great, but they should also know how to increase the profits to get a bigger cake for everyone !</p>

<p>Management By Objectives is not only about compensation. It also cascades business objectives all the way down to everyone in the company. If we get rid of MBO, people still need to know what is important.</p>

<p>Let me introduce Objectives and Key Results, aka <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OKR">OKRs</a>. Intel invented OKRs. Nowadays, among many other companies, Google is famous for using them.</p>

<p><a href="http://upraise.io/blog/difference-mbo-okr/"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-01-11-why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-4-transparency/MBO_OKR.jpg" alt="A visual comparision of MBO and OKRs" /></a></p>

<blockquote><p>💡 OKRs have nothing to do with compensation !</p></blockquote>

<p>OKRs match this experimentation mindset. OKR objectives should be ambitious, with room for overachievement. OKRs also provide Key Results, which let people measure how well they are doing ! As OKRs are public, teams get a full understanding of the context of their actions.</p>

<p>To max out the value of OKRs, we should make as much data public as possible. Financial figures can really help teams to know if they are doing a good job.</p>

<p>The end result is that teams can take informed decisions. They can measure the impact of their work at their scale, but also on the full organization.</p>

<h2>Compelling mission</h2>

<p>A last good point of OKRs is that they make very good higher level backlog items. Both <a href="https://www.scrumalliance.org/community/articles/2014/march/stories-versus-themes-versus-epics">Team Epics</a> and full products can be OKRs. Even the company&rsquo;s mission can be an OKR. Check Toyota&rsquo;s mission, for example, &ldquo;Better cars for more people&rdquo;. This provides invaluable guidance for everyone to take day to day decisions.</p>

<p>In fact, a clear and motivating company mission statement is not only good but mandatory. Without it, people will go in all direction, resulting in very slow progress. It&rsquo;s an absolute pre-requisite for self organization to work. This is particularly a challenge for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business-to-business">business-to-business</a> companies. One symptom is when developers succumb to <a href="https://dev.to/tra/expert-resum-driven-development">Resume Driven Development</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Self organization does not work without a clear and compelling mission.</p></blockquote>

<h2>To summarize</h2>

<p>Organization&rsquo;s initiatives to become agile fast are doomed. They can at best expect small productivity and visibility improvements.</p>

<p>The benefits of being agile include lasting continuous improvement and business resiliency. Unfortunately, this cannot happen in a day. The road starts with the following :</p>

<ul>
<li>Creating a safe environment by getting the compensation issues out of the picture</li>
<li>Providing a clear goal and all the data people need to take informed decisions</li>
<li>Finally, leave the time for the people to learn</li>
</ul>


<p>I discovered another fun fact while looking for references. People from lean manufacturing have been <a href="http://blog.maskell.com/?p=2306">arguing the same thing</a> for decade ! The good news though, is that we ripe improvements all along the way !</p>

<p>This was the last post of a series about making large organizations more agile. Next week, I&rsquo;ll present an idea to apply the <a href="https://mikadomethod.wordpress.com/">Mikado Method</a> to refactor organizations one step at a time !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Agile transformations usually don't work - part 3 - What to do]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-3-what-to-do/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-25T09:43:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-3-what-to-do</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the third post in a <a href="/blog/categories/agile-transformations-fail-series/">series about making large organizations more agile</a>. I encourage you to <a href="/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-1-the-situation/">start with the beginning</a>.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s summarize the previous posts. Large scale &ldquo;Agile&rdquo; transformation programs usually fall short of their promise. One reason is that leaders forget to provide a safe context to learn.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-01-11-why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-3-what-to-do/donkey-carrot-stick.jpg" alt="A kid trying to drive a donkey with a carrot and a stick" /></p>

<h2>What should we do ?</h2>

<p>First, we should take the time ! Rome wasn&rsquo;t built in a day. The road to an agile organization is a never ending path. We should also remember what we are after :</p>

<ul>
<li>Super fast adaptation to business changes through massive decentralization</li>
<li>Low process overhead thanks to people&rsquo;s buy-in</li>
<li>Continuous innovation in both products and organization, relying on everyone&rsquo;s creativity</li>
</ul>


<p>This is far more ambitious than a mere 5% productivity increase !</p>

<h2>Be patient for people to learn</h2>

<p>The goal is for people to be able to take bigger decisions on the spot. No one can learn this in a few hours. All over the company, people will have to improve their problem solving skills. They might also need to learn how to do root cause analysis. They&rsquo;ll need to take into account the point of views of other people in the organization. Some will need to beef up their communication skills as well. All will need to master new collaboration practices to stay up to date with what is going on.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 An organization cannot be agile if all decisions have to go up and down the management ladder.</p></blockquote>

<p>That&rsquo;s a lot, and it takes time. The visible part of the iceberg, the collaboration practices, can be setup in a few weeks. But it won&rsquo;t yield much until the people are bold enough to take decisions by themselves.</p>

<p>First, I need to have a word about the workload in this section. If people are <a href="http://barryoreilly.com/2017/05/31/busy-to-death/">Busy to Death</a>, They won&rsquo;t have the time to learn. They won&rsquo;t even have the mood to think. Again, lasting productivity goes through sustainable pace. Slack time or a 20% policy are very good investments here !</p>

<p>Communication skills alone take months or years to improve. A communication training campaign can help to make the company ready to be more agile. In a previous team, new joiners used to attend a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nonviolent_Communication">Non-Violent Communication</a> training. Being transparent a constructive is a foundation of an agile organization.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Five-Dysfunctions-Team-Leadership-Fable/dp/0787960756/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1515736081&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=five+dysfunctions+of+a+team"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-01-11-why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-3-what-to-do/5-dysfunctions-of-a-team.jpg" alt="Pyramid of the 5 dysfunctions of a team book&quot;" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, root cause analysis and problem solving skills take practice to get around. Some organizations, used to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carrot_and_stick">carrots and sticks</a>, have been avoiding this for years ! Good coaches can teach this to teams. People first need to learn that it&rsquo;s OK to look into problems and to experiment solutions though. That&rsquo;s where a safe environment helps.</p>

<h2>The Safe environment enhancer</h2>

<p>If people remain afraid to fail, they won&rsquo;t do enough experiments. As a result, they&rsquo;ll learn slower. They&rsquo;ll also keep delegating more decisions ! The organization won&rsquo;t become very agile. Sure, leaders will get small productivity and predictability improvements. Unfortunately, exclusive focus on these puts innovation in danger.</p>

<p>People should have the means to experiment. By far the greatest experimentation killer is carrots and stick management. If people live in fear of losing their job, we have no chance of becoming more agile.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Encouraging experimentation while sticking to compensation by objectives is schizophrenic.</p></blockquote>

<p>The situation is only slightly better with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Management_by_objectives">management by objectives</a>. One of the reason is that as people start to expect their bonus, they also start to fear not having it next year ! We&rsquo;re back at the fear problem. There&rsquo;s a more direct issue with MBO though. A good experiment should be ambitious and have a high likelihood of failure. Unfortunately, people will negotiate unambitious objectives, to secure their bonus. In the end, people do far too few bold experiments and don&rsquo;t raise problems to safeguard their bonuses. Eventually, both people and the organization fail to learn.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Punished-Rewards-Trouble-Incentive-Praise/dp/0618001816"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-01-11-why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-3-what-to-do/punished-by-rewards.jpg" alt="Cover of the book &quot;Punished by rewards&quot;" /></a></p>

<p>Instead of using MBO, we need to find a different way to deal with compensation. The management 3.0 literature has plenty of ideas for that. For example :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://management30.com/practice/salary-formula/">Salary formula</a>. Some companies, like <a href="https://buffer.com/">Buffer</a> use a <a href="https://buffer.com/salary">transparent formula</a> to compute everyone&rsquo;s compensation. This base salary is independent from any subjective performance evaluation. On top <a href="https://open.buffer.com/transparent-pay-revolution/">boosting motivation</a>, it provides plenty of room for experimentation.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p><a href="https://qz.com/169147/applications-have-doubled-to-the-company-that-discloses-its-salaries/">After disclosing employee salaries, Buffer was inundated with resumes</a></p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.holacracy.org/badge-based-compensation-app/">Badge-based compensation</a>. Holocracy describes how to take valuable skills into account in a salary formula. To get a badge on a topic, you need to be recognized by the people who already own this badge. Examples of badges can be &ldquo;UX Expert&rdquo; or &ldquo;Senior Software Engineer&rdquo;.</li>
<li><a href="https://management30.com/practice/merit-money/">Merit money</a>. Company profits redistribution to employees should be both motivating and fair. Instead of typical yearly bonuses, merit money is a crowd-sourced money allocation scheme. Everyone regularly receives a fixed amount of monkey money. You should give some back to a colleague who helped you. You could also give some to acknowledge someone else&rsquo;s great job. Every month a lottery is played to know if employees should receive their share of profits. If so, everyone gets his share in proportion with the monkey money they received. Otherwise, profits accumulate until the next lottery.</li>
</ul>


<p>We could worry that dropping MBO will drop people&rsquo;s motivation as well. It turns out it&rsquo;s the exact opposite ! Check out <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LFlvor6ZHdY">this talk</a> by Daniel Pinks to understand how bonuses kill motivation.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LFlvor6ZHdY" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>To be continued</h2>

<p>This was part 3 of a <a href="/blog/categories/agile-transformations-fail-series/">series of posts on making large organizations more agile</a>. We&rsquo;re almost at the end. <a href="/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-4-transparency/">The last post</a> will dig into how to provide the data to everyone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kudo Boxes for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/kudo-boxes-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-30T04:48:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/kudo-boxes-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How do you get your kids to participate with housekeeping ? I guess that&rsquo;s the dream of all parents. As so, we&rsquo;ve tried quite a lot of tactics throughout the years. Carrots and stick never really worked, so we tried positive reinforcement, gratitude &hellip; Unfortunately, nothing really made any noticeable improvement.</p>

<h2>Until now !</h2>

<p>At work, we&rsquo;ve been using <a href="https://management30.com/practice/intrinsic-motivation/">Kudo Boxes</a> for a <a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">while now</a>. A kudo box is a small mailbox where teammates can drop a word of thank or some praise (No blame allowed here !)</p>

<p>Why not try the same thing at home ? During the summer holidays, we&rsquo;ve build kudo boxes for everyone in the family.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-08-30-kudo-boxes-for-kids/kudo-box.jpg" alt="Our family Kudo Box" /></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a nice and easy way to express gratitude for any good stuff our kids do. The great thing is that it&rsquo;s cheap, it&rsquo;s easy to carry cards around and to hand one out at any moment.</p>

<h2>What happened ?</h2>

<p>First, we now have very joyful kudo reading sessions : our kids rush to the boxes to check for new cards. The second most noticeable change we observed is that they are both participating more in the house chores ! For example, as soon as we start cooking, they might spontaneously dress the table up. Or they might bring tools to help us as best as they can when we are tending to the garden.</p>

<p>To summarize, it seems it brought a lot of joy and love in the house.</p>

<h2>How we started ?</h2>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-08-30-kudo-boxes-for-kids/typical-kudo-box.jpg" alt="The typical employee's kudo box, as can be found on the management 3.0 website" /></p>

<p>They are many ways to build a kudo box. The simplest way might be to get an old shoe box, and to cut a hole in the cover. We bought a wooden box with four drawers, and spent some time all together to decorate it. This in itself was already fun.</p>

<p>We started using simple pieces of paper as kudo cards, but I later downloaded and printed a bunch of <a href="https://management30.com/product/kudo-cards/">official kudo cards</a> from the Management 3.0 website. It turns out there is a version in <a href="https://1qjpt15fhlq3xjfpm2utibj1-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/Management30-KudoCards-2015-self-print-A4-French.pdf">french</a>.</p>

<h2>Bonus</h2>

<p>An unexpected, but great, side effect is that my spouse and I started to get kudos as well ! It&rsquo;s really nice to receive a word from your kids. For example, here is a drawing I got from my daughter.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-08-30-kudo-boxes-for-kids/kudo-drawing.jpg" alt="A nice drawing from my daughter that I found in my kudo box" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Grow a Culture Book]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-grow-a-culture-book/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-08T05:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-grow-a-culture-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you read valve&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf">Handbook for new employees</a> ?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-08-08-how-to-grow-a-culture-book/valve-handbook-for-new-employees.jpg" alt="A stack of Valve's Handbook for new employees" /></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://management30.com">Management 3.0</a> terms, that&rsquo;s a <a href="https://management30.com/practice/value-stories/">culture book</a>. It&rsquo;s a great way to build and crystallize a culture, and it serves as a guide for newcomers, and can later serve as an hiring ad for your team or company.</p>

<p>The good thing about a culture book, is that you don&rsquo;t have to write it in one go. It&rsquo;s a living artifact anyway, so you&rsquo;d better not ! Our current culture book has emerged from a collection of pages in our wiki.</p>

<h2>It started as working agreements</h2>

<p>The first real contributions to our culture book (though we did not know it at the time) was spending some time in retrospectives to define and review our working and coding conventions.</p>

<p>When we started doing retrospectives, we had to discuss, agree and formalize the decisions we made about our way of working. We usually did a &lsquo;review how we work&rsquo; activity at the beginning the retros, spending 10 minutes to make sure we all understood and agreed on our current working conventions. If there was any disagreement or update required, we would discuss them during the retro, and at the end, add, remove or modify items from our agreement page.</p>

<h2>It continued as self-organization workshops</h2>

<p>After a while, we had built up a pretty extensive set of working and coding conventions. The team had already become quite productive, but to keep the momentum in the long run, we needed to increase self-organization. By reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Jurgen-Appelo/e/B00460MCJM/ref=sr_tc_2_0?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;qid=1470715896&amp;sr=8-2-ent">Management 3.0 books</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Workout-Practices-Improve-Delight-Management-ebook/dp/B00N6REYKQ/ref=asap_bc?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8#navbar">Management Workout</a> (which has been re-edited as <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Managing-Happiness-Games-Practices-Motivate/dp/1119268680/ref=asap_bc?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8">Managing for Happiness</a>) in particular, I found description about how to use a <a href="https://management30.com/practice/delegation-board/">delegation board</a> and <a href="https://management30.com/product/delegation-poker/">delegation pokers</a> to measure and formalize the current delegation level of a team.</p>

<p>We did this, and started a lot of self-organization workshops :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/">Stop feeling like a kid every time you ask a day off</a></li>
<li><a href="/scrum-teams-do-not-need-a-scrum-master/">Scrum Teams Do Not Need a Scrum Master</a></li>
<li><a href="/make-hiring-everyones-business/">Make hiring everyone&rsquo;s business</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">How to deal with the incentive system in an agile team ?</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/">How We Decentralized Our Company&rsquo;s Training Program</a></li>
</ul>


<p>After each of these workshops, we created a wiki page, explaining how we planned to handle the subject in the team.</p>

<h2>The book</h2>

<p>At that point, we had fairly extensive and formal descriptions of our working practices and conventions. By reading this set of pages, someone would get a pretty accurate grasp of our principles and values.</p>

<p>Wondering how we could write our own culture book, I had an &ldquo;Aha !&rdquo; moment and realized that all I had to do was to create a wiki page pointing to all our different agreement pages. This only took 5 minutes.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-08-08-how-to-grow-a-culture-book/content.jpg" alt="The table of content of our culture book" /></p>

<p>At the moment, our culture book serves 3 purposes :</p>

<ul>
<li>documentation for the team members</li>
<li>guide for newcomers</li>
<li>description about how we work for people in the company who might want to move to our team</li>
</ul>


<p>Next step would be to add a dash of design, a few war stories, export it as a PDF, and use it outside to advertise the team and the company.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How We Decentralized Our Company's Training Program]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-18T05:31:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Maybe your company too has a development program you can use to track and organize your training path. That&rsquo;s already great ! It is often not perfect though. Sometimes, the initiative in itself can feel like an afterthought. Some other times, the process is completely left to the employee and his manager, with varying results, from great to forced upon everyone.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-04-18-how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/learning.jpg" alt="A 'learning' word cloud" /></p>

<h2>How did we rebuild this program in our team</h2>

<p>As you might remember if you read my <a href="/blog/categories/selforganizing/">previous posts</a>, we started a self organization initiative using a <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/delegation-employee-engagement/">delegation board</a>. When we tried to decentralize <a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">the end of year evaluation</a>, we started discussing the subjects of personal development. We decided to have a dedicated workshop about this subject</p>

<h2>Guiding principles</h2>

<p>In our company, the development program allows a manager to assign specific learning goals to his collaborators, and anyone can also create his own goals to justify going to specific trainings. Starting from that, we agreed that the development program should be used to help anyone in the team to improve skills that are interesting for both the company and the employee. If the employee is interested in something completely unrelated to work, then he should obviously tackle that in his own time. If the company needs its employee to acquire some immediate mandatory skills, then that should be part of the daily job and subject to the end of year evaluation.</p>

<p>The idea is to try to find a win-win combinations, were employees are motivated to work their best at a company that they know helps them to full-fill their long term goals.</p>

<h2>What did we came us with ?</h2>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-04-18-how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/mentor-mentee.jpg" alt="A lion and a lion cub side by side" /></p>

<p>This workshop was quite effective :</p>

<ul>
<li>First of all, everyone is responsible for his own development, it&rsquo;s a chance offered by the company. It cannot be forced unto people.</li>
<li>It is based on volunteer mentorship : everyone should have regular meetings with his mentor to asses his progress on his long term goal, to try to get feedback and ideas about how to move forward. We started by saying that the team leader is the default mentor, but anyone can find another mentor at any moment.</li>
<li>The process starts with the search for a long term goal. Examples are &ldquo;I want to be an agile coach&rdquo;, or &ldquo;I want to be a performance expert&rdquo;</li>
<li>With the help of the mentor if needed, the long term goal should be split in yearly objectives and tracked using <a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/HenrikJanVanderPol/how-to-outperform-anyone-else-introduction-to-okr">OKRs</a></li>
<li>Everyone is free to track his progress has he wishes. Visual tracking makes the discussion with the mentor a lot easier. We have been looking at tools to track OKRs but it was surprisingly difficult to find one that suited our use. Most are enterprisy tools with manager-managee relationships. We just wanted simple personal tracking tools. For my part, I adapted a <a href="https://trello.com/b/MPM4rspd/okrs">Trello</a> board I found on the internet.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>After doing a few months of this, I can say that this has a positive aspect on motivation, people told me that they felt more in control of their destiny. Something else I noted, is that junior developers need help and guidance. They often don&rsquo;t really know what they want to do in a few years, so they really need a mentor to help them find out the what and the how. The other side of this is that a team obviously needs senior developers to act as mentor &hellip; among other things.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
