<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: incremental-software-development | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/incremental-software-development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-08-08T13:37:42+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Incremental Software Development Strategies for Large Scale Refactoring #1 : Constant Merciless Refactoring]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-1-constant-merciless-refactoring/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-02T08:31:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-1-constant-merciless-refactoring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/incremental-software-development-techniques-for-large-scale-refactorings/">My previous post</a> advocated incremental software development for large scale refactorings. It&rsquo;s less risky and it prevents tunnel effects. Most of all, it&rsquo;s a lot easier to convince business people of engaging in a refactoring this way.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s one thing to understand why it&rsquo;s the way to go, but it&rsquo;s another to be able to do it ! In this post, I&rsquo;ll start by explaining how to find the time to do constant <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/refactor.html">merciless refactoring</a>.</p>

<p>This is the sixth post in <a href="/blog/categories/large-scale-refactoring-sponsorship-series/">a series about how to get sponsorship for large scale refactoring</a>. If you haven&rsquo;t, I encourage you to start from <a href="/how-to-convince-your-business-to-sponsor-a-large-scale-refactoring/">the beginning</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-08-02-incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-1-constant-merciless-refactoring/recurring-cleanup.jpg" alt="Constant Merciless Refactoring illustrated as a recurring cleanup activity" /></p>

<h2><del>Steal</del> Take the time for constant merciless refactoring</h2>

<blockquote><p>If it hurts, do it more often ! <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/FrequencyReducesDifficulty.html">Wisdom of the internet</a></p></blockquote>

<p>As a child, I used to be a very untidy kid. Every few week, my room would get in a real mess, and my mum would order me to clean all this mess. I would then lose 1 or 2 hours tidying my room up. She used to tell me that if I kept things tidy as I used them, I would not have to lose this time. From the top of my 10 years old, I would judge this advice as nonsense. </p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-08-02-incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-1-constant-merciless-refactoring/messy-bedroom.jpg" alt="This is the kind of mess my bedroom used to be in, when I was a kid, before I learned the virtues of constant merciless refactoring" /></p>

<p>Fast forward a few years, I am myself a parent and I&rsquo;ve been working with legacy code for many years. These years have taught me how much I was wrong &hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 The easiest refactorings to negotiate are the ones we don&rsquo;t have to talk about !</p></blockquote>

<p>The more refactoring we embed in &lsquo;Business As Usual&rsquo;, the more we&rsquo;ll do, and the less we&rsquo;ll argue with the business. We can wonder if this is still &lsquo;professional&rsquo; ? In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Art-Agile-Development-Pragmatic-Software/dp/0596527675/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1533190334&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+agile">The Art Of Agile Development</a>, <a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/">James Shore</a> explains that managing technical debt is the key to long term productivity. (Details in the <a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/risk_management.html">Risk Management section of his book</a>). As developers, <em>we</em> are the only experts in the code, the responsibility to keep it clean falls on us.</p>

<blockquote><p>Never ask the permission to do a good job ! <a href="http://docondev.com/">Doc Norton</a></p></blockquote>

<p>There&rsquo;s more to constant merciless refactoring ! It also keeps us in a good position to accept new features or refactorings later down the road.</p>

<p>Following are the 3 practices that make up constant merciless refactoring.</p>

<h2>Yesterday&rsquo;s weather and slack time</h2>

<p>20 years ago, a promises of agile software development was to stick to a <a href="http://www.sustainablepace.net/what-is-sustainable-pace">sustainable pace</a>. When we are working with a flavor of <a href="https://www.scrum.org/">Scrum</a>, we can rely on it&rsquo;s literature to inject some <a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/slack.html">slack time</a>.  Slack time is buffer time at the end of every iteration. We should not plan any work during the slack, to accommodate with the unexpected. It&rsquo;s a way to deliver on forecasts, whatever happens.</p>

<p>In short, if your velocity chart looks something like that :</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-08-02-incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-1-constant-merciless-refactoring/velocity.jpg" alt="Drawing of a fluctuating team velocity. This is often the result of not enough constant merciless refactoring" /></p>

<p>Scrum tells us to plan what you delivered in your worst iteration for the next one ! When things will work bad, we&rsquo;re still pretty likely to deliver what we wanted. When things work well, we&rsquo;ll have time to tackle refactoring.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lot more to say about slack time. How to take some when you are using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban">Kanban</a> ? How to make sure you keep some when your velocity becomes pretty stable ? How to do you increase your velocity in the long term ? (I guess I&rsquo;ll have to write a full blog post about this some day.)</p>

<h2>The Boy Scout Rule</h2>

<p>I already blogged about the <a href="http://www.informit.com/articles/article.aspx?p=1235624&amp;seqNum=6">Boy Scout Rule</a>. Here is how <a href="https://blog.cleancoder.com/">Uncle Bob</a> wrote it :</p>

<blockquote><p>Always leave the file you are editing a little better than you found it. Bob Martin</p></blockquote>

<p>Following this simple rule goes a long way to keep the code clean and ready for larger refactorings. It works arm in arm with Yesterday&rsquo;s weather principle. The extra time we take for clean up impacts our capacity to plan stories and features. This creates time to keep on doing the boy scout rule in future iterations.</p>

<p>How &lsquo;clean&rsquo; the code should be is a team decision. Coding conventions and a static code analyzer are very important to track the boy scout rule. I learned that code reviews, pairing, mobbing and <a href="/blog/categories/team-randori-series/">coding dojos</a> are great to agree on coding conventions.</p>

<h2>Embedding refactoring in features</h2>

<p>The Test Driven Development loop goes as Red-Green-Refactor.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-08-02-incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-1-constant-merciless-refactoring/red-green-refactor.jpg" alt="TDD's Red-Green-Refactor loop. Itself highlighting Constant Merciless Refactoring as a recurring activity" /></p>

<p>The same loop goes on at larger scale for Acceptance or Feature Test. When repeated many times, the loop could as well be Refactor &ndash; Red &ndash; Green. In fact, it&rsquo;s a lot easier to refactor when you know what feature you want to build than at the end of the previous one. (Nat Pryce <a href="http://natpryce.com/articles/000780.html">wrote about that</a> in more details)</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 &ldquo;Disguise&rdquo; refactoring as first technical sub tasks of features to get them prioritized.</p></blockquote>

<p>All this to say, we should start our features with the pre-requisite refactoring ! We should not build features on shaky foundations. We should also impact our estimates. In fact, it&rsquo;s a lot easier to justify to business people at that moment. We don&rsquo;t need to mention &lsquo;refactoring&rsquo; or &lsquo;clean up&rsquo;. We can use technical sub-tasks to track these technical refactorings. Technical sub-tasks are the team&rsquo;s and don&rsquo;t need to be understandable by business people.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-08-02-incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-1-constant-merciless-refactoring/tech-tasks-sea-level.jpg" alt="Technical tasks drawn &quot;Under the sea&quot; and visible to devs only. This leaves them room to do constant merciless refactoring" /></p>

<h2>To be continued</h2>

<p>Finding the time for constant merciless refactoring is one thing, but how do we fit the work in these short slots ? In the <a href="http://eepurl.com/dxKE95">next post</a>, I&rsquo;ll continue about how to actually work in baby steps.</p>

<p>This was the sixth post about <a href="/blog/categories/large-scale-refactoring-sponsorship-series/">how to get sponsorship for large scale refactoring</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Incremental Software Development for Large Scale Refactorings]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/incremental-software-development-techniques-for-large-scale-refactorings/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-26T09:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/incremental-software-development-techniques-for-large-scale-refactorings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My <a href="/principles-that-will-make-you-become-a-badass-developer/">previous post</a> was about the badass developer attitude. More specifically, how it can buy sponsorship for large scale refactorings. Unfortunately, attitude is not enough. We also need to be able to deliver in a way that builds trust with the business. Most of all, business <a href="/how-to-convince-your-business-to-sponsor-a-large-scale-refactoring/">is scared of the tunnel effect</a>. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iterative_and_incremental_development">Incremental software development</a> techniques allows to deliver large scale refactoring step by step. Not only that, but it also allows to do so alongside business features. That&rsquo;s how badass developers walk their talk and gain the business people&rsquo;s trust.</p>

<p>This is the fifth post in <a href="/blog/categories/large-scale-refactoring-sponsorship-series/">a series about how to get sponsorship for large scale refactoring</a>. If you haven&rsquo;t, I encourage you to start from <a href="/how-to-convince-your-business-to-sponsor-a-large-scale-refactoring/">the beginning</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-07-20-incremental-software-development-techniques-for-large-scale-refactorings/incremental-plant.jpg" alt="Drawing of a plant at different stages of growth, illustrating Incremental Software Development" /></p>

<h2>Why does incremental software development matter ?</h2>

<h3>A short story</h3>

<p>A few years ago, I joined a team whose work involved a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain-specific_language">Domain Specific Language</a> and a parser. The parser had grown in an ad-hoc way for a few years, and was now both very brittle and difficult to extend. We knew the way to go was to adopt a more solid parsing approach. We wanted to migrate to <a href="http://www.antlr.org/">ANTLR</a> and a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-pass_compiler">multi pass parser</a>.</p>

<p>As always, the business was very pushy for new features. There was no way we could have stoped everything for a full parser re-write. We explained to them that some of their features would be impossible to write without the new parser. We suggested that we work on migrating the parser as a background technical Epic. We did so using incremental software development techniques.</p>

<p>It took us a few months to migrate the parser. Meanwhile, we kept the software in a releasable state. This allowed us to validate our progress on the refactoring. We could continue to release features. We were able to share our progress on the refactoring with  the business people. They were very happy with the way we did this refactoring. In fact, it set a standard about how to prepare the software for big features later on.</p>

<h3>The real problems</h3>

<p>To understand why incremental software development works, let&rsquo;s understand the alternatives' problems. The main alternative it to do the refactoring in one massive task. This kind of initiative screams &ldquo;Tunnel effect waiting to happen&rdquo; ! The <a href="http://www.wethetalent.co/data-robots-ai/the-tunnel-effect-and-the-abstruse-trap/">tunnel effect</a> scares business people for 3 reasons :</p>

<ol>
<li>Because they don&rsquo;t know how much money they&rsquo;ll need to put in the tunnel to get out of it</li>
<li>Because they don&rsquo;t know when they&rsquo;ll get the other features which they are also waiting for</li>
<li>To be blocked in the tunnel if something unexpected and important comes along</li>
</ol>


<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-07-20-incremental-software-development-techniques-for-large-scale-refactorings/tunnel-effect.jpg" alt="Picture of someone holding a light, alone in a tunnel. Incremental Software Development helps to avoid the tunnel effect when performing a large scale refactoring" /></p>

<p>Delivering a large scale refactoring with incremental software development fixes these 3 points.</p>

<ul>
<li>Every commit is a step forward while keeping the system in a releasable state. If ever something unexpected comes along, we can pause the refactoring for a while. (point 3)</li>
<li>Not all the team has to work on refactoring at the same time. Working on the refactoring does not block the delivery of other features. (point 2)</li>
<li>Finally, after working on a refactoring for a while, it becomes easier to have an idea of how long it will take. (point 1)</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>💡 Incremental software development fixes the business people&rsquo;s fear of refactoring tunnel.</p></blockquote>

<p>It is true that performing the refactoring in one team-wide batch would be more efficient. It would reduce the overall Work In Progress and get it done quicker. Unfortunately, it&rsquo;s also a lot more scary for business people !</p>

<h2>Incremental Software Development techniques</h2>

<p>Like any skills, we can learn these techniques. Some are easy, and we can learn them from books. Others are more difficult and are usually learned through hard won experience. They can also be learned from a veteran developer in your team who&rsquo;s been through all this already. If you aren&rsquo;t or don&rsquo;t have a veteran around, we can still manage. <a href="https://medium.com/the-crossover-cast/deliberate-practice-learn-like-an-expert-cc3114b8a10e">Deliberate practice</a> is a great way to <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-i-got-my-feet-wet-with-machine-learning-with-the-first-20-hours/">learn almost anything</a>. <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/coding-dojo/">Coding dojos</a> are the thing here (I&rsquo;ll write more about this later).</p>

<p>Once we master these skills, a lot of things change. First, we can do refactoring without harming our relationship with business people. Second, it builds enough self confidence among developers to negotiate with business people. This in itself, makes us more credible in their eyes. As a result, they are more likely to compromise on prioritizing refactoring.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Mastering incremental software development builds self-confidence for developers.</p></blockquote>

<h2>To be continued</h2>

<p>This was the fifth post about <a href="/blog/categories/large-scale-refactoring-sponsorship-series/">how to get sponsorship for large scale refactoring</a>. In the next posts, I&rsquo;ll deal headlong with the actual techniques. <a href="/incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-1-constant-merciless-refactoring/">How to get bandwidth</a> ? How to work in baby steps ? How to track the progress ? How to deal with the large scale ? Finally how to go further ? As you can see, there is still a lot to come, so <a href="http://eepurl.com/dxKE95">stay tuned</a> !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
