<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: concurrency | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/concurrency/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-28T07:20:24+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Actors and Green Threads in Java Demystified]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/actors-and-green-threads-in-java-demystified/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-15T13:17:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/actors-and-green-threads-in-java-demystified</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After finishing my <a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata">concurrency-kata</a>, one of the things that most surprised me, is how simple it was to prototype the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actor_model">Actor Model</a> in Java using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_threads">Green Threads</a>.</p>

<h2>The Code</h2>

<p>First, here is the base class for all actors.</p>

<p>```java
public class Actor implements Runnable {</p>

<pre><code>private final ExecutorService threadPool;
private final ConcurrentLinkedQueue&lt;Runnable&gt; mailbox = new ConcurrentLinkedQueue&lt;&gt;();
private boolean stoped;

public Actor(ExecutorService threadPool) {
    this.threadPool = threadPool;
}

public void run() {
    if (stoped) {
        return;
    }

    Runnable nextMessage = mailbox.poll();
    if (nextMessage != null) {
        nextMessage.run();
    }
    submitContinuation();
}

public void start() {
    submitContinuation();
}

protected void stop() {
    stoped = true;
}

protected void send(Runnable runnable) {
    mailbox.add(runnable);
}

private void submitContinuation() {
    threadPool.submit(this);
}
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>As you can see, I simply used Runnable as the type of the messages.</p>

<p>The Actor itself is Runnable, meaning that it can be submitted to the thread pool. When executed :</p>

<ol>
<li>it tries to handle a message from the mailbox if there is one.</li>
<li>It then re-submits the actor itself</li>
</ol>


<p>This ensures that only one thread is executing messages on an actor at a given time, and it also avoids spawning new thread for every new actor.</p>

<p>As an example, here is how I used this to make an actor of an existing InProcessChatRoom class.</p>

<p>```java
public interface ChatRoom {</p>

<pre><code>void broadcast(Output client, String message);
...
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>```java
public class InProcessChatRoom implements ChatRoom {</p>

<pre><code>...
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>```java
public class ChatRoomActor extends Actor implements ChatRoom {</p>

<pre><code>private final ChatRoom realChatroom;

public ChatRoomActor(ChatRoom realChatroom, ExecutorService threadPool) {
    super(threadPool);
    this.realChatroom = realChatroom;
    start();
}

@Override
public void broadcast(final Output client, final String message) {
    send(new Runnable() {
        @Override
        public void run() {
            realChatroom.broadcast(client, message);
        }
    });
}
...
</code></pre>

<p>}
```
ChatRoomActor is in fact some kind of proxy to use from other actors to send messages to the chat room.</p>

<p>As with any implementation of the Actors Model, the neet thing is the separation of threading and logic. That makes it so much simpler ! (You can get more detail about the complexity I am talking about by taking a look at the <a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata">concurrency-kata</a>)</p>

<h2>Performances</h2>

<p>Here is a performance summary of this implementation compared to others on a &ldquo;throughput vs clients&rdquo; benchmark of the style &ldquo;Enter while others are talking&rdquo;</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata"><img class="center" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/philou/concurrency-kata/master/enter-while-others-are-talking.png" title="Result graphs of benchmark enter while others are talking" ></a></p>

<p>Results can be disappointing compared to other implementations but the example itself is a bit misleading. The chatroom does exclusively message passing, there is not much computation to parallelize, in a different setting, the results would have been completely different.</p>

<h2>Limitations</h2>

<p>As you can see, this implementation is just a quick prototype, nothing production ready. Here are the main limitations I can think of right now :</p>

<ul>
<li>It uses <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Busy_waiting">Busy Waiting</a> for the next message, meaning that it consumes unnecessary resources, and that more important messages to other Actors might be delayed</li>
<li>Usually, actor messages are selected on their type rather than on their order of arrival, this is not the case here</li>
<li>The usage of the Runnable interface as base message type, though handy, opens the door to inter-thread calls that might violate the model altogether</li>
<li>There is absolutely no support of out of process actors until the messages are Serializable</li>
</ul>


<h2>Going Further</h2>

<p>I started this <a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata">concurrency-kata</a> as a training material about concurrency for colleagues at <a href="http://www.murex.com">work</a>. In the spirit of the coding kata, it&rsquo;s a git repo you can walk, explore and experiment with.</p>

<p>So if you want to learn more about different models of concurrency, you are welcome to have a look at the How-To section in the <a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata">README</a> file.</p>

<p>On my part, although it was a lot more work than I would have guessed at the beginning, I barely scratch the surface of the subject ! I could now :</p>

<ul>
<li>extract the <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communicating_sequential_processes">CSP</a> or Actor implementation and make them more robust</li>
<li>practice and present the whole kata as a 2 hours live coding session</li>
<li>prepare a hands-on training about concurrency</li>
</ul>


<p>So, if you are willing to do any of the above you are welcome to contribute !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
