<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: selforganizing | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/selforganizing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-08T06:40:17+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Ultimate Jira Personal Kanban]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-ultimate-jira-personal-kanban/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:46:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-ultimate-jira-personal-kanban</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few years ago, I <a href="/bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/">wrote</a> about how I started to use <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira">Jira</a> as my <a href="http://www.personalkanban.com/pk/">personal Kanban</a> board <a href="https://twitter.com/work_at_murex">at work</a>. A lot of things have changed since then, which brought me to update my board and make it even more productive !</p>

<h2>The context</h2>

<p>During the almost 18 months since I wrote this first post, a lot of things have changed in my daily work (hopefully : I&rsquo;m not doing the same thing again and again !). Essentially, I got involved in more projects, some of which involve people from all around the company and some of which don&rsquo;t require any code to be written. For example, I&rsquo;m now engaged in our Agile Community of Practice, where I sometimes contribute content.</p>

<p>Here are the consequences on my work :</p>

<ul>
<li>I have more tasks to deal with, not necessarily more work, but still more tasks</li>
<li>I have more sources of tasks : tasks can come from any of the projects I am involved in</li>
<li>I have more tasks depending on other people, and that are in a <code>WAITING</code> state meanwhile</li>
</ul>


<p>I had to adapt my personal Kanban to this new workload.</p>

<h2>The changes</h2>

<p>As I explained in <a href="/bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/">the previous description of my Jira Personal Kanban</a>, I am using a custom project and Kanban board to aggregate all my tasks from various projects, in order to see everything in a single unique place. Here are the changes I&rsquo;ve made since, so if you haven&rsquo;t yet, it might be a good idea to read <a href="/bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/">that previous version</a> first.</p>

<h3>Quick filters</h3>

<p>In his post <a href="http://paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html">Maker&rsquo;s Schedule, Manager&rsquo;s Schedule</a> Paul Graham explained the challenge of having a lot of non-programming work to do everyday for programmers. He then advises to use slots for different activities during the day, in order to keep uninterrupted chunks of time to do creative work. To apply this technique, I reserved &lsquo;Unbookable except for X&rsquo; slots in my calendar everyday.</p>

<p>I had previously been using Swim-lanes to track work from different projects. This turned out not to scale very well to more projects : it made the board messy, and I kept being distracted by all these other tasks. I ditched all the Swim-lanes (not exactly, I kept one for urgent issues only). Instead of Swim-lanes for tracking projects, I now use Quick Filters. I created such filters as <code>With Project X</code> and <code>Without Project X</code>. During the day, when I want to focus on Project X, I use quick filters to only show tasks related to it.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-03-03-my-ultimate-jira-personal-kanban/quick-filters.jpg" alt="Quick filters screen capture" /></p>

<h3>Day markers</h3>

<p>I have a daily routine of checking what&rsquo;s on my plate and deciding what I&rsquo;d like to achieve during the day (picking the right time to do this is an art in itself). In order to keep track of this, I use special day marker tasks : as <code>^^^ TODAY ^^^</code>, <code>^^^ TOMORROW ^^^</code> and <code>^^^ THIS WEEK ^^^</code>. This tasks are always in my <code>TODO</code> column, and will never be completed. I move them around to mark what I expect to finish at different time horizon. Ex : everything above <code>^^^ TODAY ^^^</code> should be finished before the end of the day.</p>

<p>Again, this helps me to focus on today&rsquo;s activities, and to do just enough prioritization.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-03-03-my-ultimate-jira-personal-kanban/day-markers.jpg" alt="Day marker tasks screen capture" /></p>

<p>One last thing here, you&rsquo;ll have noticed the Epic for these special tasks. It&rsquo;s a way to identify them in JQL queries.</p>

<h3>WAITING flag</h3>

<p>Quite often, you have tasks waiting for someone else. That&rsquo;s surely not the most efficient situation, but once you leave the comfort of your focused dev team, handoffs are often the norm (at least until the lean principles spread in every part of the business). Status of waiting tasks is worth checking regularly, but very certainly not many times per day !</p>

<p>Again, leaving them in my board created useless distraction. I have now taken the habit of renaming the tasks I&rsquo;m waiting for with a <code>[WAITING] ...</code> prefix. On top of that, I created 2 quick filters <code>WAITING</code> and <code>Without WAITING</code> to quickly check and then forget about waiting tasks.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-03-03-my-ultimate-jira-personal-kanban/waiting-tasks.jpg" alt="Waiting tasks screen capture" /></p>

<h3>Watching tasks I&rsquo;m not the assignee of</h3>

<p>On some occasions, we might be two of us working on the same task, or I might want to keep an eye on a task to know if something is needed from me. As there is only a single possible assignee in Jira, I changed my global filters to also include tasks with a custom label <code>pbourgau-watch</code>. Any time I want to add a task in my board, I just add this label to it.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-03-03-my-ultimate-jira-personal-kanban/pbourgau-watch.jpg" alt="Screen capture of a task description I'm not the assignee of" /></p>

<h3>Getting the Lean reports back</h3>

<p>In order not to have too many old tasks in my board, I used to filter out old items in the global filter. This did the job, but at the cost of invalidating the lean reports (cumulative flow and control charts). In order to get these back, I removed this constraint from the global filter, and created yet another quick filter <code>Without Old</code> which I almost always keep on.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-03-03-my-ultimate-jira-personal-kanban/control-chart.jpg" alt="Control chart screen capture" /></p>

<h2>Scripts</h2>

<h4>Global Filter</h4>

<p>```sql
project in (POP, POPABTODO, &ldquo;Development Engineering Program&rdquo;, COPA)
AND type != Epic
AND (Assignee = pbourgau OR</p>

<pre><code>Co-Assignees in (pbourgau) OR 
mentors in (pbourgau) OR
labels in (pbourgau-watch))
</code></pre>

<p>ORDER BY Rank ASC
```</p>

<h4>Quick Filters</h4>

<p>```sql
&mdash; With &ldquo;Project X&rdquo; + Day marker tasks (Epic link &hellip;) + tasks containing &ldquo;BRANDING&rdquo;
project = &ldquo;Project X&rdquo; or &ldquo;Epic Link&rdquo; = POPABTODO-410 or summary ~ &ldquo;BRANDING&rdquo;</p>

<p>&mdash; Without &ldquo;Project X&rdquo;
project != &ldquo;Project X&rdquo; and summary  !~ &ldquo;BRANDING&rdquo;</p>

<p>&mdash; Without Old
status not in (DONE,CLOSED) OR updated >= -14d</p>

<p>&mdash; WAITING
summary ~ &lsquo;WAITING&rsquo;</p>

<p>&mdash; Without WAITING
summary !~ &lsquo;WAITING&rsquo;
```</p>

<h4>Things that did not change</h4>

<p>I still use a WIP limit on the In Progress column, display the Epic in on the cards and special use custom color coding for tasks :</p>

<p>```sql
&mdash; Tasks with an imminent due date become red
duedate &lt;= 1d or priority = &ldquo;1-Very High&rdquo;</p>

<p>&mdash; Tasks with a due date are orange
duedate is not EMPTY
```</p>

<h2>The result</h2>

<p>Overall, this is how my board looks like :</p>

<p><a href="../imgs/2017-03-03-my-ultimate-jira-personal-kanban/full-board.jpg"><img src="../imgs/2017-03-03-my-ultimate-jira-personal-kanban/full-board-small.jpg" alt="Full board screen capture" /></a></p>

<p>I guess I&rsquo;m a kind of personal productivity geek &hellip; but I believe it&rsquo;s a skill of utter importance for developers, especially when they get a bit of experience and are not fed ready made tasks to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Grow a Culture Book]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-grow-a-culture-book/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-08T05:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-grow-a-culture-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you read valve&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf">Handbook for new employees</a> ?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-08-how-to-grow-a-culture-book/valve-handbook-for-new-employees.jpg" title="A stack of Valve&rsquo;s Handbook for new employees" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://management30.com">Management 3.0</a> terms, that&rsquo;s a <a href="https://management30.com/practice/value-stories/">culture book</a>. It&rsquo;s a great way to build and crystallize a culture, and it serves as a guide for newcomers, and can later serve as an hiring ad for your team or company.</p>

<p>The good thing about a culture book, is that you don&rsquo;t have to write it in one go. It&rsquo;s a living artifact anyway, so you&rsquo;d better not ! Our current culture book has emerged from a collection of pages in our wiki.</p>

<h2>It started as working agreements</h2>

<p>The first real contributions to our culture book (though we did not know it at the time) was spending some time in retrospectives to define and review our working and coding conventions.</p>

<p>When we started doing retrospectives, we had to discuss, agree and formalize the decisions we made about our way of working. We usually did a &lsquo;review how we work&rsquo; activity at the beginning the retros, spending 10 minutes to make sure we all understood and agreed on our current working conventions. If there was any disagreement or update required, we would discuss them during the retro, and at the end, add, remove or modify items from our agreement page.</p>

<h2>It continued as self-organization workshops</h2>

<p>After a while, we had built up a pretty extensive set of working and coding conventions. The team had already become quite productive, but to keep the momentum in the long run, we needed to increase self-organization. By reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Jurgen-Appelo/e/B00460MCJM/ref=sr_tc_2_0?qid=1470715896&amp;sr=8-2-ent">Management 3.0 books</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Workout-Practices-Improve-Delight-Management-ebook/dp/B00N6REYKQ/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8#navbar">Management Workout</a> (which has been re-edited as <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Managing-Happiness-Games-Practices-Motivate/dp/1119268680/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8">Managing for Happiness</a>) in particular, I found description about how to use a <a href="https://management30.com/practice/delegation-board/">delegation board</a> and <a href="https://management30.com/product/delegation-poker/">delegation pokers</a> to measure and formalize the current delegation level of a team.</p>

<p>We did this, and started a lot of self-organization workshops :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/">Stop feeling like a kid every time you ask a day off</a></li>
<li><a href="/scrum-teams-do-not-need-a-scrum-master/">Scrum Teams Do Not Need a Scrum Master</a></li>
<li><a href="/make-hiring-everyones-business/">Make hiring everyone&rsquo;s business</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">How to deal with the incentive system in an agile team ?</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/">How We Decentralized Our Company&rsquo;s Training Program</a></li>
</ul>


<p>After each of these workshops, we created a wiki page, explaining how we planned to handle the subject in the team.</p>

<h2>The book</h2>

<p>At that point, we had fairly extensive and formal descriptions of our working practices and conventions. By reading this set of pages, someone would get a pretty accurate grasp of our principles and values.</p>

<p>Wondering how we could write our own culture book, I had an &ldquo;Aha !&rdquo; moment and realized that all I had to do was to create a wiki page pointing to all our different agreement pages. This only took 5 minutes.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-08-how-to-grow-a-culture-book/content.jpg" title="The table of content of our culture book" ></p>

<p>At the moment, our culture book serves 3 purposes :</p>

<ul>
<li>documentation for the team members</li>
<li>guide for newcomers</li>
<li>description about how we work for people in the company who might want to move to our team</li>
</ul>


<p>Next step would be to add a dash of design, a few war stories, export it as a PDF, and use it outside to advertise the team and the company.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Lego Office Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-lego-office-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-20T05:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-lego-office-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rome wasn&rsquo;t built in a day, neither will be your Lego Office &hellip; This week is Devoxx in Paris, for the occasion, we decided to stream a <a href="/recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/">Lego office</a> experiment that my team did.</p>

<h2>What are Lego Offices</h2>

<p>I wrote about Lego office in a previous post, as a concept and a set of material that would allow teams to easily configure their workspaces as they wish. At that time, I thought of :</p>

<ul>
<li>laptops</li>
<li>extra monitors</li>
<li>tables and chairs on wheels</li>
<li>movable walls</li>
<li>movable white boards</li>
<li>movable wall screens</li>
<li>a good Wifi</li>
</ul>


<h2>Our experiment</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/empty-meeting-area.jpg" title="Meeting area in the empty office" >
<img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/empty-work-area.jpg" title="Work area in the empty office" ></p>

<p>The last floor of our building in Paris has a nice (really) open space area with rolling tables that we could use. We moved all the team there for one week. As we don&rsquo;t have laptops with Wifi, we simply asked for enough power and network plugs.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/setup-work-area.jpg" title="Setup work area" >
<img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/setup-meeting-area.jpg" title="Setup meeting area" >
<img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/setup-rest-area.jpg" title="Setup rest area" ></p>

<p>The place is large enough to have dedicated rest and meeting space. We managed to create a visio setup using our build monitor. We even had a remote lunch once, which we should repeat more often !</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s missing</h2>

<p>Obviously, this was a quick experiment, nothing like a fully architectured Lego workspace, still it helped us to discover issues and blocking points. It turns out that cables <em>are</em> an issue !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/cables.jpg" title="Cables on the floor" ></p>

<p>After getting some feedback throughout the company, it turns out that some developers would never trade their high end connected desktop workstation for a Wifi laptop. Our C++ build can be pretty CPU and network intensive &hellip; I guess that means that a real Lego office might require one of the following :</p>

<ul>
<li>A technical floor with all the place required to bring any kind of cables to your machine</li>
<li>Powerful servers in a data center to do the grunt work for you</li>
<li>Single cable machines (Apple&rsquo;s USB-C is the only one I can think of right now)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Last minute question</h2>

<p>Thinking of it &hellip; could different remote offices such as your home, or a co-working space be considered as Lego blocks ?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How We Decentralized Our Company's Training Program]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-18T05:31:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Maybe your company too has a development program you can use to track and organize your training path. That&rsquo;s already great ! It is often not perfect though. Sometimes, the initiative in itself can feel like an afterthought. Some other times, the process is completely left to the employee and his manager, with varying results, from great to forced upon everyone.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-18-how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/learning.jpg" title="A &lsquo;learning&rsquo; word cloud" ></p>

<h2>How did we rebuild this program in our team</h2>

<p>As you might remember if you read my <a href="/blog/categories/selforganizing/">previous posts</a>, we started a self organization initiative using a <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/delegation-employee-engagement/">delegation board</a>. When we tried to decentralize <a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">the end of year evaluation</a>, we started discussing the subjects of personal development. We decided to have a dedicated workshop about this subject</p>

<h2>Guiding principles</h2>

<p>In our company, the development program allows a manager to assign specific learning goals to his collaborators, and anyone can also create his own goals to justify going to specific trainings. Starting from that, we agreed that the development program should be used to help anyone in the team to improve skills that are interesting for both the company and the employee. If the employee is interested in something completely unrelated to work, then he should obviously tackle that in his own time. If the company needs its employee to acquire some immediate mandatory skills, then that should be part of the daily job and subject to the end of year evaluation.</p>

<p>The idea is to try to find a win-win combinations, were employees are motivated to work their best at a company that they know helps them to full-fill their long term goals.</p>

<h2>What did we came us with ?</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-18-how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/mentor-mentee.jpg" title="A lion and a lion cub side by side" ></p>

<p>This workshop was quite effective :</p>

<ul>
<li>First of all, everyone is responsible for his own development, it&rsquo;s a chance offered by the company. It cannot be forced unto people.</li>
<li>It is based on volunteer mentorship : everyone should have regular meetings with his mentor to asses his progress on his long term goal, to try to get feedback and ideas about how to move forward. We started by saying that the team leader is the default mentor, but anyone can find another mentor at any moment.</li>
<li>The process starts with the search for a long term goal. Examples are &ldquo;I want to be an agile coach&rdquo;, or &ldquo;I want to be a performance expert&rdquo;</li>
<li>With the help of the mentor if needed, the long term goal should be split in yearly objectives and tracked using <a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/HenrikJanVanderPol/how-to-outperform-anyone-else-introduction-to-okr">OKRs</a></li>
<li>Everyone is free to track his progress has he wishes. Visual tracking makes the discussion with the mentor a lot easier. We have been looking at tools to track OKRs but it was surprisingly difficult to find one that suited our use. Most are enterprisy tools with manager-managee relationships. We just wanted simple personal tracking tools. For my part, I adapted a <a href="https://trello.com/b/MPM4rspd/okrs">Trello</a> board I found on the internet.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>After doing a few months of this, I can say that this has a positive aspect on motivation, people told me that they felt more in control of their destiny. Something else I noted, is that junior developers need help and guidance. They often don&rsquo;t really know what they want to do in a few years, so they really need a mentor to help them find out the what and the how. The other side of this is that a team obviously needs senior developers to act as mentor &hellip; among other things.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to deal with the incentive system in an agile team ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-30T05:10:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For an organization, there&rsquo;s something schizophrenic about valuing team work, wanting agility but sticking to individual objectives and assessments.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-30-how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/schizophrenic-smiley.jpg" title="A schizophrenic :(: smiley" ></p>

<p>As highlighted in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Built-Last-Successful-Visionary-Essentials/dp/0060516402/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1459922545&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=build+to+last">Build To Last</a> genuine company values must permeate all aspects of the organization. Being agile also means putting teamwork first and that is quite incompatible with typical individual management by objectives and bonuses.</p>

<p>This is nothing new, many have already written about the subject</p>

<ul>
<li>Joel Spolsky : <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000070.html">Incentive Pay Considered Harmful</a></li>
<li>Daniel Pink : <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Drive-Surprising-Truth-About-Motivates/dp/1594484805/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1459665370&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=drive+daniel+pink">Drive : The Surprising Truth About What Motivates Us</a></li>
<li>Alfie Kohn : <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Punished-Rewards-Trouble-Incentive-Praise/dp/0618001816/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1459665424&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=punished+by+rewards">Punished by Rewards: The Trouble with Gold Stars, Incentive Plans, A&rsquo;s, Praise, and Other Bribes</a></li>
<li>Jurgen Appelo : <a href="http://noop.nl/2013/01/the-bonus-system.html">The Bonus System</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The problem is you usually don&rsquo;t have the choice ! Whether your team wants to or not, the chances are that your company already has a mandatory individual bonus scheme in place.</p>

<h2>Our delegation initiative</h2>

<p>As you might remember if you read my <a href="/stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/">previous articles</a>, our team decided to move to more self organization. After identifying the end of year evaluation as something that could be further delegated, we embarked on brainstorming sessions about how to do it.</p>

<p>We discussed quite some options during our workshops. Things like :</p>

<ul>
<li>What is the goal of the annual evaluation ?</li>
<li>Should some people have a central role in the process ?</li>
<li>Should we encourage efforts or results ?</li>
<li>Should evaluations be public or private ?</li>
<li>What&rsquo;s at stack at the annual evaluation ?</li>
<li>Should individual learning plans be part of the evaluation ?</li>
</ul>


<h2>What we came up with</h2>

<p>As a guiding principle, we agreed to value efforts rather than results. Sometimes, results are independent of efforts, and through efforts, it is always possible to get the best of any situation, even if the best is not a good result in itself.</p>

<h3>Throughout the year</h3>

<p>We are all sharing the same team objectives :</p>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;the team finishes the prioritized epics&rdquo; : we do regular epics prioritization sessions with our product owner and add the main epics to everyone&rsquo;s objectives</li>
<li>&ldquo;work on the same subject as the whole team&rdquo; : we have an overspecialization matrix that uses correlation to make sure that everyone touches the same parts of the system as the rest of the team</li>
</ul>


<p>Every 2 months, we are doing <a href="/feedback-on-360-degrees-feedback-session/">360° feedback sessions</a>, for everyone to give continuous feedback to others.</p>

<p>Optionally, we setup <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/intrinsic-motivation/kudo-box/">Kudo boxes</a> to give and receive thanks from others.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-30-how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/kudo.jpg" title="A kudo card" ></p>

<h3>At the end of the year</h3>

<p>When the time of the official end of year evaluation comes, we do 360°, 1 to 1 rating on the following topics.</p>

<ul>
<li> commitment &amp; courage (doing not so fun work, find difficult compromises, say the truth, strive for quality work)</li>
<li> helping others (giving a training, providing coaching, help others, do some evangelization)</li>
<li> self improvement (taking feedback into account, improve technical skills, work on soft skills)</li>
<li> team player (build friendly environment, contribute to team improvement, positive attitude, use a non violent communication)</li>
</ul>


<p>Grades are signed, and anyone can ask someone else for a discussion about his grades.</p>

<p>Overall, everyone gets an average grade, which we use to suggest a company grade (below, achieved, exceeded) to the HR system. It then gets homogenized with the rest of the company, but this is then out of our control.</p>

<p>One thing that made this possible is also that after taking a close look at the company grade system, we saw that not so much was at stake &hellip; Provided we make sure everyone has what it takes to do the job, anyone can get an achieved evaluation by doing enough efforts. Getting an exceeded is like a bonus for a particular good year.</p>

<h2>Last word</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m pretty sure we could make this more simple in an environment with more end to end feedback (start-up or pizza teams) but we feel that our current alternative is a lot better than having the manager deciding everything on his own.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
