<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: selforganizing | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/selforganizing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-08-30T06:12:41+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Incremental Software Development Strategies for Large Scale Refactoring #3 : Manage it !]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-3-manage-it/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-23T06:53:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-3-manage-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-1-constant-merciless-refactoring/">My previous posts</a> where about how to find and use small time slots for large scale refactorings. <a href="/incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-2-baby-steps/">Refactoring step by step</a> is a series of slack slots, sub tasks of features and boy scout rule increments. Unfortunately, keeping track of all these is a challenge of its own.</p>

<p>Here is a little story of what can go bad. I used to work in a team which <a href="/refactoring-trick-to-insert-a-wrapper/">had a high &lsquo;refactoring culture&rsquo;.</a> Everyone in the team wanted to apply the kind of practices I mentioned in my previous posts. To make things more tricky, we were <a href="/from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/">working from 2 cities</a>. We had introduced slack time and developers would tackle refactoring at the end of every iteration. As we did not particularly organize or collaborate on slack time, we soon ran into conflicts. People wanted to refactor the same code, maybe in different ways ! After a while we also had too many large scale refactorings going on at the same time. This slowed down progress, increased the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_factor">bus factor</a> and the failure rate. Worst of all, it made it difficult to refocus on a newly discovered but urgent refactoring.</p>

<p>With a bit of organization though, we got things to work. Let&rsquo;s see how we managed it.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-08-08-incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-3-manage-it/manage-it.jpg" alt="Drawing of a calendar entitled &quot;Manage It !&quot;. Collaboration and organization are key to succeed to use incremental software development for large scale refactorings." /></p>

<p>This is the eighth post in a <a href="/blog/categories/large-scale-refactoring-sponsorship-series/">series about how to get sponsorship for large scale refactoring</a>. If you haven&rsquo;t, I encourage you to start from <a href="/how-to-convince-your-business-to-sponsor-a-large-scale-refactoring/">the beginning</a>.</p>

<h2>Manage it with a Design Vision</h2>

<p>To succeed at anything, we need to know where we are going. It&rsquo;s the same for large scale refactorings. We don&rsquo;t need to have all the details of what we want to build. We do need a good enough draft to avoid going in the wrong direction. That&rsquo;s even more true when we work as a team. Without a shared design vision, people will refactor in conflicting directions.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s very important to share the vision with all the team. We can stick high level UML sketches on the walls for example. As <a href="https://twitter.com/kentbeck">Kent Beck</a> suggests, we can also use <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/metaphor.html">metaphores</a> to communicate the design. In <a href="https://vimeo.com/275530146">this talk</a>, <a href="http://www.natpryce.com/">Nat Pryce</a> explains that it&rsquo;s a great way start, but that we will have to drop the metaphore later.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/275530146?title=0&byline=0&portrait=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<div class="image-credits">By <a href="https://vimeo.com/275530146">Nat Pryce - What we talk about when we talk about software</a> from <a href="https://vimeo.com/newcrafts">NEWCRAFTS Conferences</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a></div>


<br>


<p>The idea is not to waste time in a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Design_Up_Front">Big Design Up Front</a>. We just want to draft a vision :</p>

<ul>
<li>We can run a Design level Event Storming (I guess I&rsquo;ll have to blog about this some day)</li>
<li>We can grab a copy of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Gamestorming-Playbook-Innovators-Rulebreakers-Changemakers/dp/0596804172/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1534409953&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=gamestorming">Gamestorming</a> and run another kind of collaborative design game</li>
<li>Or a few team members could work on something the way they prefer</li>
</ul>


<p>Whatever the technique we start with, we&rsquo;ll be able to refine and evolve the vision down the road.</p>

<h2>Manage it with Mikado Graphs</h2>

<p>Remember the &lsquo;<a href="http://mikadomethod.info/">Mikado Method</a>&rsquo; from <a href="/incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-2-baby-steps/">my previous post</a> ? It&rsquo;s a technique to code and deploy large scale refactorings in baby steps. If you had a look at the reference links, you&rsquo;ll might seen mentions of a &lsquo;Mikado Graph&rsquo;. Here is what it looks like :</p>

<p><a href="http://mikadomethod.info/"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-08-08-incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-3-manage-it/mikado-graph.png" alt="Sample Mikado Graph. The Mikado graph is a great tool to manage and collaborate on incremental software development of large scale refactoring." /></a></p>

<div class="image-credits">Sample mikado graph from <a href="http://mikadomethod.info/">http://mikadomethod.info/</a></div>


<br>


<p>As the number of refactoring steps grows, it becomes tricky to keep track of them all. A simple way is to draw them as nodes in a graph, and tackle the work from the leaves. If you are interested, check <a href="/blog/categories/mikado-method/">these posts about the Mikado Method</a>. In my previous team, we became fans of the Mikado Method. We even built a tool to generate mikado graph from <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira">JIRA</a> (our ticket management system) dependencies ! Using colors, we could track where we stood in the refactoring.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-08-08-incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-3-manage-it/generated-mikado-graph.jpg" alt="Sample Mikado Graph generated by our tool. Automating around Mikado graphs is of great help for large scale refactoring." /></p>

<p>The key advantage of mikado graphs is that we can stick them on the wall. This enables all the team to know where we stand in a refactoring. This way, team members can collaborate during their slack. It can also make the boy scout rule more effective. When a developer happens to touch a file that appears in the graph, he or she can move it further in the good direction.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 A key benefit of mikado graphs is that we can stick them on the wall for everyone to know where we stand in a refactoring.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Manage it with Metrics</h2>

<p>I mentioned coding conventions and a clear <a href="https://www.agilealliance.org/glossary/definition-of-done/">Definition of Done</a> in <a href="/incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-1-constant-merciless-refactoring/">a previous post</a>.  Having code quality constraints is the compass of constant merciless refactoring. To make this actionable and real, we should take the time to setup an automatic metrics system. For example :</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/Env47tQewIA?t=2685"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-08-08-incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-3-manage-it/tech-debt-trap.jpg" alt="Doc Norton's talk about &quot;The Technical Debt trap&quot;. His metrics are very useful to manage large scale refactoring." /></a></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Env47tQewIA">Doc Norton suggests</a> to track maintainability, coverage, complexity and coupling over time.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://www.agilealliance.org/the-agile-alliance-debt-analysis-model/">A2DAM model</a> suggests using specific rules to create Definition of Done constraints</li>
</ul>


<p>Putting this in place will help everyone in the team to know if she or he should do more or less refactoring. The first benefit is that it prevents under and over engineering on new code. The second benefit is progress validation through metrics changes as we refactor.</p>

<p><a href="https://codeclimate.com/github/philou/planning-poker"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2018-08-08-incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-3-manage-it/code-climate-dashboard.jpg" alt="Sample metrics dashboard. Out of the box, Code Climate supports 3 out of the 4 metrics suggested by Doc Norton. This can be really helpful to manage incremental software development." /></a></p>

<h2>Manage it with a bit of Planning</h2>

<p>Granted, planning is not the most fun part of our job. It can save us a ton of work though. <a href="https://code.joejag.com/2018/lego-workstream-visualisation.html">Joe Wright explains</a> how they doubled their productivity by spending more time planning. If we want to make a good job of incremental refactoring, we&rsquo;ll need to spend enough time preparing it. Important questions are :</p>

<ul>
<li>What are the most important refactorings to work on ?</li>
<li>How many refactorings should we tackle at the same time ?</li>
<li>Are we making good progress on our refactorings ?</li>
<li>Why is this refactoring not yielding any visible results through our metrics system ?</li>
<li>Are there any news that should change our plans ?</li>
<li>Are we doing enough refactoring to keep things under control ?</li>
<li>What are the next steps in these refactorings ?</li>
<li>etc</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m not talking about a big 6 month planning but rather regular short planning sessions. In <a href="https://www.scrum.org/">Scrum</a> this kind of planning happens every sprint. To make plannings more visual, engaging and fun, we might us something like <a href="https://jpattonassociates.com/user-story-mapping/">Story Mapping</a>. (I guess I should blog about this someday.)</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Keeping a Work In Progress limit on refactorings is essential.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Manage it through Time-Boxing</h2>

<p>One last advice before I&rsquo;m done. We must be very careful to time-box our work on refactoring increments. It&rsquo;s all too easy, to get caught up in a refactoring during the slack at the end of the iteration. If we let the refactoring spill on features we risk loosing the business people&rsquo;s trust.</p>

<p>Here again, using extra small baby steps helps to pause the refactoring. Another way is to do <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban_(development">Kanban</a>) style slack. Replace end of sprint slack by a fixed number of people slacking all the time. But I&rsquo;ll come back to this in more details in a future post.</p>

<h2>Next post</h2>

<p>Using this set of practices my team was able to deliver large scale refactorings in small steps. That said, some refactorings are very difficult to technically deliver incrementally. Fortunately, people have come up with patterns like the Strangler and the Bubble Context to cope with this. That&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;ll go over in the <a href="/incremental-software-development-strategies-for-large-scale-refactoring-number-4-a-pattern-language/">next post</a>.</p>

<p>This was the eighth post in <a href="/blog/categories/large-scale-refactoring-sponsorship-series/">a series about how to get sponsorship for large scale refactoring</a>. I&rsquo;ve already been through why it&rsquo;s so difficult to get sponsorship for a refactoring. Why a badass developer attitude is important ? How to deliver refactorings steps by steps ? If you haven&rsquo;t start by <a href="/how-to-convince-your-business-to-sponsor-a-large-scale-refactoring/">the beginning</a> !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Grow a Culture Book]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-grow-a-culture-book/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-08T05:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-grow-a-culture-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you read valve&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf">Handbook for new employees</a> ?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-08-08-how-to-grow-a-culture-book/valve-handbook-for-new-employees.jpg" alt="A stack of Valve's Handbook for new employees" /></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://management30.com">Management 3.0</a> terms, that&rsquo;s a <a href="https://management30.com/practice/value-stories/">culture book</a>. It&rsquo;s a great way to build and crystallize a culture, and it serves as a guide for newcomers, and can later serve as an hiring ad for your team or company.</p>

<p>The good thing about a culture book, is that you don&rsquo;t have to write it in one go. It&rsquo;s a living artifact anyway, so you&rsquo;d better not ! Our current culture book has emerged from a collection of pages in our wiki.</p>

<h2>It started as working agreements</h2>

<p>The first real contributions to our culture book (though we did not know it at the time) was spending some time in retrospectives to define and review our working and coding conventions.</p>

<p>When we started doing retrospectives, we had to discuss, agree and formalize the decisions we made about our way of working. We usually did a &lsquo;review how we work&rsquo; activity at the beginning the retros, spending 10 minutes to make sure we all understood and agreed on our current working conventions. If there was any disagreement or update required, we would discuss them during the retro, and at the end, add, remove or modify items from our agreement page.</p>

<h2>It continued as self-organization workshops</h2>

<p>After a while, we had built up a pretty extensive set of working and coding conventions. The team had already become quite productive, but to keep the momentum in the long run, we needed to increase self-organization. By reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Jurgen-Appelo/e/B00460MCJM/ref=sr_tc_2_0?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;qid=1470715896&amp;sr=8-2-ent">Management 3.0 books</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Workout-Practices-Improve-Delight-Management-ebook/dp/B00N6REYKQ/ref=asap_bc?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8#navbar">Management Workout</a> (which has been re-edited as <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Managing-Happiness-Games-Practices-Motivate/dp/1119268680/ref=asap_bc?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8">Managing for Happiness</a>) in particular, I found description about how to use a <a href="https://management30.com/practice/delegation-board/">delegation board</a> and <a href="https://management30.com/product/delegation-poker/">delegation pokers</a> to measure and formalize the current delegation level of a team.</p>

<p>We did this, and started a lot of self-organization workshops :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/">Stop feeling like a kid every time you ask a day off</a></li>
<li><a href="/scrum-teams-do-not-need-a-scrum-master/">Scrum Teams Do Not Need a Scrum Master</a></li>
<li><a href="/make-hiring-everyones-business/">Make hiring everyone&rsquo;s business</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">How to deal with the incentive system in an agile team ?</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/">How We Decentralized Our Company&rsquo;s Training Program</a></li>
</ul>


<p>After each of these workshops, we created a wiki page, explaining how we planned to handle the subject in the team.</p>

<h2>The book</h2>

<p>At that point, we had fairly extensive and formal descriptions of our working practices and conventions. By reading this set of pages, someone would get a pretty accurate grasp of our principles and values.</p>

<p>Wondering how we could write our own culture book, I had an &ldquo;Aha !&rdquo; moment and realized that all I had to do was to create a wiki page pointing to all our different agreement pages. This only took 5 minutes.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-08-08-how-to-grow-a-culture-book/content.jpg" alt="The table of content of our culture book" /></p>

<p>At the moment, our culture book serves 3 purposes :</p>

<ul>
<li>documentation for the team members</li>
<li>guide for newcomers</li>
<li>description about how we work for people in the company who might want to move to our team</li>
</ul>


<p>Next step would be to add a dash of design, a few war stories, export it as a PDF, and use it outside to advertise the team and the company.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Lego Office Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-lego-office-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-20T05:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/a-lego-office-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rome wasn&rsquo;t built in a day, neither will be your Lego Office &hellip; This week is Devoxx in Paris, for the occasion, we decided to stream a <a href="/recipes-for-an-agile-workspace/">Lego office</a> experiment that my team did.</p>

<h2>What are Lego Offices</h2>

<p>I wrote about Lego office in a previous post, as a concept and a set of material that would allow teams to easily configure their workspaces as they wish. At that time, I thought of :</p>

<ul>
<li>laptops</li>
<li>extra monitors</li>
<li>tables and chairs on wheels</li>
<li>movable walls</li>
<li>movable white boards</li>
<li>movable wall screens</li>
<li>a good Wifi</li>
</ul>


<h2>Our experiment</h2>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/empty-meeting-area.jpg" alt="Meeting area in the empty office" />
<img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/empty-work-area.jpg" alt="Work area in the empty office" /></p>

<p>The last floor of our building in Paris has a nice (really) open space area with rolling tables that we could use. We moved all the team there for one week. As we don&rsquo;t have laptops with Wifi, we simply asked for enough power and network plugs.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/setup-work-area.jpg" alt="Setup work area" />
<img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/setup-meeting-area.jpg" alt="Setup meeting area" />
<img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/setup-rest-area.jpg" alt="Setup rest area" /></p>

<p>The place is large enough to have dedicated rest and meeting space. We managed to create a visio setup using our build monitor. We even had a remote lunch once, which we should repeat more often !</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s missing</h2>

<p>Obviously, this was a quick experiment, nothing like a fully architectured Lego workspace, still it helped us to discover issues and blocking points. It turns out that cables <em>are</em> an issue !</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-04-20-a-lego-office-experiment/cables.jpg" alt="Cables on the floor" /></p>

<p>After getting some feedback throughout the company, it turns out that some developers would never trade their high end connected desktop workstation for a Wifi laptop. Our C++ build can be pretty CPU and network intensive &hellip; I guess that means that a real Lego office might require one of the following :</p>

<ul>
<li>A technical floor with all the place required to bring any kind of cables to your machine</li>
<li>Powerful servers in a data center to do the grunt work for you</li>
<li>Single cable machines (Apple&rsquo;s USB-C is the only one I can think of right now)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Last minute question</h2>

<p>Thinking of it &hellip; could different remote offices such as your home, or a co-working space be considered as Lego blocks ?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How We Decentralized Our Company's Training Program]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-18T05:31:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Maybe your company too has a development program you can use to track and organize your training path. That&rsquo;s already great ! It is often not perfect though. Sometimes, the initiative in itself can feel like an afterthought. Some other times, the process is completely left to the employee and his manager, with varying results, from great to forced upon everyone.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-04-18-how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/learning.jpg" alt="A 'learning' word cloud" /></p>

<h2>How did we rebuild this program in our team</h2>

<p>As you might remember if you read my <a href="/blog/categories/selforganizing/">previous posts</a>, we started a self organization initiative using a <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/delegation-employee-engagement/">delegation board</a>. When we tried to decentralize <a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">the end of year evaluation</a>, we started discussing the subjects of personal development. We decided to have a dedicated workshop about this subject</p>

<h2>Guiding principles</h2>

<p>In our company, the development program allows a manager to assign specific learning goals to his collaborators, and anyone can also create his own goals to justify going to specific trainings. Starting from that, we agreed that the development program should be used to help anyone in the team to improve skills that are interesting for both the company and the employee. If the employee is interested in something completely unrelated to work, then he should obviously tackle that in his own time. If the company needs its employee to acquire some immediate mandatory skills, then that should be part of the daily job and subject to the end of year evaluation.</p>

<p>The idea is to try to find a win-win combinations, were employees are motivated to work their best at a company that they know helps them to full-fill their long term goals.</p>

<h2>What did we came us with ?</h2>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-04-18-how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/mentor-mentee.jpg" alt="A lion and a lion cub side by side" /></p>

<p>This workshop was quite effective :</p>

<ul>
<li>First of all, everyone is responsible for his own development, it&rsquo;s a chance offered by the company. It cannot be forced unto people.</li>
<li>It is based on volunteer mentorship : everyone should have regular meetings with his mentor to asses his progress on his long term goal, to try to get feedback and ideas about how to move forward. We started by saying that the team leader is the default mentor, but anyone can find another mentor at any moment.</li>
<li>The process starts with the search for a long term goal. Examples are &ldquo;I want to be an agile coach&rdquo;, or &ldquo;I want to be a performance expert&rdquo;</li>
<li>With the help of the mentor if needed, the long term goal should be split in yearly objectives and tracked using <a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/HenrikJanVanderPol/how-to-outperform-anyone-else-introduction-to-okr">OKRs</a></li>
<li>Everyone is free to track his progress has he wishes. Visual tracking makes the discussion with the mentor a lot easier. We have been looking at tools to track OKRs but it was surprisingly difficult to find one that suited our use. Most are enterprisy tools with manager-managee relationships. We just wanted simple personal tracking tools. For my part, I adapted a <a href="https://trello.com/b/MPM4rspd/okrs">Trello</a> board I found on the internet.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>After doing a few months of this, I can say that this has a positive aspect on motivation, people told me that they felt more in control of their destiny. Something else I noted, is that junior developers need help and guidance. They often don&rsquo;t really know what they want to do in a few years, so they really need a mentor to help them find out the what and the how. The other side of this is that a team obviously needs senior developers to act as mentor &hellip; among other things.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to deal with the incentive system in an agile team ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-30T05:10:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For an organization, there&rsquo;s something schizophrenic about valuing team work, wanting agility but sticking to individual objectives and assessments.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-03-30-how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/schizophrenic-smiley.jpg" alt="A schizophrenic :(: smiley" /></p>

<p>As highlighted in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Built-Last-Successful-Visionary-Essentials/dp/0060516402/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1459922545&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=build+to+last">Build To Last</a> genuine company values must permeate all aspects of the organization. Being agile also means putting teamwork first and that is quite incompatible with typical individual management by objectives and bonuses.</p>

<p>This is nothing new, many have already written about the subject</p>

<ul>
<li>Joel Spolsky : <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000070.html">Incentive Pay Considered Harmful</a></li>
<li>Daniel Pink : <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Drive-Surprising-Truth-About-Motivates/dp/1594484805/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1459665370&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=drive+daniel+pink">Drive : The Surprising Truth About What Motivates Us</a></li>
<li>Alfie Kohn : <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Punished-Rewards-Trouble-Incentive-Praise/dp/0618001816/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1459665424&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=punished+by+rewards">Punished by Rewards: The Trouble with Gold Stars, Incentive Plans, A&rsquo;s, Praise, and Other Bribes</a></li>
<li>Jurgen Appelo : <a href="http://noop.nl/2013/01/the-bonus-system.html">The Bonus System</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The problem is you usually don&rsquo;t have the choice ! Whether your team wants to or not, the chances are that your company already has a mandatory individual bonus scheme in place.</p>

<h2>Our delegation initiative</h2>

<p>As you might remember if you read my <a href="/stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/">previous articles</a>, our team decided to move to more self organization. After identifying the end of year evaluation as something that could be further delegated, we embarked on brainstorming sessions about how to do it.</p>

<p>We discussed quite some options during our workshops. Things like :</p>

<ul>
<li>What is the goal of the annual evaluation ?</li>
<li>Should some people have a central role in the process ?</li>
<li>Should we encourage efforts or results ?</li>
<li>Should evaluations be public or private ?</li>
<li>What&rsquo;s at stack at the annual evaluation ?</li>
<li>Should individual learning plans be part of the evaluation ?</li>
</ul>


<h2>What we came up with</h2>

<p>As a guiding principle, we agreed to value efforts rather than results. Sometimes, results are independent of efforts, and through efforts, it is always possible to get the best of any situation, even if the best is not a good result in itself.</p>

<h3>Throughout the year</h3>

<p>We are all sharing the same team objectives :</p>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;the team finishes the prioritized epics&rdquo; : we do regular epics prioritization sessions with our product owner and add the main epics to everyone&rsquo;s objectives</li>
<li>&ldquo;work on the same subject as the whole team&rdquo; : we have an overspecialization matrix that uses correlation to make sure that everyone touches the same parts of the system as the rest of the team</li>
</ul>


<p>Every 2 months, we are doing <a href="/feedback-on-360-degrees-feedback-session/">360° feedback sessions</a>, for everyone to give continuous feedback to others.</p>

<p>Optionally, we setup <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/intrinsic-motivation/kudo-box/">Kudo boxes</a> to give and receive thanks from others.</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-03-30-how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/kudo.jpg" alt="A kudo card" /></p>

<h3>At the end of the year</h3>

<p>When the time of the official end of year evaluation comes, we do 360°, 1 to 1 rating on the following topics.</p>

<ul>
<li> commitment &amp; courage (doing not so fun work, find difficult compromises, say the truth, strive for quality work)</li>
<li> helping others (giving a training, providing coaching, help others, do some evangelization)</li>
<li> self improvement (taking feedback into account, improve technical skills, work on soft skills)</li>
<li> team player (build friendly environment, contribute to team improvement, positive attitude, use a non violent communication)</li>
</ul>


<p>Grades are signed, and anyone can ask someone else for a discussion about his grades.</p>

<p>Overall, everyone gets an average grade, which we use to suggest a company grade (below, achieved, exceeded) to the HR system. It then gets homogenized with the rest of the company, but this is then out of our control.</p>

<p>One thing that made this possible is also that after taking a close look at the company grade system, we saw that not so much was at stake &hellip; Provided we make sure everyone has what it takes to do the job, anyone can get an achieved evaluation by doing enough efforts. Getting an exceeded is like a bonus for a particular good year.</p>

<h2>Last word</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m pretty sure we could make this more simple in an environment with more end to end feedback (start-up or pizza teams) but we feel that our current alternative is a lot better than having the manager deciding everything on his own.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
