<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: large scale | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/large-scale/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-18T06:04:48+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Agile transformations usually don't work - part 2 - The problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-2-the-problem/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-18T09:24:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-2-the-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second post in a <a href="/blog/categories/agile-transformations-fail-series/">series about making large organizations more agile</a>. I encourage you to <a href="/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-1-the-situation/">start with the beginning</a>.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s summarize the previous post. I illustrated the typical disappointment with large scale &ldquo;Agile&rdquo; transformations. At best they bring a small short term productivity improvement. At worst, they turn into micro-management.</p>

<h2>Why doesn&rsquo;t it work ?</h2>

<p>An organization is agile if it is able to respond and take advantage of changes fast. An organization where decisions need to go up and down the ladder will be slow. To thrive in this complex world, everyone needs to be able to take faster and bigger decisions. To do so, people need the good data, but also the right to fail, and the chance to learn new ways of working.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2018-01-09-why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-2-the-problem/decision-making.jpg" alt="A sign post with 2 directions : a convoluted 'centralized decision making' road, and a simpler 'agile decision making' road" /></p>

<p>People with the right authority could make data available fast enough. Learning new habits and convincing every one of their right to fail takes time though.</p>

<h2>A safe environment</h2>

<p>In &ldquo;Turn the shop around&rdquo; Navy captain David Marquet explains how he empowered his crew. They would take decisions and inform him with &ldquo;I intend to &hellip;&rdquo;. Doing that, he also took on him the responsibility of his subordinates errors !</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Turn-Ship-Around-Turning-Followers/dp/1591846404"><img src="../imgs/2018-01-09-why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-2-the-problem/turn-the-ship-around.jpg" alt="Cover of the book &quot;Turn the ship around&quot;" /></a></p>

<p>There are always people who put the organization&rsquo;s interests before theirs. They will try new experiments, even if could backfire in their faces, because it&rsquo;s the right thing to do. Unfortunately, these people are pretty rare. The vast majority will not try things that would get them troubles. They need a safe environment to unleash autonomy.</p>

<p>The typical adoption technique is to &ldquo;fake it until you make it&rdquo;. Apply the practices until the principles and values soak in everyone&rsquo;s mind. There&rsquo;s a catch though ! People need great models. People buy-in values, not actions. Think of Apple and other technology brands. People buy Apple hardware because they &ldquo;Think Different&rdquo; not for the products ! (Though I admit I love their products too :&ndash;))</p>

<p>Although people buy-in values, they measure them through actions. Leaders need to walk their talk for people to trust them.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 People buy-in values, but they measure them through actions.</p></blockquote>

<p>Very often, leaders stick to actions that communicate that it is <em>not ok</em> to fail. Like compensation by objectives for example. Or highlighting the <a href="https://www.scrum.org/resources/commitment-vs-forecast-subtle-important-change-scrum">commitment</a> of sprints. Praising overwork is another one !</p>

<h2>Place to learn</h2>

<p>Real learning comes from experimentation.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 “Never help a child with a task at which he feels he can succeed.” Maria Montessori</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Montessori"><img src="../imgs/2018-01-09-why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-2-the-problem/Maria_Montessori.jpg" alt="Photograph of educator Maria Montessori" /></a></p>

<p>This is still true for adults at work. Every time management pushes top-down incentives to speed up change, general understanding suffers. There is a limit to what an organization can withstand before it falls prey to cargo cult.</p>

<p>Leaders must provide a safe environment. They must also provide the conditions for the teams to learn and improve their unique way of working.</p>

<p>Too often, leaders are in a hurry. &ldquo;Why should we waste our time rediscovering what others have already understood ? Let&rsquo;s apply Scrum (or SAFe or LeSS) !&rdquo;</p>

<p>Did you ever learn something by copying the results of others ?</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at <a href="http://www.scaledagileframework.com/">SAFe</a> for example. It&rsquo;s a collection of proven best practices. That&rsquo;s only half of the story though. What&rsquo;s not clear is how a practice is proven to work ? By definition, a team had success with it before adding it to SAFe. It can only be the result of experimentation and learning, as it was not yet part of SAFe !</p>

<h2>In the end</h2>

<p>Many leaders embark their organization in an Agile transformation for some business benefits. Unfortunately, people often perceive that &ldquo;It&rsquo;s just the latest way to squeeze a bit more out of us all !&rdquo;.</p>

<p>It does not have to be that way. What if they followed massive decentralization of power. What if they made more data available ? What if they adapted the compensation scheme to encourage risk taking. What if they gave authority to their teams to experiment and learn from their own problems. Would people still feel it&rsquo;s just another re-org ? As a reference, see how <a href="https://www.solidarity-us.org/leanproduction">unions have been fighting lean manufacturing for decades</a>.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s what we&rsquo;ll look into the next posts. This was part 2 of a <a href="/blog/categories/agile-transformations-fail-series/">series of posts on making large organizations more agile</a>. Further posts will propose what to do. <a href="https://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=PhilippeBourgau&amp;loc=en_US">Subscribe</a> to be notified as soon as next post is ready.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Agile transformations usually don't work - part 1 - The situation]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-1-the-situation/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-11T06:35:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-1-the-situation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Goose_That_Laid_the_Golden_Eggs">Aesop&rsquo;s famous tale</a>, a farmer kills his goose that lays a golden egg every day to get all the eggs at once. He finds no eggs, lost his goose, and remains poor ever after.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve seen the same pattern happen many times in the software industry. A team decides to become more agile. After a few years of continuous improvement, it shows largely above average performances. Managers start to notice and ask how the team got there, to replicate this success. Unfortunately, they don&rsquo;t want to wait a few years for the other teams to find their own way. As a result, an &ldquo;Agile&rdquo; process is copy printed to all teams. Follows only ephemeral improvement, at the same time that the initial team gets drowned in a company &ldquo;Scaled Agile&rdquo; initiative &hellip;</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2018-01-09-why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-1-the-situation/lets-all-do-this-agile-thing.jpg" alt="Drawing of a street tag 'Let's all do this Agile thing !&quot;" /></p>

<h2>Examples</h2>

<p>In the 60&rsquo;s, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Toyota">Toyota</a> was innovating new ways to build cars. Other car manufacturers used to visit the Toyota plants to understand how they did it. Toyota was welcoming them with open arms ! (You can still <a href="http://www.visittoyotaky.com/">visit Toyota plants</a> today) Fortunately for Toyota, none of the visitors managed to copy their results.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Competitors managed to copy Toyota&rsquo;s practices, but not their results !</p></blockquote>

<p>Let&rsquo;s think of other agile companies like Google, Apple or Spotify. Did they copy an existing Agile framework or recipe ? No, they rather learned to embrace change in their own way. The HP LaserJet team did not become more agile by sticking to best practices either, they also did it their own way.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Practical-Approach-Large-Scale-Agile-Development/dp/0321821726/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1515476483&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=hp+large+scale+agile"><img src="../imgs/2018-01-09-why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-1-the-situation/hp-large-scale-agile-dev.jpg" alt="The cover of &quot;A Practical Approach to Large-Scale Agile Development. How HP Transformed LaserJet FutureSmart Firmware&quot;" /></a></p>

<p>Thinking about it, I never read a single story of how a team succeeded by sticking to method X, Y or Z.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s just not possible to be agile by strict adherence to a method. Unfortunately, that&rsquo;s what most companies do. Have a look at the job posts, everyone is looking for agile devs, but do these companies look agile once you are in ?</p>

<h2>What are the actual results ?</h2>

<p>With a move to &ldquo;Agile&rdquo;, management usually envisions some of the following benefits :</p>

<ul>
<li>better quality</li>
<li>increased productivity through waste reduction</li>
<li>more innovation</li>
</ul>


<p>People who want these changes fast don&rsquo;t understand what they are doing. If they were, they would not expect this to be fast. It&rsquo;s all too easy to see &ldquo;Agile&rdquo; as a method, or a process.</p>

<p>Following the traditional <a href="http://www.reinventingorganizations.com/">&ldquo;machine&rdquo; organization metaphor</a>, processes are to be applied ! Deploying the new &ldquo;Agile&rdquo; process, leaves little room for self-organization and empowerment. People throughout the organization perceive it as yet another reorganization. People still feel like cogs in the machine. Cogs don&rsquo;t show a lot of autonomy and motivation ! That&rsquo;s when the vicious circle kicks in. To fix the lack of drive, management adds more top-down process !</p>

<p>Long story short, these transformations bring very little improvements. At the beginning, when everyone is keeping a close look at the process, things will go a bit better. A few month later, things will get back to where they were.</p>

<blockquote><p><iframe src="http://philippe.bourgau.net//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/JAoAahDozJKWD5?startSlide=13" width="595" height="485" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe> <div style="margin-bottom:5px"> <strong> <a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net//www.slideshare.net/ThoughtWorks/lean-enterprise-how-to-innovate-at-scale" title="Lean Enterprise - Enabling Innovative Culture" target="_blank">Lean Enterprise &ndash; Enabling Innovative Culture</a> </strong> de <strong><a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net//www.slideshare.net/ThoughtWorks" target="_blank">ThoughtWorks</a></strong> </div></p></blockquote>

<p>A specific danger of &ldquo;Agile&rdquo; is that it can serve micro-management. Short iterations, code reviews and other feedback practices puts everyone under the radar. This makes decision makers feel more in control, at the cost of motivation and innovation. As an example, check <a href="http://sceptical-meerkat.blogspot.fr/2016/12/pair-programming-whats-in-it-for-me.html">this post</a> from a pair programming sceptic.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 &ldquo;Agile&rdquo; can easily slip into micro-management</p></blockquote>

<h2>Next Week&rsquo;s post</h2>

<p>This was part 1 of a <a href="/blog/categories/agile-transformations-fail-series/">series of posts on making large organizations more agile</a>. <a href="/why-agile-transformations-usually-dont-work-part-2-the-problem/">Next post</a> will dig into why the traditional approach described above does not work. Further posts will propose what to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
