<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: java | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/java/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-08-20T19:49:59+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3 More Great Talks From JavaOne 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/3-more-great-talks-from-javaone-2016/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-14T04:05:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/3-more-great-talks-from-javaone-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the top <a href="/top-5-talks-i-attented-at-java-one-2016-part-1/">5 talks I attended at JavaOne</a> here are more !</p>

<h2>Managing Open Source Contributions in Large Organizations</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jamesward.com/presos">James Ward</a></p>

<p>This talk was very interesting for companies or organizations that want to use Open Source in some way without ignoring the risks.</p>

<p>After an introduction listing the benefits of contributing to open source, James explained the associated risks :</p>

<ul>
<li>Security (evil contributions or information leaks)</li>
<li>Quality (bad contributions, increased maintenance or showing a bad image)</li>
<li>Legal (responsibility in case of patent infringing contribution, ownership of a contribution, licenses)</li>
</ul>


<p>He then explained that there are 3 ways to deal with the issue :</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Strategy </th>
<th> Description </th>
<th> Pros </th>
<th> Cons </th>
<th> Popularity </th>
<th> Examples </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Do nothing </td>
<td> Devs just contribute without saying it </td>
<td> Easy, Gets it done </td>
<td> Need to stay under the radar, Risks for all parties are ignores </td>
<td> +++++ </td>
<td> Most open source code on <a href="https://github.com">Github</a> is shared in this manner |</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Join a foundation </td>
<td> Joining an existing open source foundation, with a framework </td>
<td> Everything out of the box (infra, governance), builds trust </td>
<td> Rules can be heavy, Ownership is given to the foundation </td>
<td> +++ </td>
<td> <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/">Linkedin</a> put <a href="https://kafka.apache.org/">Kafka</a> in the <a href="https://www.apache.org/">Apache Foundation</a> |</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Build tools </td>
<td> Use your own tools to mitigate the main risks associated with the &lsquo;Do nothing&rsquo; strategy </td>
<td> Built on top of Github, Keep control, Keeps things easy </td>
<td> Need to develop, test and operate the tools </td>
<td> + </td>
<td> Demo of a tool plugged into Github to enforce a contributor license agreement for anyone pushing a pull request |</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-10-14-3-more-great-talks-from-javaone-2016/CLA.jpg"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-10-14-3-more-great-talks-from-javaone-2016/CLA-small.jpg" alt="Slide with a Github capture for Contributor License Agreement" /></a></p>

<p>The &lsquo;build tools&rsquo; strategy looks promising, even if it is not yet widely used !</p>

<p>Here are <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X71HrW6vC_0">the talk</a> and <a href="http://presos.jamesward.com/managing_open_source_contributions_in_large_orgs/index.html#/">the slides</a> on the authors website.</p>

<h2>Java Performance Analysis in Linux with Flame Graphs</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.brendangregg.com/">Brendan Gregg</a></p>

<p>This is what a flame graph looks like :</p>

<p><a href="http://www.brendangregg.com/FlameGraphs/cpu-mixedmode-vertx.svg"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-10-14-3-more-great-talks-from-javaone-2016/flamegraph.png" alt="An example of a Java flame graph" /></a></p>

<p>Technically, it&rsquo;s just an SVG with some Javascript. It shows the performance big picture. It aggregates data from Linux and JVM profilers. Vertically, you can see the call stacks in your system. The larger a block, the more time is taken inside a function (or in a sub call). The top border is where the CPU time is actually taken. If you want to speed up your system, speed up the wider zones at the top of the graph.</p>

<p>At <a href="https://www.netflix.com">Netflix</a>, the speaker is a performance engineer, and his job is to build tools to help other teams discover performance issues. This is how they use Flame Graphs :</p>

<ul>
<li>Compare 2 flame graphs at different times to see what changed</li>
<li>Do a <a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/CanaryRelease.html">canary release</a> and compare the new flame graph before finishing the deployment</li>
<li>Taking continuous flame graphs on running services helps identify JVM behavior like JIT or GC</li>
<li>They use different color themes to highlight different things</li>
<li>They also use them to identify CPU cache misses</li>
</ul>


<p>By the way, I also thought this was a great example of using an innovative visualization to manage tons of data.</p>

<p>I could find neither the video nor the slides of the talk, but I managed to find a lot of <a href="https://www.google.fr/search?safe=active&amp;client=ubuntu&amp;espv=2&amp;biw=1600&amp;bih=810&amp;tbm=vid&amp;q=Flame+Graphs&amp;oq=Flame+Graphs&amp;gs_l=serp.3...1396.1396.0.1616.1.1.0.0.0.0.59.59.1.1.0....0...1c.1.64.serp..0.0.0.z-3ygDHx4-Q">others talks about Flame Graphs</a>, as well as extra material on <a href="http://www.brendangregg.com/flamegraphs.html">the speaker&rsquo;s homepage</a>.</p>

<h2>Increasing Code Quality with Gamification</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/alex90_ch">Alexander Chatzizacharias</a></p>

<p>You might be wondering why we should care about gamification ?</p>

<ul>
<li>Worldwide 11.2 billion hours are spent playing every week !</li>
<li>People love to play because it makes them feel awesome</li>
<li>Games are good teachers</li>
<li>At work we are the ones who need to make others successful</li>
<li>But only 32% of workers are engaged in their work !</li>
</ul>


<p>Games rely on 4 main dynamics :</p>

<ul>
<li>Competition (be very careful of closed economics which can be very bad for teams)</li>
<li>Peer pressure (Public stats push teams and individual to conform to the norm)</li>
<li>Progression (regular recognition of new skills is motivating)</li>
<li>Rewards (Badges, Level ups, Monkey Money, real money &hellip;)</li>
</ul>


<p>He went on to demonstrate two games that are based on Jenkins and Sonar that aim at better code quality :</p>

<ul>
<li>One mobile app developed during a 24h Hackathon at CGI which might be open sourced at some point</li>
<li>Another one called &lsquo;Dev Cube&rsquo; created at an university, where you get to decorate you virtual cubicle</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hfT2_HxOQdk"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-10-14-3-more-great-talks-from-javaone-2016/quincy-adams.jpg" alt="The speaker demoing his code quality game" /></a></p>

<p>At the end of the talk, he gave the following recommendations :</p>

<ul>
<li>Understand the needs of all to respond to everyone&rsquo;s personal goals</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t assign things to do, that&rsquo;s not fun, give rewards instead</li>
<li>Keep managers out of the picture</li>
<li>To keep it going, you need regular improvements, special events and new rules</li>
<li>KISS !</li>
</ul>


<p>Playing at work might not be unproductive in the end !</p>

<p>The same <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hfT2_HxOQdk">talk given at NLJug</a>, unfortunately, it&rsquo;s in Dutch. English slides are <a href="https://static.rainfocus.com/oracle/oow16/sess/14625567983370011wPS/ppt/increasing%20code%20quality%20with%20gamification.pdf">here</a> though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Top 5 talks I attended at JavaOne 2016 (Part 2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/top-5-talks-i-attended-at-javaone-2016-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-28T20:02:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/top-5-talks-i-attended-at-javaone-2016-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my second post relating the talks I attended at JavaOne 2016. <a href="/top-5-talks-i-attented-at-java-one-2016-part-1/">Here</a> is the beginning of the story. Here we go.</p>

<h2>Euphoria Despite the Despair</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/holly_cummins">Holly Cummins</a></p>

<p>Our jobs aren&rsquo;t always fun &hellip; and that&rsquo;s in fact an issue ! Studies show that people who have fun at work are 31% more productive ! The talk was organized in 3 parts :</p>

<ol>
<li>What is fun ?</li>
<li>How to remove the parts that are not fun ?</li>
<li>How to add even more fun ?</li>
</ol>


<p>She defined what she called the funtinuum, which is that fun is a function of engagement and interaction. Basically, you won&rsquo;t have fun if you are doing nothing, or if no one cares about your work. That aligns well with <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Drive-Surprising-Truth-About-Motivates/dp/1594484805/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1475123675&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=daniel+pink+drive">Daniel Pink&rsquo;s drivers of motivation</a> : Autonomy, Mastery and Purpose.</p>

<p>If something is not fun, it&rsquo;s because it does not require engagement or interaction. It&rsquo;s either boring or no one cares, or both. If that&rsquo;s the case, it&rsquo;s probably some kind of waste in some sense &hellip; Removing un-fun activities would mean removing waste. It&rsquo;s interesting to note how this sounds like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muda_(Japanese_term">lean Muda</a>) ! She gave examples such as :</p>

<ul>
<li>automate stuff</li>
<li>pair programming transforms criticism into collaboration (bonus: it gives excuse to skip meetings)</li>
<li>go <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23NoEstimates">#NoEstimates</a> because estimating is painful and useless</li>
<li>YAGNI defers useless things until they really add value</li>
<li>Organize to skip meetings and other boring stuff</li>
<li>&hellip;</li>
</ul>


<p>Last step is to add fun to the workplace. She warned that adding fun before removing the un-fun stuff would feel fake and would make things worse &hellip;</p>

<iframe src="http://philippe.bourgau.net//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/DMpHQcMebTVGsz?startSlide=148" width="595" height="485" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p>To add fun, she suggested using things like :</p>

<ul>
<li>gamification (there was actually another great talk about gamification)</li>
<li>build a hacking contest instead of a security training</li>
<li>Install a <a href="https://sirenofshame.com/">Siren of Shame</a> for whoever breaks the build</li>
<li>&hellip;</li>
</ul>


<p>Here are <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/HollyCummins/software-developers-guide-to-fun-in-the-workplace-euphoria-despite-the-despair">the slides</a></p>

<h2>Java 9: The Quest for Very Large Heaps</h2>

<p>Bernard Traversat, Antoine Chambille</p>

<p><a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attended-at-javaone-2016-part-2/java-9-gc.jpg"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attended-at-javaone-2016-part-2/java-9-gc-small.jpg" alt="Slide of the memory regions in G1" /></a></p>

<p>This talk might not be of interest for all, but it is for us <a href="http://murex.com">at work</a>. It went through the improvement to come to Java 9&rsquo;s G1 garbage collector. To summarize, to scale to very large heaps, it will split the memory into regions. Objects should be allocated on different regions depending on their specificities, which might help to build NUMA aware applications. Having the heap split up in smaller chunks enables the GC to run in parallel, which can speed up the old generation GC by up to 50 times !</p>

<p><a href="http://www.java9countdown.xyz/">Java 9 is scheduled for march 2017</a></p>

<h2>Agility and Robustness: Clojure + spec</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/stuarthalloway">Stuart Halloway</a></p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t been touching Clojure for a while but I gave the language a try a few years ago. I had heard about Clojure spec but hadn&rsquo;t taken the time to look at it in details. As I understood it all, Spec is like some sort of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Design_by_contract">Design by Contract</a> on steroïds ! Clojure is not statically typed, but you can now assign spec metadata to values. A spec is roughly a predicate. By defining specs for the inputs and outputs of functions, it is possible to verify at runtime that the function is behaving correctly.</p>

<p>As did Bertrand Meyer in the classic <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Object-Oriented-Software-Construction-Book-CD-ROM/dp/0136291554/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1475211259&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=object+oriented+software+construction+meyer">OOSC2</a>, who advised to use contracts during development only, Stuart explained that we should care about developer vs production time instead of compile vs runtime. From this point of view, it is not of great importance whether the compiler or the continuously running test suite finds an issue.</p>

<p>But specs are a lot more than predicates ! They can be used to :</p>

<ul>
<li>enable assertions at runtime</li>
<li>generate documentation</li>
<li>generate test cases</li>
<li>generate precise call logs</li>
<li>get precise error messages</li>
<li>explore a function and see how it can be called</li>
</ul>


<p>He went on to compare the virtues of Clojure spec with static typing (à la Java) and example based testing :</p>

<p><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attended-at-javaone-2016-part-2/clojure-spec.jpg" alt="Slide comparing Clojure spec with example based testing and static typing" /></p>

<p>Although I don&rsquo;t believe that generative testing can ever replace example based testing altogether, it certainly can help.</p>

<p>All in all, the presentation was insanely great and engaging. It made me seriously think of going into Clojure programming again !</p>

<p>Here are <a href="https://t.co/0FBl2l473N">the slides</a> and the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VNTQ-M_uSo8">the same talk at Strangeloop</a></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Overall, JavaOne was great ! If I had the opportunity, I&rsquo;d go back every year ! There was a lot of other great talks I did not write about in these 2 posts, for example :</p>

<ul>
<li>Development Horror Stories was a lot of fun, especially the winning story !</li>
<li>Hacking Hiring was full of good advises</li>
<li>Managing Open Source Contributions in Large Organizations was full of good ideas</li>
<li>Increasing Code Quality with Gamification was very inspiring</li>
</ul>


<h2>Edit 17 October 2016</h2>

<p>I summarized 3 others JavaOne talks <a href="/3-more-great-talks-from-javaone-2016/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Top 5 talks I attended at JavaOne 2016 (Part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/top-5-talks-i-attented-at-java-one-2016-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-28T19:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/top-5-talks-i-attented-at-java-one-2016-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With a few other colleagues, I had the chance to be sent to San Francisco last week to attend the <a href="https://www.oracle.com/javaone/index.html">JavaOne 2016</a> conferences by my <a href="http://www.murex.com">company</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/exhibition-hall.jpg"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/exhibition-hall-small.jpg" alt="Photo of the JavaOne exhibition hall" /></a></p>

<p>Here is super short list of the conferences I attended which I found really interesting</p>

<h2>Preventing errors before they happen</h2>

<p><a href="https://ece.uwaterloo.ca/~wdietl/">Werner Dietl</a> &amp; <a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~mernst/">Michael Ernst</a></p>

<p>Since Java 6, it is possible to pass custom annotation processors to javac. Since Java 8, it is possible to add annotations to types. The guys behind the <a href="http://checkerframework.org">Checker Framework</a> used this to create custom pluggable type systems for your Java programs. These type systems enforce properties on your program, and will emit warnings or errors at compile time otherwise.</p>

<p>Here are a few example :</p>

<ul>
<li>declare <code>@Immutable MyObject myObject</code> to make sure that myObject won&rsquo;t be muted</li>
<li>declare <code>@NonNull MyObject myObject</code> to make sure that myObject is never null</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/type-systems.jpg"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/type-systems-small.jpg" alt="Architecture of the type checker" /></a></p>

<p>Under the hood, the compiler behaves as if <code>@Immutable MyObject</code> and <code>MyObject</code> where completely separate types, and it knows and tracks specific ways of converting between the two. The framework provides a simple API to define your own type systems. They did a live demo showing how to quickly define things like <code>@Regex String</code>, <code>@Encrypted String</code> or <code>@Untainted String</code> (which forbids user input strings to avoid SQL injections).</p>

<p>The talk was really interesting, the framework seems lightweight and to integrate well with the typical tool stack. I definitely will give it a try the next time I have a bit of slack time.</p>

<p>Here are <a href="http://types.cs.washington.edu/checker-framework/2016-javaone/2016-09-19%20CF%20@%20JavaOne.pdf">the slides</a> and a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kb6nz85jbuQ">previous session of the presentation</a></p>

<h2>Keeping Your CI/CD Pipeline as Fast as It Needs to Be</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/abrahammarin?lang=fr">Abraham Marin-Perez</a></p>

<p>Continuous Delivery and Microservices are what you need to do, aren&rsquo;t they ? Well, when actually trying to setup a CI / CD pipeline for all your code, things quickly get complicated pretty fast ! The speaker presented how to deal with this complexity by using metrics from your VCS and build servers to draw an annotated graph of your build pipeline.</p>

<p><a href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/build-pipeline.jpg"><img src="http://philippe.bourgau.net/imgs/2016-09-28-top-5-talks-i-attented-at-javaone-2016-part-1/build-pipeline-small.jpg" alt="Graph of the build pipeline" /></a></p>

<ul>
<li>He used the build time to set the size of every node : the longer, the larger</li>
<li>The color for the change rate : the more often it was built the warmer the color</li>
</ul>


<p>It was then possible to determine other metrics such as :</p>

<ul>
<li>the impact time of every node : build time + build time of all the dependencies</li>
<li>the weighted impact time : impact time * change rate</li>
<li>the overall average impact time : sum of all the weighted impact times</li>
<li>the overall max impact time : max of all the impact times</li>
</ul>


<p>Using this and your SLAs it is possible to define policies for your build times such as &ldquo;the max build time should not be more than X&rdquo;. If you want to speed up your build, you can set a target build time and analyzing the graph should help you to understand what architecture changes you need to make to your system in order to meet this build time (this sounds a lot like <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">Toyota&rsquo;s Improvement Kata</a> &hellip;)</p>

<p>I loved this talk ! I found the speaker captivating, he presented novel ideas which is not always the case.</p>

<p>Here are <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/AbrahamMarinPerez/keeping-your-cicd-pipeline-as-fast-as-it-needs-to-be">the slides</a>, and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8JxoKJng_eQ">the same presentation at Devoxx UK</a>.</p>

<h2>To Be Continued</h2>

<p>I promised 5, and that&rsquo;s only 2 talks ! Stay tuned, I&rsquo;ll write about the 3 others in the coming weeks. <a href="/top-5-talks-i-attended-at-javaone-2016-part-2/">Here they are</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Actors and Green Threads in Java Demystified]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/actors-and-green-threads-in-java-demystified/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-15T13:17:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/actors-and-green-threads-in-java-demystified</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After finishing my <a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata">concurrency-kata</a>, one of the things that most surprised me, is how simple it was to prototype the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actor_model">Actor Model</a> in Java using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_threads">Green Threads</a>.</p>

<h2>The Code</h2>

<p>First, here is the base class for all actors.</p>

<p>```java
public class Actor implements Runnable {</p>

<pre><code>private final ExecutorService threadPool;
private final ConcurrentLinkedQueue&lt;Runnable&gt; mailbox = new ConcurrentLinkedQueue&lt;&gt;();
private boolean stoped;

public Actor(ExecutorService threadPool) {
    this.threadPool = threadPool;
}

public void run() {
    if (stoped) {
        return;
    }

    Runnable nextMessage = mailbox.poll();
    if (nextMessage != null) {
        nextMessage.run();
    }
    submitContinuation();
}

public void start() {
    submitContinuation();
}

protected void stop() {
    stoped = true;
}

protected void send(Runnable runnable) {
    mailbox.add(runnable);
}

private void submitContinuation() {
    threadPool.submit(this);
}
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>As you can see, I simply used Runnable as the type of the messages.</p>

<p>The Actor itself is Runnable, meaning that it can be submitted to the thread pool. When executed :</p>

<ol>
<li>it tries to handle a message from the mailbox if there is one.</li>
<li>It then re-submits the actor itself</li>
</ol>


<p>This ensures that only one thread is executing messages on an actor at a given time, and it also avoids spawning new thread for every new actor.</p>

<p>As an example, here is how I used this to make an actor of an existing InProcessChatRoom class.</p>

<p>```java
public interface ChatRoom {</p>

<pre><code>void broadcast(Output client, String message);
...
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>```java
public class InProcessChatRoom implements ChatRoom {</p>

<pre><code>...
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>```java
public class ChatRoomActor extends Actor implements ChatRoom {</p>

<pre><code>private final ChatRoom realChatroom;

public ChatRoomActor(ChatRoom realChatroom, ExecutorService threadPool) {
    super(threadPool);
    this.realChatroom = realChatroom;
    start();
}

@Override
public void broadcast(final Output client, final String message) {
    send(new Runnable() {
        @Override
        public void run() {
            realChatroom.broadcast(client, message);
        }
    });
}
...
</code></pre>

<p>}
```
ChatRoomActor is in fact some kind of proxy to use from other actors to send messages to the chat room.</p>

<p>As with any implementation of the Actors Model, the neet thing is the separation of threading and logic. That makes it so much simpler ! (You can get more detail about the complexity I am talking about by taking a look at the <a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata">concurrency-kata</a>)</p>

<h2>Performances</h2>

<p>Here is a performance summary of this implementation compared to others on a &ldquo;throughput vs clients&rdquo; benchmark of the style &ldquo;Enter while others are talking&rdquo;</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/philou/concurrency-kata/master/enter-while-others-are-talking.png" alt="Result graphs of benchmark enter while others are talking" /></a></p>

<p>Results can be disappointing compared to other implementations but the example itself is a bit misleading. The chatroom does exclusively message passing, there is not much computation to parallelize, in a different setting, the results would have been completely different.</p>

<h2>Limitations</h2>

<p>As you can see, this implementation is just a quick prototype, nothing production ready. Here are the main limitations I can think of right now :</p>

<ul>
<li>It uses <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Busy_waiting">Busy Waiting</a> for the next message, meaning that it consumes unnecessary resources, and that more important messages to other Actors might be delayed</li>
<li>Usually, actor messages are selected on their type rather than on their order of arrival, this is not the case here</li>
<li>The usage of the Runnable interface as base message type, though handy, opens the door to inter-thread calls that might violate the model altogether</li>
<li>There is absolutely no support of out of process actors until the messages are Serializable</li>
</ul>


<h2>Going Further</h2>

<p>I started this <a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata">concurrency-kata</a> as a training material about concurrency for colleagues at <a href="http://www.murex.com">work</a>. In the spirit of the coding kata, it&rsquo;s a git repo you can walk, explore and experiment with.</p>

<p>So if you want to learn more about different models of concurrency, you are welcome to have a look at the How-To section in the <a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata">README</a> file.</p>

<p>On my part, although it was a lot more work than I would have guessed at the beginning, I barely scratch the surface of the subject ! I could now :</p>

<ul>
<li>extract the <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communicating_sequential_processes">CSP</a> or Actor implementation and make them more robust</li>
<li>practice and present the whole kata as a 2 hours live coding session</li>
<li>prepare a hands-on training about concurrency</li>
</ul>


<p>So, if you are willing to do any of the above you are welcome to contribute !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
