<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: management | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/management/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-12T06:55:18+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 SPA Conference takeaways that could make us better software professionals]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/5-spa-conference-takeaways-that-could-make-us-better-software-professionals/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-06T22:17:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/5-spa-conference-takeaways-that-could-make-us-better-software-professionals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, my colleague <a href="https://ahmadatwi.me/">Ahmad Atwi</a> and I went to the London <a href="https://www.spaconference.org/spa2017/">SPA Conference</a> to give our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oJsukJhxt7E">Remote eXtreme Practice</a> talk.</p>

<p>The London <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/">eXtreme Programming</a> is one of the most active in the world. You could feel an XP atmosphere at the conference. For example, people like <a href="http://www.natpryce.com/">Nat Pryce</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/sf105">Steve Freeman</a>, authors of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321503627/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0321503627&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=fcdd83a07a3cfb190f2c8e7e8b9f72c3">GOOSGT</a> book were speakers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321503627/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0321503627&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=fcdd83a07a3cfb190f2c8e7e8b9f72c3"><img src="../imgs/2017-07-06-5-spa-conference-takeaways-that-could-make-us-better-software-professionals/growing.jpg" alt="The cover of Growing Object-Oriented Software, Guided By Tests" /></a></p>

<p>To summarize, we had the chance to attend a lot of very interesting sessions during the 3 days of the conference. Here are 5 pearls of wisdom I took back with me.</p>

<h2>What connascences are</h2>

<p>Identifying code <a href="http://connascence.io/">connascences</a> helps to rank refactorings and keep the system maintainable.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/rules/refactor.html">Continuous refactoring</a> is one of the core practices of XP. For me, knowing what to refactor next has been a matter of <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/CodeSmell.html">code smells</a>, discussing with my pair and gut feeling.</p>

<p>A connascence is a coupling between parts of the system. Two parts of your code are connascent if changing one implies changing the other. For example, a function call is connascent by name with the function definition. If you change one, you need to change the other.</p>

<p>Connascences are more formal than code smells. We can detect and rank them to pick the most important refactoring to do. People have listed 9 types of connascences. Some are visible in the source code, others are dynamic and difficult to spot before runtime.</p>

<p>The lowest form of connascence is <a href="http://connascence.io/name.html">&lsquo;of name&rsquo;,</a> like in the function call example above. The worst form is <a href="http://connascence.io/identity.html">&lsquo;of Identity&rsquo;</a>, when different parts of the system must reference the same object.</p>

<iframe src="http://philippe.bourgau.net//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/jPvF4gxm5z6cGN?startSlide=14" width="510" height="420" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p>The higher the connascence, the more difficult it is to evolve the parts involved. Instead of relying on intuition, you can use a connascence based refactoring algorithm :</p>

<ol>
<li>Detect the highest connascence</li>
<li>Reduce or remove it</li>
<li>Repeat.</li>
</ol>


<p>Thanks <a href="https://twitter.com/xpsurgery">Kevin Rutherford</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/mowat27">Adrian Mowat</a> for your <a href="http://xpsurgery.com/resources/connascence-hunt-slides/">Red Green then what ?</a> session about connascence.</p>

<h2>Tips for pairing with junior developers</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/irinatsyganok">Irina Tsyganok</a> and <a href="http://www.natpryce.com/">Nat Pryce</a> gave a very fun session about this topic. A lot of valuable points discussed, from which I saved a few pearls of wisdom.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="fr"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Cat eating session from <a href="https://twitter.com/natpryce">@natpryce</a> at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/spaconf17?src=hash">#spaconf17</a> (unless <a href="https://twitter.com/irinatsyganok">@irinatsyganok</a> stops him) <a href="https://t.co/XSiaPDp9kJ">pic.twitter.com/XSiaPDp9kJ</a></p>&mdash; Andy Longshaw (@andylongshaw) <a href="https://twitter.com/andylongshaw/status/879714743963054080">27 juin 2017</a></blockquote>


<script async src="http://philippe.bourgau.net//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>It was reassuring to hear Nat saying that &ldquo;As we gain experience, we are not expected to know everything&rdquo;. Pairing with developers out of college is an occasion to &ldquo;exchange&rdquo; skills. Hard learned design skills versus updates on the latest technologies.</p>

<p>I also learned about the <a href="http://actingcoachscotland.co.uk/blog/expert-induced-amnesia/">Expert&rsquo;s Amnesia</a> and why experts often have a hard time teaching. Expert level knowledge is by nature instinctive. At this level of skill, it becomes very difficult to detail the logic of things that seem obvious.</p>

<h2>We engineers are more mentors than coaches</h2>

<p>In the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0201616416/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0201616416&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=dc2f9dc4f5ca106842921bfded07b405">first XP book</a>, there were only 3 roles in the team : team members, on site customer and XP coach. The XP coach should be a developer who can help the team to learn the practices and principles of XP.</p>

<p>About the same time, the personal or professional coach jobs appeared. The Scrum Master, is to Scrum what the XP coach is to XP, without the developer part. Remember the joke &ldquo;Scrum is like XP, without everything that makes it work&rdquo; (<a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/FlaccidScrum.html">Flaccid Scrum</a>).</p>

<p>It looks like the Agile Coach job title appeared out of all this. The problem is no one exactly knows what this is. Should he be an experienced developer like the XP coach ? A great people person ? Or someone good at introducing change ? or a mix of these ?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.selfishprogramming.com/about/">Portia Tung</a> and <a href="https://uk.linkedin.com/in/helenlisowski">Helen Lisowski</a> &rsquo;s  talk &ldquo;The power of coaching&rdquo; clarified that.</p>

<p>There is no knowledge transfer from the coach to the coachees ! On the other side, a mentor does transfer knowledge to his mentees. The coach helps his coachee take a step back and take decisions in full consciousness. The goal of the mentor is to inspire and train to new techniques.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m fine being a mentor and not a coach ;&ndash;)</p>

<h2>Servant leaders need to be tough at times</h2>

<p>We hear a lot about servant leadership nowadays. Scrum Master should be servant leaders, as well as managers in agile organizations.</p>

<p><a href="https://fr.linkedin.com/company/bellebeck-limited">Angie Main</a> gave a very interesting session about servant leadership. She made an interesting point I had not heard about before. We all know that servant leaders should trust the team to get the work done most of the time. In spite of that, servant leaders must also be ready to step in and remove people who don&rsquo;t fit in and endanger the team !</p>

<p>This reminded me of what Jim Collins says in <a href="http://www.wikisummaries.org/wiki/Built_to_Last#Chapter_6_.E2.80.93_Cult-like_Cultures">Built to last</a> : &ldquo;People who don&rsquo;t fit are expelled like viruses !&rdquo;</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0060516402/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0060516402&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=pbourgau-20&amp;linkId=e83ad8e3dcf7bdb7f875d5b22e8eb4c6"><img src="../imgs/2017-07-06-5-spa-conference-takeaways-that-could-make-us-better-software-professionals/built-to-last.jpg" alt="The cover of Built to Last" /></a></p>

<h2>1/3000 ideas succeeds</h2>

<p>Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/ozzieyuce">Ozlem Yuce</a>&rsquo;s session, I learned about the &ldquo;Job To Be Done&rdquo; technique to understand the customer&rsquo;s real needs.</p>

<p>Studies measured that only 1 idea out of 3000 ends up as a successful product ! <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/file.PostFileLoader.html?id=56217976614325233f8b4567&amp;assetKey=AS%3A285916150157312%401445179130594">Here</a> seems to be the original research.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll remember this fact next time I&rsquo;m ask for a funky feature !</p>

<h2>To conclude</h2>

<p>At the end, we had a very good time at SPAconference. The talks were insightful, we had interesting discussions, the premises were comfortable and on top of that, food was great !</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m already eager to go to SPA conference 2018 !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Side Projects Matter]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/side-projects-matter/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-13T09:13:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/side-projects-matter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a manager, you could benefit a lot from helping your developers with their side projects.</p>

<p>I finished my <a href="https://philous-planning-poker.herokuapp.com/">latest side project</a>. That&rsquo;s the fifth serious one I bring to an end :</p>

<ol>
<li>2010-2014 <a href="/rip-mes-courses-dot-fr/">www.mes-courses.fr</a>, an improved UI for online groceries. This was both a technical project and a wannabe business</li>
<li>Since 2011, <a href="/">this blog</a></li>
<li>2015 <a href="/agileavatars-dot-com-magnets-for-real/">www.agileavatars.com</a>, a custom magnet shop for agile team boards. This was a lean startup style business project</li>
<li>2016 <a href="/verify-the-big-o-complexity-of-ruby-code-in-rspec/">complexity-asserts</a> a unit test matcher to enforce algorithm complexity. This was a technical project time boxed to 20h.</li>
<li>2016-2017 <a href="/planning-poker/">Philou&rsquo;s Planning Poker</a>, a technical product, that I built to solve my own problem.</li>
</ol>


<p>The more I do side projects, the more I am certain of their value to my employer.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-06-13-side-projects-matter/side-project.jpg" alt="Hand drawing with stating 'creative business idea'" /><div class="image-credits"><a href='http://fr.freepik.com/vecteurs-libre/dessines-a-la-main-business-icons_769576.htm'>Designed by Freepik</a></div></p>

<h2>Reasons companies discourage side projects</h2>

<p>Unfortunately, most companies discourage their employees to have side projects. It boils down to fundamental fears :</p>

<ul>
<li>they might get less done</li>
<li>they might leave</li>
</ul>


<p>While these are legitimate, most of the time, they are also unlikely or short sighted.</p>

<h3>Why don&rsquo;t they work extra hours ?</h3>

<p>Said another way : if developers want to code, why don&rsquo;t they add new features to the company&rsquo;s products ?</p>

<p>From my own experience, having a side project has always been an <a href="/is-there-any-room-for-the-not-passionate-developer/">energy booster</a>. Side projects have made me more effective at work !</p>

<p>For a compulsive hacker, a side project is a hobby ! As painting, piano or soccer is to others. Working on smaller software, being in full control, renews the joy of programming.</p>

<h3>They&rsquo;ll quit once they&rsquo;ve learned new skills !</h3>

<p>Simply said, if a company&rsquo;s retention strategy is to deprecate its developers &hellip; It&rsquo;s got problems a lot worse than a few people doing side projects at night !</p>

<h3>They won&rsquo;t be as productive !</h3>

<p>You could think that developers will be less focused on the company&rsquo;s issues while at work. Indeed, passionate side-project hackers always have it on top of their heads.</p>

<p>Most of the time though, the extra energy provided by the side project out-weights this focus loss.</p>

<p>In the end, we should trust people to be professional. Let&rsquo;s deal with the problem later, when someone actually starts to underdeliver.</p>

<h3>They&rsquo;ll leave if it turns into a successful product !</h3>

<p>Building a product company is pretty damn hard. A time starved side project is pretty unlikely to turn into a successful business. Not much to worry about here ! If it happens, the company is lucky to have had such a productive employee.</p>

<h3>They might steal our intellectual property !</h3>

<p>This one is true. Only a very small minority of people might do that, but the risk remains.</p>

<p>You might conclude that it&rsquo;s easier to play it safe and prohibit side projects &hellip; at the same time, it&rsquo;s always sad to punish the majority for a minority&rsquo;s bad behavior.</p>

<p>It boils down to a tradeoff between risks and rewards. How sensible the company is to IP theft vs the benefits of having a side-project friendly policy.</p>

<p>If you are wondering what these benefits are, read on !</p>

<h2>Side projects made me a more valuable employee</h2>

<p>As developers, side project teach us a lot. What is less obvious, is how these new skills benefit our employers !</p>

<h3>Keep up with technology</h3>

<p>A side project is an occasion to work on any subject, with any technology we want. That&rsquo;s the perfect time to try that latest <a href="https://colorlib.com/wp/javascript-frameworks/">JS</a> framework we cannot use at work.</p>

<p>This will help us and our companies to transition to these new technologies in the future.</p>

<p>Experimenting different platforms also widens our horizons. It teaches us new ways of addressing problems in our daily stack. For examples, learning <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/267862/what-makes-lisp-macros-so-special">LISP macros</a> pushed me to use lambdas to create new control structures in Java, C++ or C#.</p>

<p>The conclusion is that side projects make people more productive and adaptive. Which in turn makes companies more productive and resilient</p>

<h3>Understand what technical debt is</h3>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-06-13-side-projects-matter/iceberg-technical-debt.jpg" alt="A technical debt iceberg" /><div class="image-credits"><a href='https://www.vectorcast.com/testing-solutions/technical-debt-legacy-code'>Image from Vector Software</a></div></p>

<p>The bottleneck in a side project is always time. In this context, to deliver fast enough to keep my motivation high, I tend to take technical debt. Particularly because I ignore how long I&rsquo;ll be maintaining this code.</p>

<p>Even so, if I later decide to stick to this side project, this technical debt will be an issue.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s what technical debt is : a conscious choice to cut a corner and fix it later. Without keeping track of the cut corners, it&rsquo;s not debt anymore, but crappy code ! That&rsquo;s why I ended up using <a href="/a-seamless-way-to-keep-track-of-technical-debt-in-your-source-code/"><code>#TODO</code> comments</a> in my side projects.</p>

<p>Later down the road, at any moment, I can decide to invest in refactoring some technical debt out. We can apply the exact same principles at our day jobs.</p>

<h3>Understanding what a business is</h3>

<p>Trying to make money from your side project taught me other kind of lessons. To sell my product or service, I had to learn a ton of other skills than the typical developer has. Nothing will sell without marketing or sales. I also had to dip my toes in design, web content creation and project management.</p>

<p>Once I went through this, I was able to better understand a big picture at work. It became easier to discuss with product, project and sales people. I&rsquo;m able to make better tradeoffs between engineering, product and technical debt. Non technical colleagues appreciate that. As developers, it increases our value and trustworthiness.</p>

<h3>Discover new ways of doing things</h3>

<p>While progressing towards my own side project goals, I had to search the internet for help on some tasks. I ended up using SaaS tools, and discovered alternate practices to the ones I was using in my daily job.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s great for employers ! Developers will gain perspective about which company processes work well and which don&rsquo;t. If you have some form of continuous improvement in place at work, they&rsquo;ll suggest great ideas ! If you don&rsquo;t, then you should <a href="/how-we-introduced-efficient-agile-retrospectives/">start doing retrospectives</a> now !</p>

<h2>Companies should sponsor side projects</h2>

<p>I hope I convinced you that side projects are at least as efficient as a formal training. The topics are unknown at the beginning, but that&rsquo;s the trick : they deal with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_are_known_knowns">unknown unknowns</a> !</p>

<p>There are many ways a company can help its employees with their side projects :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/slack.html">Slack time</a> is a great way to spark the interest in a topic. Developers might start something in their slack time, and continue as a side project. Provided the topic as value for the company, they could continue using their Slack time on it.</li>
<li>Hosting a <a href="https://startupweekend.org/">Startup Weekend</a> or a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hackathon">Hackathon</a>. Most company offices are empty on Saturdays and Sundays. You could ask your company to lend its premises for such an event. It&rsquo;s very likely that some employees will take part.</li>
<li>Even better, some companies, like <a href="https://labs.spotify.com/2013/02/15/organizing-a-hack-week/">Spotify</a>, organize regular Hackathons <em>on office hours</em> ! That&rsquo;s Slack time, on steroids !</li>
<li>Sponsoring internal communities can enable employees with side-projects to help each other. Sponsorship could be free lunch, premises or a regular small slice of time on work hours.</li>
<li>Providing a clear legal framework around side projects reduces the risks for everyone. Questions like the ownership of intellectual property are better dealt with upfront.</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://labs.spotify.com/2013/02/15/organizing-a-hack-week/"><img src="../imgs/2017-06-13-side-projects-matter/spotify-hackathon.jpg" alt="A photo of Spotify's open space during a Hackathon" /></a></p>

<p>If you are a developer looking for a side project idea, suggest slack time in retrospective ! You could also ask for sponsorship and organize a startup week-end or a lunch time community.</p>

<p>Finally, if your company is side-project friendly, communicate about it ! It&rsquo;s a great selling point and it will attract great programmers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to kill Scrum Zombies ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-kill-scrum-zombies/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-03T05:41:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-kill-scrum-zombies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First of all, what is that ? Usually, Scrum zombies go in groups, and quite often, you&rsquo;ll find a full team of them :</p>

<p>A typical team of Scrum Zombies follows Scrum pretty well, does all the ceremonies, adopted good engineering practices, and might even be delivering OK. But all the fun is gone, everyone is on autopilot, no continuous improvement is happening anymore, retrospectives are dull and repetitive &hellip; There&rsquo;s a gut feeling in the air that sooner or later, the project will miss a turn.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-11-03-how-to-kill-scrum-zombies/sad-fans.jpg" title="A team of sad fans, looking like lost zombies" ></p>

<p>Sounds familiar ?</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s going on exactly ?</h2>

<p>When dev teams want to get more (agile|lean|reactive|.*) they often resort to hiring a full time coach. At first, a coach can have a great impact on the team. He will unblock change, show different ways of getting things done and train the team to new practices. Once all this is done, the coach becomes like any team member, or sometimes just leaves. That&rsquo;s the point when the team, as a whole, has to take on responsibility for continuous improvement.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s needed then ?</h2>

<p>The team needs to be able to conduct their own experiments and improvements. For this, they need divergent thinking, or creativity, or thinking out of the box; name it as you prefer. In a complex world, no single individual can bring all the answers to all the upcoming issues any team will face. Once the coach has put in place the practices necessary to continuous improvement, it&rsquo;s up to the team.</p>

<p>Unlike what the common idea says, creativity does not come out of thin air, it is cultivated !</p>

<h3>Diversity in the team</h3>

<p>Diversity does not mean minority quotas in your team. Diversity means diversity of interest, of way of thinking, of mentality, of way of working &hellip; The more diverse your team members, the more likely they&rsquo;ll find innovative ways to work out of their current problems.</p>

<h3>Slack</h3>

<p>Removing any slack from the planning is the surest way to kill creativity and innovation. Great ideas often come at unexpected moments (see <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Thinking-Learning-Refactor-Programmers/dp/1934356050/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1478151003&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=pragmatic+thinking+and+learning">Pragmatic Thinking and Learning: Refactor Your Wetware</a>) because the mind works in the background to find them. You want to leave some time for that.</p>

<h3>Go to conferences</h3>

<p>Creativity builds on creativity. Great ideas are often adaptations of one or many existing ones. Going to conferences is a great way to collect a lot of ideas !</p>

<h3>Share trainings and lectures</h3>

<p>Different people might react differently to the same information. When a team member finishes reading a book or comes back from a training, it&rsquo;s a great idea to have him present what he learned to the others. This will reinforce his own learning, but it might also trigger new ideas in his team mates.</p>

<h3>A dash of turnover</h3>

<p>Too much turnover can be fatal to a team, but not having any will bring other kind of problems too. Newcomers will challenge the status-quo, and the &ldquo;this is how it&rsquo;s done here&rdquo; motto won&rsquo;t be enough for them. That&rsquo;s just what&rsquo;s needed to trigger a sane re-examination of the current practices. Oh &hellip; and turnover between teams is fine too ! If your company is large enough, you don&rsquo;t need to hire or fire people to create turnover, just encourage them to move to other teams !</p>

<h2>The tricky part of complexity</h2>

<p>By leaving time for other things than just cranking out stories, life will come back into the project, and zombies should go away. But wait, there&rsquo;s even more !</p>

<p>Software projects are pretty complex beasts. One of the most counter-intuitive thing with these complex system is that they make planning very difficult. Focusing too much on your main goal might be slowing you down !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-11-03-how-to-kill-scrum-zombies/large-tunnels-in-a-mine.jpg" title="Crossroad of large tunnels in a mine" ></p>

<p>In the face of complexity your project landscape is like a maze of tunnels ! Who said you&rsquo;re choosing the best ones ? By keeping free time to explore other, seemingly unrelated, topics you might discover opportunities that will remove a lot of the work to get to your final destination !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Grow a Culture Book]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-grow-a-culture-book/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-08T05:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-grow-a-culture-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you read valve&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf">Handbook for new employees</a> ?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-08-how-to-grow-a-culture-book/valve-handbook-for-new-employees.jpg" title="A stack of Valve&rsquo;s Handbook for new employees" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://management30.com">Management 3.0</a> terms, that&rsquo;s a <a href="https://management30.com/practice/value-stories/">culture book</a>. It&rsquo;s a great way to build and crystallize a culture, and it serves as a guide for newcomers, and can later serve as an hiring ad for your team or company.</p>

<p>The good thing about a culture book, is that you don&rsquo;t have to write it in one go. It&rsquo;s a living artifact anyway, so you&rsquo;d better not ! Our current culture book has emerged from a collection of pages in our wiki.</p>

<h2>It started as working agreements</h2>

<p>The first real contributions to our culture book (though we did not know it at the time) was spending some time in retrospectives to define and review our working and coding conventions.</p>

<p>When we started doing retrospectives, we had to discuss, agree and formalize the decisions we made about our way of working. We usually did a &lsquo;review how we work&rsquo; activity at the beginning the retros, spending 10 minutes to make sure we all understood and agreed on our current working conventions. If there was any disagreement or update required, we would discuss them during the retro, and at the end, add, remove or modify items from our agreement page.</p>

<h2>It continued as self-organization workshops</h2>

<p>After a while, we had built up a pretty extensive set of working and coding conventions. The team had already become quite productive, but to keep the momentum in the long run, we needed to increase self-organization. By reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Jurgen-Appelo/e/B00460MCJM/ref=sr_tc_2_0?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;qid=1470715896&amp;sr=8-2-ent">Management 3.0 books</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Workout-Practices-Improve-Delight-Management-ebook/dp/B00N6REYKQ/ref=asap_bc?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8#navbar">Management Workout</a> (which has been re-edited as <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Managing-Happiness-Games-Practices-Motivate/dp/1119268680/ref=asap_bc?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8">Managing for Happiness</a>) in particular, I found description about how to use a <a href="https://management30.com/practice/delegation-board/">delegation board</a> and <a href="https://management30.com/product/delegation-poker/">delegation pokers</a> to measure and formalize the current delegation level of a team.</p>

<p>We did this, and started a lot of self-organization workshops :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/">Stop feeling like a kid every time you ask a day off</a></li>
<li><a href="/scrum-teams-do-not-need-a-scrum-master/">Scrum Teams Do Not Need a Scrum Master</a></li>
<li><a href="/make-hiring-everyones-business/">Make hiring everyone&rsquo;s business</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">How to deal with the incentive system in an agile team ?</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/">How We Decentralized Our Company&rsquo;s Training Program</a></li>
</ul>


<p>After each of these workshops, we created a wiki page, explaining how we planned to handle the subject in the team.</p>

<h2>The book</h2>

<p>At that point, we had fairly extensive and formal descriptions of our working practices and conventions. By reading this set of pages, someone would get a pretty accurate grasp of our principles and values.</p>

<p>Wondering how we could write our own culture book, I had an &ldquo;Aha !&rdquo; moment and realized that all I had to do was to create a wiki page pointing to all our different agreement pages. This only took 5 minutes.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-08-how-to-grow-a-culture-book/content.jpg" title="The table of content of our culture book" ></p>

<p>At the moment, our culture book serves 3 purposes :</p>

<ul>
<li>documentation for the team members</li>
<li>guide for newcomers</li>
<li>description about how we work for people in the company who might want to move to our team</li>
</ul>


<p>Next step would be to add a dash of design, a few war stories, export it as a PDF, and use it outside to advertise the team and the company.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How We Decentralized Our Company's Training Program]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-18T05:31:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Maybe your company too has a development program you can use to track and organize your training path. That&rsquo;s already great ! It is often not perfect though. Sometimes, the initiative in itself can feel like an afterthought. Some other times, the process is completely left to the employee and his manager, with varying results, from great to forced upon everyone.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-18-how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/learning.jpg" title="A &lsquo;learning&rsquo; word cloud" ></p>

<h2>How did we rebuild this program in our team</h2>

<p>As you might remember if you read my <a href="/blog/categories/selforganizing/">previous posts</a>, we started a self organization initiative using a <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/delegation-employee-engagement/">delegation board</a>. When we tried to decentralize <a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">the end of year evaluation</a>, we started discussing the subjects of personal development. We decided to have a dedicated workshop about this subject</p>

<h2>Guiding principles</h2>

<p>In our company, the development program allows a manager to assign specific learning goals to his collaborators, and anyone can also create his own goals to justify going to specific trainings. Starting from that, we agreed that the development program should be used to help anyone in the team to improve skills that are interesting for both the company and the employee. If the employee is interested in something completely unrelated to work, then he should obviously tackle that in his own time. If the company needs its employee to acquire some immediate mandatory skills, then that should be part of the daily job and subject to the end of year evaluation.</p>

<p>The idea is to try to find a win-win combinations, were employees are motivated to work their best at a company that they know helps them to full-fill their long term goals.</p>

<h2>What did we came us with ?</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-18-how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/mentor-mentee.jpg" title="A lion and a lion cub side by side" ></p>

<p>This workshop was quite effective :</p>

<ul>
<li>First of all, everyone is responsible for his own development, it&rsquo;s a chance offered by the company. It cannot be forced unto people.</li>
<li>It is based on volunteer mentorship : everyone should have regular meetings with his mentor to asses his progress on his long term goal, to try to get feedback and ideas about how to move forward. We started by saying that the team leader is the default mentor, but anyone can find another mentor at any moment.</li>
<li>The process starts with the search for a long term goal. Examples are &ldquo;I want to be an agile coach&rdquo;, or &ldquo;I want to be a performance expert&rdquo;</li>
<li>With the help of the mentor if needed, the long term goal should be split in yearly objectives and tracked using <a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/HenrikJanVanderPol/how-to-outperform-anyone-else-introduction-to-okr">OKRs</a></li>
<li>Everyone is free to track his progress has he wishes. Visual tracking makes the discussion with the mentor a lot easier. We have been looking at tools to track OKRs but it was surprisingly difficult to find one that suited our use. Most are enterprisy tools with manager-managee relationships. We just wanted simple personal tracking tools. For my part, I adapted a <a href="https://trello.com/b/MPM4rspd/okrs">Trello</a> board I found on the internet.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>After doing a few months of this, I can say that this has a positive aspect on motivation, people told me that they felt more in control of their destiny. Something else I noted, is that junior developers need help and guidance. They often don&rsquo;t really know what they want to do in a few years, so they really need a mentor to help them find out the what and the how. The other side of this is that a team obviously needs senior developers to act as mentor &hellip; among other things.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
