<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: management | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/management/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-03T20:10:38+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Grow a Culture Book]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-grow-a-culture-book/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-08T05:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-grow-a-culture-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you read valve&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf">Handbook for new employees</a> ?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/company/Valve_Handbook_LowRes.pdf"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-08-how-to-grow-a-culture-book/valve-handbook-for-new-employees.jpg" title="A stack of Valve&rsquo;s Handbook for new employees" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="https://management30.com">Management 3.0</a> terms, that&rsquo;s a <a href="https://management30.com/practice/value-stories/">culture book</a>. It&rsquo;s a great way to build and crystallize a culture, and it serves as a guide for newcomers, and can later serve as an hiring ad for your team or company.</p>

<p>The good thing about a culture book, is that you don&rsquo;t have to write it in one go. It&rsquo;s a living artifact anyway, so you&rsquo;d better not ! Our current culture book has emerged from a collection of pages in our wiki.</p>

<h2>It started as working agreements</h2>

<p>The first real contributions to our culture book (though we did not know it at the time) was spending some time in retrospectives to define and review our working and coding conventions.</p>

<p>When we started doing retrospectives, we had to discuss, agree and formalize the decisions we made about our way of working. We usually did a &lsquo;review how we work&rsquo; activity at the beginning the retros, spending 10 minutes to make sure we all understood and agreed on our current working conventions. If there was any disagreement or update required, we would discuss them during the retro, and at the end, add, remove or modify items from our agreement page.</p>

<h2>It continued as self-organization workshops</h2>

<p>After a while, we had built up a pretty extensive set of working and coding conventions. The team had already become quite productive, but to keep the momentum in the long run, we needed to increase self-organization. By reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Jurgen-Appelo/e/B00460MCJM/ref=sr_tc_2_0?qid=1470715896&amp;sr=8-2-ent">Management 3.0 books</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Workout-Practices-Improve-Delight-Management-ebook/dp/B00N6REYKQ/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8#navbar">Management Workout</a> (which has been re-edited as <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Managing-Happiness-Games-Practices-Motivate/dp/1119268680/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8">Managing for Happiness</a>) in particular, I found description about how to use a <a href="https://management30.com/practice/delegation-board/">delegation board</a> and <a href="https://management30.com/product/delegation-poker/">delegation pokers</a> to measure and formalize the current delegation level of a team.</p>

<p>We did this, and started a lot of self-organization workshops :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/">Stop feeling like a kid every time you ask a day off</a></li>
<li><a href="/scrum-teams-do-not-need-a-scrum-master/">Scrum Teams Do Not Need a Scrum Master</a></li>
<li><a href="/make-hiring-everyones-business/">Make hiring everyone&rsquo;s business</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">How to deal with the incentive system in an agile team ?</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/">How We Decentralized Our Company&rsquo;s Training Program</a></li>
</ul>


<p>After each of these workshops, we created a wiki page, explaining how we planned to handle the subject in the team.</p>

<h2>The book</h2>

<p>At that point, we had fairly extensive and formal descriptions of our working practices and conventions. By reading this set of pages, someone would get a pretty accurate grasp of our principles and values.</p>

<p>Wondering how we could write our own culture book, I had an &ldquo;Aha !&rdquo; moment and realized that all I had to do was to create a wiki page pointing to all our different agreement pages. This only took 5 minutes.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-08-08-how-to-grow-a-culture-book/content.jpg" title="The table of content of our culture book" ></p>

<p>At the moment, our culture book serves 3 purposes :</p>

<ul>
<li>documentation for the team members</li>
<li>guide for newcomers</li>
<li>description about how we work for people in the company who might want to move to our team</li>
</ul>


<p>Next step would be to add a dash of design, a few war stories, export it as a PDF, and use it outside to advertise the team and the company.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How We Decentralized Our Company's Training Program]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-18T05:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Maybe your company too has a development program you can use to track and organize your training path. That&rsquo;s already great ! It is often not perfect though. Sometimes, the initiative in itself can feel like an afterthought. Some other times, the process is completely left to the employee and his manager, with varying results, from great to forced upon everyone.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-18-how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/learning.jpg" title="A &lsquo;learning&rsquo; word cloud" ></p>

<h2>How did we rebuild this program in our team</h2>

<p>As you might remember if you read my <a href="/blog/categories/selforganizing/">previous posts</a>, we started a self organization initiative using a <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/delegation-employee-engagement/">delegation board</a>. When we tried to decentralize <a href="/how-to-deal-with-the-incentive-system-in-an-agile-team/">the end of year evaluation</a>, we started discussing the subjects of personal development. We decided to have a dedicated workshop about this subject</p>

<h2>Guiding principles</h2>

<p>In our company, the development program allows a manager to assign specific learning goals to his collaborators, and anyone can also create his own goals to justify going to specific trainings. Starting from that, we agreed that the development program should be used to help anyone in the team to improve skills that are interesting for both the company and the employee. If the employee is interested in something completely unrelated to work, then he should obviously tackle that in his own time. If the company needs its employee to acquire some immediate mandatory skills, then that should be part of the daily job and subject to the end of year evaluation.</p>

<p>The idea is to try to find a win-win combinations, were employees are motivated to work their best at a company that they know helps them to full-fill their long term goals.</p>

<h2>What did we came us with ?</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-18-how-we-decentralized-our-companys-training-program/mentor-mentee.jpg" title="A lion and a lion cub side by side" ></p>

<p>This workshop was quite effective :</p>

<ul>
<li>First of all, everyone is responsible for his own development, it&rsquo;s a chance offered by the company. It cannot be forced unto people.</li>
<li>It is based on volunteer mentorship : everyone should have regular meetings with his mentor to asses his progress on his long term goal, to try to get feedback and ideas about how to move forward. We started by saying that the team leader is the default mentor, but anyone can find another mentor at any moment.</li>
<li>The process starts with the search for a long term goal. Examples are &ldquo;I want to be an agile coach&rdquo;, or &ldquo;I want to be a performance expert&rdquo;</li>
<li>With the help of the mentor if needed, the long term goal should be split in yearly objectives and tracked using <a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/HenrikJanVanderPol/how-to-outperform-anyone-else-introduction-to-okr">OKRs</a></li>
<li>Everyone is free to track his progress has he wishes. Visual tracking makes the discussion with the mentor a lot easier. We have been looking at tools to track OKRs but it was surprisingly difficult to find one that suited our use. Most are enterprisy tools with manager-managee relationships. We just wanted simple personal tracking tools. For my part, I adapted a <a href="https://trello.com/b/MPM4rspd/okrs">Trello</a> board I found on the internet.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>After doing a few months of this, I can say that this has a positive aspect on motivation, people told me that they felt more in control of their destiny. Something else I noted, is that junior developers need help and guidance. They often don&rsquo;t really know what they want to do in a few years, so they really need a mentor to help them find out the what and the how. The other side of this is that a team obviously needs senior developers to act as mentor &hellip; among other things.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scrum teams do not need A Scrum Master]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/scrum-teams-do-not-need-a-scrum-master/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-15T05:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/scrum-teams-do-not-need-a-scrum-master</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We don&rsquo;t have an official scrum master in our team anymore. We now have 7 ! A different team member assumes the full scrum master role at every sprint.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-15-scrum-teams-do-not-need-a-scrum-master/round-robin.jpg" title="A fat round robin bird" ></p>

<h2>Why did we switch to Scrum Master round robin ?</h2>

<p>It all started with our <a href="https://management30.com/product/delegation-poker/">delegation poker</a> (see <a href="/stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/">previous post</a>). We noticed that there were still quite some activities that I (the manager) was the only one to do. We hoped that by sharing these activities throughout the team, we would :</p>

<ul>
<li>increase everyone&rsquo;s motivation by showing a bigger picture</li>
<li>leave me more time for programming</li>
<li>learn new skills to everyone</li>
</ul>


<h2>How did we do it ?</h2>

<p>Before our <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/delegation-employee-engagement/">delegation board meeting</a>, we had prepared all the activities we are regularly doing. We found quite a few recurrent non programming tasks that traditionally eschewed to the team lead (me in that case). The initial plan was to find ways to delegate these activities to the team during the meeting, but it would have took way too much time.</p>

<p>Having identified all these activities, I individually suggested at everyone in the team to do a round robin scrum master role, which would handle all these activities for a sprint. I was happily surprise by the quasi complete buy-in from all the team. Before I announced it to the team, I did 2 things :</p>

<h3>List all the activities of the scrum master.</h3>

<p>Here is a subset :</p>

<ul>
<li>attend other teams meetings</li>
<li>make sure there are enough workable stories for the next planning session with the product owner</li>
<li>prepare and animate a retrospective</li>
<li>animate the demo</li>
</ul>


<h3>Make this more fun !</h3>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="fr"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Having <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/fun?src=hash">#fun</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/geeky?src=hash">#geeky</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/work?src=hash">#work</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/environment?src=hash">#environment</a> Our scrummaster is <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/DarthVader?src=hash">#DarthVader</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Yuda?src=hash">#Yuda</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/starwars?src=hash">#starwars</a> at <a href="https://twitter.com/Work_at_Murex">@Work_at_Murex</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/pbourgau">@pbourgau</a> <a href="https://t.co/CbZXCYwBge">pic.twitter.com/CbZXCYwBge</a></p>&mdash; Ahmad Atwi (@ahmadatwi) <a href="https://twitter.com/ahmadatwi/status/694190926684618753">1 février 2016</a></blockquote>


<script async src="http://philippe.bourgau.net//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>I bought totems for the scrum master. The team chose to keep Yoda in Paris and send Darth Vador in <a href="https://twitter.com/ahmadatwi">Ahmad</a> suitcase back in Beirut.</p>

<h2>What did we get ?</h2>

<p>After a few sprints of this, the feedback I got is that people like the increased involvement in the big picture (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Drive-Surprising-Truth-About-Motivates/dp/1594484805/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1458076848&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=daniel+pink+drive">Daniel Pink told us that already</a>). On my part, it allowed to increase my programming time to nearly 7 uninterrupted days per sprint (10 days). I&rsquo;m quite happy with this ! As for the third goal, learning new skills, I guess we&rsquo;ll need a bit more time to figure this out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stop feeling like a kid every time you ask a day off]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-12T06:35:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most companies don&rsquo;t have <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/performance-management/">unlimited vacations</a>. Most likely, if you are an employee, your days off need to be validated by your boss. If you are like me, this feels like pulling teeth &hellip; Every time I have to ask for a day off, I feel like a kid asking for an extra candy</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s not the only issue with how we traditionally deal with vacations :</p>

<ul>
<li>The boss has to make sure that there are always enough people at the office to handle emergencies</li>
<li>If the boss is himself away, getting a day off at the last moment becomes difficult</li>
</ul>


<h2>Our Delegation Board</h2>

<p>Our team at work is already rather agile : we&rsquo;re using a blend of XP and Scrumban, we follow solid engineering practices and we are always trying to improve to deliver more value to our users. After reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Management-3-0-Developers-Developing-Addison-Wesley/dp/0321712471/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1457988177&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=management+3.0">Management 3.0</a> and <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/">Management Workouts</a> I was convinced that I needed to move the team towards even more self organization.</p>

<p>We started by doing <a href="https://management30.com/product/delegation-poker/">delegation poker</a>, we created a <a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/delegation-employee-engagement/">delegation board</a>, and set out to move all cards we could to the right side of the board.</p>

<p><a href="/imgs/2016-03-12-stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/delegation-board-large.jpg"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-12-stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/delegation-board.jpg" title="Our trello delegation board" ></a></p>

<p>We spotted the following topics that could be more self organized</p>

<ul>
<li>vacations</li>
<li>hiring</li>
<li>business objectives and end of year evaluations</li>
<li>various recurring scrum related activities</li>
<li>self development objectives</li>
</ul>


<h2>Vacations</h2>

<p>We decided to tackle vacations first, because it seemed easy. We did a quick brainstorming, and here is what we came up with :</p>

<ul>
<li>We cannot change the company policy, so I&rsquo;ll still have to officially validate everyone&rsquo;s vacations in the system but &hellip;</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ll validate anything asked !</li>
<li>Our internal system allows to check the other team member&rsquo;s vacations, so everyone in the team is responsible to check that there will always be at least 2 people at work before taking a day off</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="/imgs/2016-03-12-stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/mxopal.png"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-12-stop-feeling-like-a-kid-everytime-you-ask-a-day-off/mxopal.jpg" title="Screenshot of our vacation dashboard" ></a></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s been 6 months, and it&rsquo;s been working like a charm. I think it made everything simpler once we had a clear rule about when vacations were OK or not.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How To Keep Programming When Assigned A Management Job]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-keep-programming-when-assigned-a-management-job/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-03T08:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-keep-programming-when-assigned-a-management-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Remaining a competent developer is a career long effort, if you stop programming, you&rsquo;ll loose it ! As time goes, we are regularly <del>offered</del> pushed into management positions, sometimes by cluelessness, other times by cheer necessity ! Be it temporary or long term, here are some techniques to remain a relevant developer.</p>

<h2>How Joe became a manager</h2>

<p>```
def work
  if manager?</p>

<pre><code>go_to_meetings
</code></pre>

<p>  else</p>

<pre><code>program
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Imagine you&rsquo;re Joe, an expert developer in a small software company. Everything is going fine, he&rsquo;s working on interesting subjects with 4 other, rather junior, team mates. Management is OK, at least good enough not to cause too many troubles.</p>

<p>Suddenly, the team manager leaves for a better position in another company. Unprepared for this, the small organization has difficulties to find a suitable replacement, and, you&rsquo;ll guess it, Joe is asked to take on management responsibilities until someone gets hired. How is Joe going to continue to do a good job at both programming and management ?</p>

<h2>His first reaction</h2>

<p>Two weeks into the job, Joe takes a step back and summarizes :</p>

<ul>
<li>he feels depressed when he does not program for a long time</li>
<li>he has the feeling he&rsquo;s been jumping from A to B to C to Z to A, and so on for two weeks without actually getting a lot done</li>
<li>he feels everyone is waiting for him to do things before they move</li>
<li>his mailbox is starting to make him nervous</li>
<li>it&rsquo;s difficult to program anything if you are interrupted by meetings throughout the day</li>
</ul>


<p>Joe figures out that he needs to reduce his management work if he wants to get back to programming.  After setting up an efficient <a href="bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/">TODO list</a>. He has already read some personnal effectiveness books, so he knows how one can reduce his amount of work :</p>

<ul>
<li>say no : he&rsquo;ll have to keep this in mind all the time, especially when accepting meetings or when asked for some new work</li>
<li>automate : some tasks can be automated, others can be partly automated by a good process. He&rsquo;ll have to regularly stop and think to improve how he works</li>
<li>delegate : he&rsquo;d like to push more work to the team, but it will take some time. He decides to read things on self-organized team to know how to do</li>
</ul>


<h2>Joe&rsquo;s measure of programming time</h2>

<p>In order to get some continuous time for programming, Joe books &lsquo;programming days&rsquo; in his calendar. This is also a way to say no to other meetings during this period. He starts with all Mondays, he hopes he&rsquo;ll be able to book others days as he manages to do more programming. His ideal would be to book all week for programming (while still having the management job get done !)</p>

<p>This works well, and gives Joe a motivation boost since he has the opportunity to program again :&ndash;). There are still a few glitches though :</p>

<ul>
<li>Joe often doesn&rsquo;t program &lsquo;on his own&rsquo; on Mondays because he is spending is time with junior programmers who are really appreciating his help</li>
<li>Joe once made the mistake of committing to a critical programming task that he did not manage to finish in 1 day and had to hand it over to another developer, losing more time</li>
</ul>


<p>Joe is realizing that he is more of a programming coach than a direct developer now, and that he should not commit on critical tasks but rather help others to do so. Pair programming is becoming the norm for him.</p>

<h2>Communication time</h2>

<p>While doing his full programming days, Joe realized that emails can wait. If people want an immediate answer, let them use the phone ! He now reads and answers his emails in the morning when he arrives at work, at noon just after lunch and on evenings, just before leaving. That&rsquo;s good enough for a day !</p>

<p>Joe also had to interrupt his programming day once for an urgent meeting &hellip; he now reserves 1 hour at the end of his programming days to handle such urgent meetings without interrupting his programming time.</p>

<h2>Self organized teams</h2>

<p>Meanwhile, Joe read some books about self organized teams, such as <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Workout-Practices-Improve-Delight-Clients/dp/9492032023/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1454480226&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=management+3.0+workout">Management 3.0 Workout</a> by Jurgen Appelo.</p>

<p><a href="https://management30.com/product/workouts/"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-02-03-how-to-keep-programming-when-assigned-a-management-job/management-workout.jpg" title="Management 3.0 Workout Book Cover" ></a></p>

<p>Self organization is some kind of aggressive delegation. Joe sees management as described in these books as a way to increase purpose and motivation throughout the team, while getting him more time for programming.</p>

<p>This kind of management perfectly suits agile teams. His team is already using some agile practices, such as automated testing, some kind of continuous integration, and quite a few others, to varying degrees. Joe decides to embark his team on a road to self organization, and to start by applying all the standard Scrum and eXtreme Programming practices. In parallel, he introduces the rolling Scrum Master role, where sprint after sprint, a different team member is responsible for :</p>

<ul>
<li>organizing the recurring team meetings</li>
<li>representing the team in outside meetings</li>
<li>grooming the backlog before the demo and planning</li>
</ul>


<p>This alone frees Joe 1 or 2 days of programming every week. He now helps his team mates to master all the technical agile practices they are not used to.</p>

<h2>More self organization</h2>

<p>A few months later, the team is doing well, Joe has some time for programming, but he still has some pure management job to do. From what he read from self organized teams, even these subjects can be delegated ! He decides to start workshops with the team :</p>

<ul>
<li>How can we handle vacations in a self organized way ?</li>
<li>How can we handle the hiring in a self organized way ?</li>
<li>How can we handle performance feedback and pay raises in a self organized way ?</li>
</ul>


<p>The journey is long and rough : one team member left as they were going seriously into agile. Nevertheless the team is already more motivated than it ever was, and delivers more value than it ever did.</p>

<h2>The end result for Joe</h2>

<p>Joe is now programming nearly as much as his team mates ! Most of his programming time is coaching time though. He does not sit and hack his way into a feature as he used to do. He&rsquo;s missing that a bit, he&rsquo;s also missing learning new technologies.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s why he started working on <a href="/my-own-side-project-best-practices-after-reading-the-side-project-book">side projects</a> at home, using the latest hype JavaScript framework. He&rsquo;s reading generalist programming books also, such as the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss_2?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;field-keywords=%22in+seven+weeks%22&amp;rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3A%22in+seven+weeks%22">7 XXX in 7 weeks</a> series which allow him to learn without loosing time on technical quirks he&rsquo;s not interested in at the moment &hellip;</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Seven-Languages-Weeks-Programming-Programmers/dp/193435659X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1454739459&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=7+languages+in+7+weeks"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-02-03-how-to-keep-programming-when-assigned-a-management-job/7-languages.jpg" title="Seven Languages In Seven Weeks Book Cover" ></a></p>

<p>Good luck Joe !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
