<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: lessons-learned | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/lessons-learned/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-03-08T06:11:25+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RIP mes-courses.fr]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/rip-mes-courses-dot-fr/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-27T06:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/rip-mes-courses-dot-fr</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rest In Peace <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/206938/mes-courses.fr/archives/index.html">mes-courses.fr</a>. Here is what it looked like :</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-06-27-rip-mes-courses-dot-fr/screenshot.png" title="Screen shot of the home page of mes-courses.fr" ></p>

<p>I wanted to create a really fast on-line grocery front-end, where people could shop for the week in only 5 minutes. It supported shopping recipes instead of individual items but I also envisioned to allow automatic menus recommendations, and automatic item preference selection. I started 4 years ago, and this is my last doing on the subject :). If you&rsquo;re thinking about starting your own side project, this post is for you.</p>

<h3>Here are the lessons I learned</h3>

<ul>
<li>As a professional programmer, I largely underestimated the non programming time required for a serious side project. It represents more than half the time you&rsquo;ll spend on your project (marketing, discussing with people, mock ups and prototypes)</li>
<li>When I started, I kind of estimated the time it would take me to build a first prototype. Again I ridiculously underestimated this :

<ul>
<li>because of the previous point</li>
<li>because on a side project, you&rsquo;ll be on your own to handle any infra issue</li>
<li>because you don&rsquo;t have 8 hours per day to spend to your project (As a professional developer, dad of 2, I only managed to get 10 to 15 hours per week)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="/programming-as-an-exponential-problem/">A small project does not require as much infrastructure as a big one</a>. I lost some time doing things as I do when working on projects with more than 100K lines of code. So next time :

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll stick to end to end cucumber tests for as long as possible</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ll use an economical framework like described in <a href="http://www.amazon.fr/The-Principles-Product-Development-Flow/dp/1935401009">Donald G. Reinertsen&rsquo;s Flow book</a> to prioritize improvements vs features</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Eventually, what killed me was that I could not go around the &ldquo;experiment &ndash;> adapt&rdquo; loop fast enough. The project was just too big for my time

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll try to select a subject a project that suits my constraints of time and money</li>
<li>This will be one of the first hypotheses that I&rsquo;m willing to verify</li>
<li>Web marketing and HTML design are more important than coding skills to run experiments : I&rsquo;m learning both</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Scrapping is a time hog. I won&rsquo;t start any side project involving scrapping anymore.</li>
<li>Using on-line services always saved me a lot of time. They are a lot more reliable than anything I could setup. Mainly, this was :

<ul>
<li>Mailing services</li>
<li>Cloud deployment</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Go the standard way. Again, anytime I did something a bit weird, it turned out to cost me some time

<ul>
<li>Use standard open source software, stick to the latest version</li>
<li>Use standard and wide spread technology</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Automated testing and deployment saved me some time from the start. Especially with the small amount of time that I could spend on my project, it was really easy to forget details and to make mistakes.

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/philou/mes-courses/blob/master/lib/mes_courses/deployment.rb">Here</a> is the <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a> deployment script I used to test and deploy in a single shell call</li>
<li>And <a href="https://github.com/philou/mes-courses/blob/master/lib/mes_courses/utils/scheduled_tasks.rb">here</a> is a Heroku workaround to run some cron tasks weekly, this allowed me to run some scrapping tests every week on Heroku</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>It took all my time ! Next time I start a side project, I&rsquo;ll be prepared to

<ul>
<li>Spend all my free time on it (my time was divided between day-job, family, side project)</li>
<li>Spend all my learning time (books, on-line trainings &hellip;) for it</li>
<li>Choose something that I am passionate about !</li>
<li>Choose a different kind of project to fit my constraints

<ul>
<li>Joining an existing open source project would let me focus on technical work at my own pace</li>
<li>Volunteer for a not for profit project might be less time intensive while allowing some fulfilment</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I did my project alone, and it was hard to keep my motivation high on the long run. Next time :

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll join someone else</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ll <a href="/my-own-side-project-best-practices-after-reading-the-side-project-book/">time box my project</a> before a pivot or starting something completely different</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I did not manage to get anything done before I settled a regular daily rhythm. I used to work from 5:30am to 7:30am, I first tried in the evening, but after a day&rsquo;s work, I was too tired to be really productive.</li>
<li>When I could afford it, paying for things or services really saved me some time. I&rsquo;m thinking of

<ul>
<li>A fast computer</li>
<li>Some paying on-line services</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>It is sure that doing a side project seriously is a heavy time investment, but there&rsquo;s also a lot of benefits !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-06-27-rip-mes-courses-dot-fr/side-projects-are-important.gif" title="Side projects are important blackboard" ></p>

<h3>Here is what I gained</h3>

<ul>
<li>Real experience with new technologies. For me, this included

<ul>
<li>Ruby on Rails</li>
<li>Coffeescript</li>
<li>HTML scrapping</li>
<li>Dev-ops practices with Heroku</li>
<li>Web design with HTML and CSS</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I also learned a lot of non technical skills in which I was completely inexperienced

<ul>
<li>Web marketing</li>
<li>Blogging</li>
<li>Mailing</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Trying to bootstrap a for profit side project is like running a micro company, it&rsquo;s a good opportunity to understand how a company is ran. This can help you to become a better professional during your day-job.</li>
<li>Having control on everything is a good situation to use Lean techniques.

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Lean-Startup-Entrepreneurs-Continuous/dp/0307887898/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1404024050&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=lean+startup">Lean Start-up</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Principles-Product-Development-Flow/dp/1935401009/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1404024094&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=reinersten">Lean product development (Donald G. Reinertsen)</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Failing allowed me to actually understand Lean Start up ! The ideas are easy to understand in theory, the practice is a very different thing. It should help me for my next project.</li>
<li>Resolving real problems on my own was a very good source for valuable blog articles.</li>
<li>I collaborated with very clever people on open source libraries

<ul>
<li>By fixing some bugs in some libraries I was using</li>
<li>By releasing some parts of my code as open source libraries</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Next time, I hope I&rsquo;ll get more euros as well !</p>

<p>You&rsquo;ve got nothing to loose from trying ! Just do it. Give yourself 1 year to get some small success, and then continue or repeat with something else !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
