<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: book | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/book/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-16T20:07:49+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Flow book summary (lean software development part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-29T06:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Principles-Product-Development-Flow/dp/1935401009">The principles of product development flow</a> from Donald G. Reinertsen.</p>

<p>{% img center /imgs/2014-08-29-the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/flow_book_cover.jpg The cover of the book %}</p>

<p>I read it both for work and for my side projects, and I think it will be useful for both. The book is about lean product development, and is in fact a collection of 175 lean principles that one can study and understand in order to make better decisions when developing new products. The principles are divided into the following 8 categories</p>

<ol>
<li>Economics</li>
<li>Queues</li>
<li>Variability</li>
<li>Batch sise</li>
<li>WIP constraints</li>
<li>Cadence, synchronization and flow control</li>
<li>Fast feedback</li>
<li>Decentralized control</li>
</ol>


<p>I really loved the book. I have not been thrilled like that by a book since <a href="http://www.threeriversinstitute.org/">Kent Beck</a>&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0201616416">1st edition of Extreme Programming Explained</a>. Where Kent Beck described some values, principles and practices that work. D.G. Reinertsen has the ambition to help us to quantify these practices in order not move from belief based to fact based decisions. For this, he gives us the keys to creating an economical framework with which we should be able to convert any change option to its economical cost</p>

<p>{% img center /imgs/2014-08-29-the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/xp_book_cover.jpg The cover of the book &ldquo;Extreme Programming Explained&rdquo; %}</p>

<p>Lately, I&rsquo;ve been thinking of an economical framework of my own, that I could use on the projects I am currently involved in. This post is the first of a series about this :</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1">The Flow book summary</a></li>
<li><a href="/why-extreme-programming-works-lean-software-development-part-2/">Why eXtreme Programming works ?</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to-measure-your-speed-with-your-business-value-lean-software-development-part-3/">How to measure your speed with your business value ?</a></li>
<li><a href="/measure-the-business-value-of-your-spikes-and-take-high-payoff-risks-lean-software-development-part-4/">Measure the business value of your spikes and take high payoff risks</a></li>
<li><a href="/what-optimization-should-we-work-on-lean-software-development-part-5/">What optimization should we work on ?</a></li>
<li>Measure the value of the lean startup &lsquo;learning&rsquo;</li>
<li>Prioritizing technical improvements</li>
<li>Summing it up for my next side project</li>
</ol>


<p>Next part will feature an explanation of the XP practices with the lean principles. Stay tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My own side project best practices after reading the 'Side Project Book']]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-own-side-project-best-practices-after-reading-the-side-project-book/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-25T07:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-own-side-project-best-practices-after-reading-the-side-project-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First, i recommend <a href="http://sideprojectbook.com/">this book</a> to any side project infected person : it&rsquo;s a great motivation boost !</p>

<p>After reading it, it seems that there are no absolute rules to side projects success. Some did no marketting and just did what they loved, others did à carefull market study before building anything, some did the whole things, others outsourced the code or the design, or even both &hellip; That said, as I read somewhere, it seems that one is more likely to achieve commercial success if he first focusses on the market, then marketting, then the design, and eventually on the features.</p>

<p>Common advices from the interviewees are :</p>

<ul>
<li>ship early</li>
<li>iterate</li>
<li>don&rsquo;t give up</li>
</ul>


<p>Why not apply these principle to &ldquo;building a side project&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;building XXX in my free time&rdquo; ?</p>

<p>From now on, I am going to set up project target duration and revenue. For example, if I don&rsquo;t make at least 100€ / month after one year, I&rsquo;ll stop working on it and start a new one.</p>

<p>I hope that by iterating more quickly through projects I&rsquo;ll learn more and increase my chances of successes as the time goes. Keeping the same target duration and revenue for all projects should make me better at filtering ideas that are a good fit to my resources. As I tend to get bored quickly, it should also allow me to keep my motivation high.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s see what happens !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
