<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: book | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/book/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-03T20:10:38+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How To Keep Up With Software Technologies]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-30T04:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I started to program professionally 15 years ago, a lot of things have changes. A lot of technologies appeared and became mainstream while others fell out of fashion.</p>

<p>As software developers, it is really challenging to stay fit and productive in new technologies. I cannot obviously say that I am an expert in all new technologies, but I can say that I can get up to speed in a pretty short time in nearly all.</p>

<p>If there is a single reason for that I strongly believe it is because &ldquo;I studied my classics&rdquo; !</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/outdated.jpg" title="An outdated computed covered in spider webs" ></p>

<h2>How does it work</h2>

<p>At the same time I started to program all day long for my living, I also started to read a lot of programming books on my spare time. This allowed me to learn at night and practice at day, setting everything in my brain.</p>

<p>This might come as a surprise, but I never read a lot of books about the technologies I was using. I&rsquo;d rather study fundamental programming books. These contain a lot of transportable knowledge, unlike in most books about a particular technology.</p>

<p>I believe this is a pretty good use of time since it made me a better programmer and also greatly reduced the time I need to master most new technologies. I can now easily relate them to some more general concept I learned before.</p>

<p>For example, I never read a book about UI. By the time I had to do some UI programming, I had absolutely no issue getting up to speed on the topic. I had already seen quite some UI code examples in other books, I knew that most UI frameworks are built from a set of Object Oriented patterns. Coming from a different perspective, I was even able to suggest improvements to the code that UI experts had not thought of.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s not to say that I never read books about a particular technology, sometimes, that&rsquo;s just what you need to start something new. But when I do, I usually find them quite easy to read and digest. And I tend to skip things I intuitively understand and use them as cookbooks containing recipes for particular problems rather than end to end walk-through.</p>

<h2>My books</h2>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Programmer-Journeyman-Master/dp/020161622X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666382&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+pragmatic+programmer">The Pragmatic Programmer: From Journeyman to Master</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Programmer-Journeyman-Master/dp/020161622X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666382&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+pragmatic+programmer"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/the-pragmatic-programmer.jpg" title="Cover of the pragmatic programmer book" ></a></p>

<p>As a young programmer this book made me understand that my job was not only about writing code, but about building maintainable systems. It provided me with tools to do so, 10 years later, I can still remember &ldquo;The power of plain text&rdquo;. This is also the book that made me have a first look into Ruby :).</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666776&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=refactoring+improving+the+design+of+existing+code">Refactoring: Improving the Design of Existing Code</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Code/dp/0201485672/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666776&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=refactoring+improving+the+design+of+existing+code"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/refactoring.jpg" title="Cover of the refactoring book" ></a></p>

<p>Here is the theory behind all automated IDE refactorings. Reading this book had a profound influence on my coding style. The examples made me understand the difference between readable and unreadable code &hellip; It&rsquo;s also the foundation for any kind of incremental design and architecture. That&rsquo;s the book that got me started with TDD.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666833&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design+eric+evans">Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Domain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software/dp/0321125215/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666833&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=domain+driven+design+eric+evans"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/ddd.jpg" title="Cover of the DDD book" ></a></p>

<p>This book teaches good object oriented programming. Some say it is tough to read, but it&rsquo;s definitely worth doing so. Among other things, it explains how to use functional programming concept in your object oriented project, by separating Value Objects and Entities for example.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Programming-Language-Brian-W-Kernighan/dp/0131103628/ref=pd_sim_14_2?ie=UTF8&amp;dpID=41qX6YdIJ7L&amp;dpSrc=sims&amp;preST=_AC_UL160_SR122%2C160_&amp;refRID=035C81Y95A0A1C6K25F6">The C Programming Language</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Programming-Language-Brian-W-Kernighan/dp/0131103628/ref=pd_sim_14_2?ie=UTF8&amp;dpID=41qX6YdIJ7L&amp;dpSrc=sims&amp;preST=_AC_UL160_SR122%2C160_&amp;refRID=035C81Y95A0A1C6K25F6"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/c.jpg" title="Cover of the C book" ></a></p>

<p>With around 250 pages, it&rsquo;s pretty difficult to find a programming book with a greater value/page ratio. This one will teach you all there is to learn about C, and help you understand everything that was built on top of C (and that&rsquo;s quite a lot &hellip;)</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Structure-Interpretation-Computer-Programs-Engineering/dp/0262510871/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666981&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=sicp">Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Structure-Interpretation-Computer-Programs-Engineering/dp/0262510871/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464666981&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=sicp"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/sicp.jpg" title="Cover of the SICP book" ></a></p>

<p>Compared to C, Lisp is at the other side of the language spectrum. Learning C and Lisp gives the ability to put nearly anything in contrast to these 2 languages. Lisp is dynamic, functional and meta. It can be morphed into nearly anything and SICP teaches how to do so. There&rsquo;s a Lisp practice that is invaluable to any programmer : use your language to express your problem as simply as possible. SICP teaches that.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Programming-Erlang-Concurrent-Pragmatic-Programmers/dp/193778553X/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464667113&amp;sr=1-2&amp;keywords=erlang+programming">Programming Erlang: Software for a Concurrent World</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Programming-Erlang-Concurrent-Pragmatic-Programmers/dp/193778553X/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1464667113&amp;sr=1-2&amp;keywords=erlang+programming"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-05-30-how-to-keep-up-with-software-technologies/erlang.jpg" title="Cover of the Erlang book" ></a></p>

<p>Neither the C book nor SICP deals with distribution and concurrency. That&rsquo;s what this book does. I had never programmed distributed systems before reading this book. After I read it, I learned how to code for distribution in a maintainable way. The lessons taught by Erlang are applicable in many languages.</p>

<h2>Not the best books</h2>

<p>I did not and will never read all programming books available. There might be newer books that treat the same subjects better, but these books are the ones that taught me the most about our craft. My point is that learning fundamentals and things far away from our daily technologies will teach us more.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Are Most Agile Teams Doing Continuous Improvement The Silly Way ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-06T07:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, as I was looking the internet for Lean principles to improve our way of working, I fell upon this book <a href="leanagilecamp.fr">Petit guide de management lean a l'usage des équipes agiles</a> (NB: the book is in French, the title means &lsquo;Little lean management guide at the usage of agile teams&rsquo;). It made me think and I thought it deserved a blog post.</p>

<p><a href="http://leanagilecamp.fr"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-06-are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way/cover.svg" title="The book cover" ></a></p>

<p>It explains that agility can be though of as a set of practices and principles, shared through a huge community. This makes it a great production system, where improvement are mostly brought by gut feeling retrospectives and trial of other teams practices. At the contrary, Lean is very light framework for continuous improvement, relying on a more systematic waste elimination.</p>

<p>After this introduction, the bulk of the book is composed of a set of 9 detailed real life stories demonstrating the lean way of bringing improvements. Are is a summary of 3 of these :</p>

<h2><a href="http://leanagilecamp.fr/guide.html#sc%C3%A8ne-de-crime-la-cat%C3%A9gorie-myst%C3%A8re-du-projet-condor">Unknown Category at Project Condor</a></h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-06-are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way/condor.jpg" title="Issue indicators" ></p>

<p>The team maintains a virtual call center of poor quality, resulting in lots of incidents in production. Here is how they deal with the situation :</p>

<ol>
<li>They start by showing the issues, by categorizing them from the logs, they discover that they are mainly related to training, network, but surprisingly, the majority (30%) cannot be categorized and fall in the &lsquo;unknown&rsquo; category.</li>
<li>By improving logging, the unknown category falls to 5% ! Fixing network timeout issues then makes the client a lot happier.</li>
<li><p>Eventually, they go to client&rsquo;s site while monitoring the logs at the same time. They discover that remaining issues are explained by</p>

<ul>
<li>some users are using a double click to hack the system and jump ahead of the queue</li>
<li>the hang up and hang off buttons being too close, which results in operator misleadingly ending their communication</li>
<li>calls to wrong numbers being logged as incidents</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<p>The authors conclude that while uncomfortable, going to the clients increased motivation for everyone, fixed issues and made the client happier.</p>

<h2><a href="http://leanagilecamp.fr/guide.html#sc%C3%A8ne-de-crime-tous-coupables">All Guilty !</a></h2>

<p>An author is called to help a team which is working on unifying reimbursement systems after a merge. The project is late and the product is unreliable.</p>

<p>The first step he takes is to visualize a target (next batch in 3 months) and the flow</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-06-are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way/target.jpg" title="Details of the 3 months target" ></p>

<p>The flow whiteboard shows that tasks get stuck when in need of clarifications from business analysts. Tension between people is already increasing. They Team decides to visualize this with &lsquo;blocker&rsquo; post-its.</p>

<p>After an inquire with the BAs, it turns out that they don&rsquo;t see the waiting tasks the issue management software.</p>

<p>The final step is to agree all together (developers and BAs) on an uniform way of defining and following blocking issues</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-06-are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way/blockers.jpg" title="The shared blocked issues follow up wall board" ></p>

<p>Tickets are discussed at the stand-up, and unblocked issues are also visualized. As a result in only 2 weeks, the process fluidifies, and the tensions decrease.</p>

<p>The authors conclude that cross functional teams work better</p>

<h2><a href="http://leanagilecamp.fr/guide.html#sc%C3%A8ne-de-crime-joue-la-courte-et-pr%C3%A9cise">PDCA</a></h2>

<p>This story starts in a rather typical way : the client would like the team to go faster.</p>

<p>The team engages into a series of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDCA">Plan Do Check Act</a> cycles.</p>

<h3>Hypothesis 1 : There must be some obvious waste</h3>

<p>The team decides to log any waste occurring for 2 weeks. Even with discipline, only 2 hours are spotted during the 60 man.days of the sprint</p>

<h3>Hypothesis 2 : Too much refactoring or too much test writing</h3>

<p>For a few weeks, the authors keeps a daily log of the team activities during after every stand-up meeting.</p>

<p>It turns out that writing tests accounts for 5,5% of the time, refactoring for only 2% but programming for 40% !</p>

<h3>Hypothesis 3 : if there is something to improve, it must be in programming.</h3>

<p>For 20 half days, the author embarks on the tedious task of keeping a very detailed log of activities while taking the role of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pair_programming#Remote_pair_programming">navigator</a> in pair programming sessions.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-06-are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way/log.jpg" title="The detailed log of programming activities" >
<img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-03-06-are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way/activities.jpg" title="Ratio of different programming activities" ></p>

<p>They clearly understand that most time is taken not in writing tests, doing refactoring or writing complicated code, but in understanding existing code, third-parties and APIs</p>

<h3>Aftermath</h3>

<p>First, they avoided loosing time on improving the wrong thing
The team also agreed on the practice of asking for help at the good person when starting stories. Doing that, they got a nearly 100% speed boost !</p>

<h2>The rest of the book</h2>

<p>The book highlights a lot of other continuous improvement practices. For example :</p>

<ul>
<li>The &lsquo;problem box&rsquo; where team members can log any waste they are going through during their work. This made me think of my <a href="/a-plan-for-technical-debt-lean-software-development-part-7/">Plan For Technical Debt</a></li>
<li>Individual improvement follow up : a single team member is responsible to drive an improvement to its conclusion, in order to make sure that it is not forgotten</li>
</ul>


<p>I personally found this book to be just great ! It&rsquo;s short and focused, pragmatic, and a pretty easy read. If you liked <a href="http://www.infoq.com/minibooks/scrum-xp-from-the-trenches-2">Scrum and XP from the trenches</a> I think you should read it. More generally, I think it&rsquo;s very useful for anyone involved in the development process who would like to push agility a little further.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a catch though, it&rsquo;s in french ! I guess I could take the time to translate it, tell me if you are interested.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Flow book summary (lean software development part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-29T06:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Principles-Product-Development-Flow/dp/1935401009">The principles of product development flow</a> from Donald G. Reinertsen.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-08-29-the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/flow_book_cover.jpg" title="The cover of the book" ></p>

<p>I read it both for work and for my side projects, and I think it will be useful for both. The book is about lean product development, and is in fact a collection of 175 lean principles that one can study and understand in order to make better decisions when developing new products. The principles are divided into the following 8 categories</p>

<ol>
<li>Economics</li>
<li>Queues</li>
<li>Variability</li>
<li>Batch sise</li>
<li>WIP constraints</li>
<li>Cadence, synchronization and flow control</li>
<li>Fast feedback</li>
<li>Decentralized control</li>
</ol>


<p>I really loved the book. I have not been thrilled like that by a book since <a href="http://www.threeriversinstitute.org/">Kent Beck</a>&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0201616416">1st edition of Extreme Programming Explained</a>. Where Kent Beck described some values, principles and practices that work. D.G. Reinertsen has the ambition to help us to quantify these practices in order not move from belief based to fact based decisions. For this, he gives us the keys to creating an economical framework with which we should be able to convert any change option to its economical cost</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2014-08-29-the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1/xp_book_cover.jpg" title="The cover of the book &ldquo;Extreme Programming Explained&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Lately, I&rsquo;ve been thinking of an economical framework of my own, that I could use on the projects I am currently involved in. This post is the first of a series about this :</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="/the-flow-book-summary-lean-software-development_part_1">The Flow book summary</a></li>
<li><a href="/why-extreme-programming-works-lean-software-development-part-2/">Why eXtreme Programming works ?</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to-measure-your-speed-with-your-business-value-lean-software-development-part-3/">How to measure your speed with your business value ?</a></li>
<li><a href="/measure-the-business-value-of-your-spikes-and-take-high-payoff-risks-lean-software-development-part-4/">Measure the business value of your spikes and take high payoff risks</a></li>
<li><a href="/what-optimization-should-we-work-on-lean-software-development-part-5/">What optimization should we work on ?</a></li>
<li><a href="/you-dont-have-to-ask-your-boss-for-a-fast-build-lean-software-development-part-6/">You don&rsquo;t have to ask your boss for a fast build</a></li>
<li><a href="/a-plan-for-technical-debt-lean-software-development-part-7/">A Plan for Technical Debt</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-ill-measure-the-lean-startup-value-of-information-in-my-next-side-project-lean-software-development-part-8/">How I&rsquo;ll Measure the Lean Startup Value of Information in My Next Side Project</a></li>
<li><a href="/my-dream-lean-software-development-tool-lean-software-development-part-9/">My Dream Lean Software Development Tool</a></li>
</ol>


<p>Next part will feature an explanation of the XP practices with the lean principles. Stay tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My own side project best practices after reading the 'Side Project Book']]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-own-side-project-best-practices-after-reading-the-side-project-book/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-25T07:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/my-own-side-project-best-practices-after-reading-the-side-project-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First, i recommend <a href="http://sideprojectbook.com/">this book</a> to any side project infected person : it&rsquo;s a great motivation boost !</p>

<p>After reading it, it seems that there are no absolute rules to side projects success. Some did no marketting and just did what they loved, others did à carefull market study before building anything, some did the whole things, others outsourced the code or the design, or even both &hellip; That said, as I read somewhere, it seems that one is more likely to achieve commercial success if he first focusses on the market, then marketting, then the design, and eventually on the features.</p>

<p>Common advices from the interviewees are :</p>

<ul>
<li>ship early</li>
<li>iterate</li>
<li>don&rsquo;t give up</li>
</ul>


<p>Why not apply these principle to &ldquo;building a side project&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;building XXX in my free time&rdquo; ?</p>

<p>From now on, I am going to set up project target duration and revenue. For example, if I don&rsquo;t make at least 100€ / month after one year, I&rsquo;ll stop working on it and start a new one.</p>

<p>I hope that by iterating more quickly through projects I&rsquo;ll learn more and increase my chances of successes as the time goes. Keeping the same target duration and revenue for all projects should make me better at filtering ideas that are a good fit to my resources. As I tend to get bored quickly, it should also allow me to keep my motivation high.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s see what happens !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
