<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: zero-bugs-series | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/zero-bugs-series/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-12-14T06:38:18+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why and how to start a #ZeroBugs policy - part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2017-12-14T10:40:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second post of a <a href="/blog/categories/zero-bugs-series/">series about the #ZeroBugs policy</a>. In the <a href="/why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-1/">previous post</a>, I detailed what a <a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/no_bugs.html">#ZeroBugs</a> policy is and how we tried to apply it. I encourage you start <a href="/why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-1/">there</a>.</p>

<p>Here is a quick summary of where we stood. We had tried to apply a #ZeroBugs policy with exploratory testing. We had discovered a lot of bugs, and we had agreed to tackle them little by little. We hoped to finish in a few months.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-11-22-why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-2/bug-panic.jpg" alt="The Bug Panic game" /></p>

<h2>The final bug rules</h2>

<p>At about the same time, we started an improvement kata to increase our productivity. I wrote in details about <a href="/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/">the full story</a>, but to make it short, here is what we discovered :</p>

<ul>
<li>It would take us years, not months to fix all our bugs</li>
<li>Our definition for bugs was part of the problem</li>
</ul>


<p>After some experimentation, here is the bug definition we came up with :</p>

<ul>
<li>It corrupts data</li>
<li>It returns wrong results</li>
<li>It crashes with an unexpected error message</li>
</ul>


<p>It stopped scope creep by removing the subjective &ldquo;it used to work&rdquo; rule. This rule also sped up bug fixing a lot. We closed many bugs with descriptive error messages.</p>

<h2>Consequences</h2>

<p>Within 2 sprints, we reached a #ZeroBugs state. Backlog &lsquo;management&rsquo; was simpler as it did not contain bugs anymore. We were also spending less time fixing bugs and more building stories. Even as we resumed our intense exploratory testing sessions, our bug backlog did not grow.</p>

<p>After a while, we discovered other benefits to the #ZeroBugs policy.</p>

<p>Spending less time on bugs made our velocity more stable. Our product owner was happier to see us deliver new features more reliably. In the end, this improved our relationship with him. </p>

<blockquote><p>💡 #ZeroBugs policy makes developers happier</p></blockquote>

<p>It also made the team happier. First, because we had a lot less of stressful emergencies to answer to. Second, because programming new features is more interesting than fixing bugs.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-11-22-why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-2/happy-developer.jpg" alt="A relaxed developer" /></p>

<p>It also made the other teams happier and more productive ! They encountered a lot less bugs when using our product. When they had problems, they usually got a clear error message. They would fix it on their side, or suggest us a new feature.</p>

<p>A #ZeroBugs policy and exploratory testing also have a side effect on technical debt ! Bugs tend to appear in the more brittle parts of the code. When fixing bugs, you took the opportunity to refactor technical debt at the same time.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 #ZeroBugs policy reduces technical debt</p></blockquote>

<p>Finally, having a definition for bugs was very helpful. It allowed decentralized prioritization of bugs. The alternative to that is to have a domain expert available to sort bugs from stories. A decentralized rule prevents all sort of coordination and people issues. Our system was rather technical, which made it easy to define what a bug is. In other cases, it might be worth spending some time with the domain expert to define similar rules.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Use decision rules to decentralize economic control.&rdquo; From <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Principles-Product-Development-Flow-Generation-ebook/dp/B007TKU0O0/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1511344068&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=reinertsen+flow">Principles of Product Development Flow</a> by <a href="http://reinertsenassociates.com/">Donald G. Reinertsen</a></p></blockquote>

<p>To summarize, sticking to #ZeroBugs is a win-win and sustainable situation for all.</p>

<h2>Next week</h2>

<p>This was part 2 of a <a href="/blog/categories/zero-bugs-series/">series of posts about the #ZeroBugs policy</a>. In next week&rsquo;s post, I&rsquo;ll provide a step by step guide about how to inject a #ZeroBugs policy in your team.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why and how to start a #ZeroBugs policy - part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2017-12-07T10:22:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some teams spend 95% of their development time fixing bugs &hellip; An entrepreneur I worked with reported an even scarier story. He went bankrupt because bugs were taking <em>all</em> the development time. He had no time left for new features !</p>

<p>At the other end of the spectrum, some <a href="http://leanagilepartners.com/library/Vanschooenderwoert-EmbeddedNumbers.pdf">eXtreme Programming teams</a> reported bug rates as low as 1.5 per month !</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Some XP teams reported bug rates as low as 1.5 per month !</p></blockquote>

<p>Wouldn&rsquo;t it be great for everyone if we had less bugs to fix ? Programmers would do more interesting work. Business people would get more valuable features. People would do less overtime. All this while users get a better product !</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-11-22-why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-1/aim-bug.jpg" alt="A bug in a viewfinder" /></p>

<p>Last year, in my team, we reached and maintained a #ZeroBugs state. Here is how we did it.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s the <a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/no_bugs.html">#ZeroBugs</a> policy</h2>

<p>Before we jump into our story, let&rsquo;s take a second to understand what this is all about.</p>

<p>Bugs waste time. They waste the time of users, who can&rsquo;t do what they need. They waste everyone&rsquo;s time with interruptions from unhappy user. They steal time from new features development. If you have a large number of known bugs, you&rsquo;ll also waste some time organizing them : eliminating duplicates, prioritizing them, ignoring others &hellip;</p>

<p>A #ZeroBugs policy is the convention of having no bugs in your backlog. This means that when someone finds a defect, it should be immediately :</p>

<ul>
<li>fixed before any other feature</li>
<li>prioritized as a new story</li>
<li>or ignored (for the moment)</li>
</ul>


<p>Obviously, the less bug you create the easier this will be.</p>

<h2>Our journey to a #ZeroBugs policy</h2>

<h3>Context</h3>

<p>We were an R&amp;D team, building a data management system. Our product was moving outside of pure research and development. Other teams were starting to use it and often reported bugs back to us.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;d first read about #ZeroBugs in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Art-Agile-Development-Pragmatic-Software/dp/0596527675/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1511342870&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+agile">The Art of Agile Software Development</a>. Given enough automated testing, XP teams could almost stop doing bug fixing !</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Art-Agile-Development-Pragmatic-Software/dp/0596527675/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1511342870&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+art+of+agile"><img src="../imgs/2017-11-22-why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-1/art-of-agile.jpg" alt="Cover of the book &quot;The Art of Agile Software Development&quot;" /></a></p>

<p>As we had very solid automated testing in place, we decided to take the extra steps to save time on bug fixing.</p>

<h3>First attempt</h3>

<p>There is a straightforward way to install a #ZeroBugs policy. Make sure to have a customer or a Product Owner to prioritize defects as soon as they appear (check <a href="https://medium.com/quality-functions/the-zero-bug-policy-b0bd987be684">this story</a> for an example).</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this would not work for us. Our Product Owner was great at providing us with a long term vision. He could not be available for day to day bug prioritization though.</p>

<p>Our first try was to propose a definition for bugs that we could use ourselves to classify them. We decided that something was a bug if either of the following was true :</p>

<ul>
<li>It corrupts data.</li>
<li>It returns wrong results. As we were building a data management system, this was rather easy to verify.</li>
<li>It used to work but is now broken</li>
</ul>


<p>Whenever we found an issue meeting any of these points, we would start working on it straightaway.</p>

<blockquote><p>💡 Exploratory testing goes hand in hand with #ZeroBugs policy</p></blockquote>

<p>To speed up downstream integration of our product by other teams, we also <a href="/how-we-started-exploratory-testing/">started Exploratory Testing</a>. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exploratory_testing">Exploratory testing</a> is a practice that goes hand in hand with a #ZeroBugs policy.</p>

<h3>Unearthing a bug debt</h3>

<p>During the first exploratory testing session, we found more than 10 bugs. We thought that with a bit of focus we could fix all lingering bugs in a few weeks max &hellip; After 2 other sessions and more than one sprint of intense bug fixing, we had even unearthed more bugs. We were wrong, this would take a lot more than a few weeks.</p>

<p>If we kept on our 1 hour exploratory testing sessions every sprint, we would fill our backlog with bugs. We would also be fixing bugs for a few months before we could tackle any new feature !</p>

<p>We agreed on the following strategy to fix all these bugs little by little :</p>

<ul>
<li>stop these intense exploratory testing sessions</li>
<li>do shorter exploratory testing sessions at the end of every story</li>
<li>fix 5 to 6 bugs every sprint</li>
</ul>


<p>We hoped to fix all our bugs in a few months.</p>

<h2>Next week</h2>

<p>That was the first part of <a href="/blog/categories/zero-bugs-series/">a series of posts about #ZeroBugs policy</a>. In the <a href="/why-and-how-to-start-a-number-zerobugs-policy-part-2/">next post</a>, I&rsquo;ll explain how we dealt with this bug debt and dig into the consequences it had on our work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
