<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: continuous improvement | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/continuous-improvement/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-14T06:39:07+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How we used the improvement kata to gain 25% of productivity - Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-12T09:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/">previous post</a>, I described the productivity issue our team was facing. How retrospectives did not work, and how I started looking at the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">improvement kata</a>.</p>

<p>We had gone through the first phase of the improvement kata : set the end goal.</p>

<blockquote><p>Generating enough profit for the business while sticking to a sustainable pace.</p></blockquote>

<p>Time to start the second phase : Understand.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/question-light.jpeg" alt="Drawing of a question mark transforming into a light bulb" /></p>

<h2>Understand</h2>

<p>Where we really slower ? Or was it an illusion ?</p>

<p>When trying to understand, you have to start with the data you have. You continue digging until you get a deeper understanding of the situation.</p>

<h3>Velocity</h3>

<p>We started with available data : story points and velocity. For sure this is a pretty bad measure of productivity. (Note : we should never use velocity for performance appraisal) In our case though, it felt like a good starting proxy measure.</p>

<p>Here is our velocity curve over 2 years.</p>

<p><a href="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity.jpg"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity-small.jpg" alt="Velocity graph" /></a></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s obvious that something changed. There are 2 parts to this graph. The velocity dropped between sprint 54 and 16.01. That&rsquo;s a clue that our gut feeling was not completely wrong. Our productivity did change.</p>

<h3>Man days</h3>

<p>Our first hypothesis was that team members turnover was the cause. As with any team, some people came, and some people left. Let&rsquo;s superpose the man days and velocity curves.</p>

<p><a href="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity-vs-manpower.jpg"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/velocity-vs-manpower-small.jpg" alt="Velocity vs Manpower graph" /></a></p>

<p>That could only explain <em>part</em> of the problem !</p>

<p>We tried to fine tune the man days curve. We took people&rsquo;s involvement in tasks outside of programming into account. We used coefficients depending on the developers' experience. That did not provide a better explanation.</p>

<p>We had to find another explanation.</p>

<h3>Velocity computation</h3>

<p>As I said earlier, velocity is not a measure of productivity. Any change in the way we were computing velocity would impact this curve.</p>

<p>We had kept photos and Trello boards of our <a href="/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">retrospectives meetings</a>. We searched them through for anything that could impact velocity. Here is what we found :</p>

<ul>
<li>At sprint 55, we decided to ditch the <a href="https://www.scrum.org/resources/deadly-disease-focus-factor">focus-factor</a></li>
<li>At sprint 61, we started to do regular <a href="/how-we-started-exploratory-testing/">exploratory-testing</a>. Exploratory testing discovers more bugs on top of user reported bugs. This made us spend more time on fixing bugs.</li>
<li>At sprint 62, as we opted for a <a href="https://medium.com/quality-functions/the-zero-bug-policy-b0bd987be684">No Bug policy</a> we decided not to count story points for bugs</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>💡Keep Photos and Trello boards of Retrospectives as a log of your working agreements changes</p></blockquote>

<p>The timings almost perfectly matched what we had observed in the first place. The question that came to our minds was :</p>

<blockquote><p>Are we spending too much time on bugs ?</p></blockquote>

<h2>Halfway through understanding</h2>

<p>This is how we started to dig into our situation. It&rsquo;s a good time to give you a bit of feedback about how we felt at that point.</p>

<p>It was the first time we tried the improvement kata. More than that, we did not find any tutorial or guides about how to run it. The only instructions we had were theoretical descriptions or super concrete examples. We had to bridge the gap and come up with our own way.</p>

<p>To summarize, we felt a bit lost, we had gathered data from here and there, and we did not know what to look at next. On top of that, the quality of the data we were collecting was not great. We were wondering if we would get anything out of these investigations.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/First-20-Hours-Learn-Anything/dp/1591846943/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1483258282&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+first+20+hours"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-12-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/the-first-20-hours.jpg" alt="The cover of the book 'The First 20 Hours'" /></a></p>

<p>It felt a bit like when I did the <a href="/how-i-got-my-feet-wet-with-machine-learning-with-the-first-20-hours/">20 hours experiment to learn anything</a>. We did exactly what had worked with the learning experiment : we pushed through !</p>

<blockquote><p>💡If you feel lost when doing something for the first time. Push through !</p></blockquote>

<p>In <a href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-3/">next week&rsquo;s post</a>, I&rsquo;ll continue to detail the &lsquo;understand&rsquo; phase. <a href="/blog/categories/first-improvement-kata-series/">The series</a> also gained an extra post, and will now be 5 posts long.</p>

<p>See you next week.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How we used the improvement kata to gain 25% of productivity - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-07T06:39:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are serious about continuous improvement, you should learn the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">improvement kata</a>.</p>

<p><a href="/blog/categories/retrospectives/">Retrospectives</a> are great to pick all the low hanging improvements. Once you&rsquo;ve caught up with the industry&rsquo;s best practices, retrospectives risk drying up. Untapped improvement opportunities likely still exist in your specific context. The improvement kata can find those.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-09-07-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/low-hanging-fruits.jpeg" alt="Low and high hangling fruits on a tree" /></p>

<p>Here is how we applied the improvement kata to gain 25% of productivity in my previous team.</p>

<h2>The Situation</h2>

<p>Thanks to repeated retrospectives, the team had been improving for 2 years. Retrospectives seemed like a silver bullet. We would discuss the current problems, grasp an underlying cause and pick a best practice. Most of the time, that fixed the problem.</p>

<p>Sometimes it did not work though. Even if the issue came back in a later retrospective, it would not survive a second scrutiny. In the previous two years, the team had transformed the way it worked. It adopted TDD, incremental refactoring, pair programming, remote work, automated performance testing and many others.</p>

<p>Lately though, things did not work so well. The team was struggling with productivity issues. The team was not slowing down, but the scope and complexity of the product had grown. Features were not getting out of the door as fast as they used to. We had the habit of prioritizing improvements and bug fixes over features. That used to improve the flow enough to get more and more feature done. It did not seem to work anymore.</p>

<p>We tried to tackle the issue in retrospectives. We would change the way we prioritized features &hellip; To be later bogged down by bugs, technical debt or bad tools. We would discuss that in retrospective, and decide to change the priorities again &hellip; The loop went on and on a few times.</p>

<p>We were getting nowhere.</p>

<h2>The improvement kata </h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s why I started to look for other ways to do continuous improvement. I stumbled upon a book called <a href="http://leanagilecamp.fr/">Small Lean Management Guide for Agile Teams</a>. The book is in french, but I wrote an <a href="/are-most-agile-teams-doing-continuous-improvement-the-silly-way/">english review</a>. I fell in love with the way the authors dug into the hard data of how they worked to understand and fix their problems.</p>

<p>To learn more about this technique, I read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Toyota-Kata-Managing-Improvement-Adaptiveness/dp/0071635238/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1504758735&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=toyota+kata">Toyota Kata</a>. It details two management tools used at Toyota : the improvement and coaching katas. Some say these are Toyota&rsquo;s special weapon. <em>The</em> thing that grew them from a small shop to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automotive_industry">largest car manufacturer in the world</a>.</p>

<p>They are katas because they are routines. They must be re-execute many times. The <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html">improvement kata</a> should improve the flow of work. The <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Coaching_Kata.html">coaching kata</a> helps someone (or yourself) to learn the improvement kata. Every time we go through the kata, we also understand it better.</p>

<p>Here is how the improvement kata goes :</p>

<ol>
<li>Describe your end goal</li>
<li>Understand where you stand about this goal by measuring facts and data</li>
<li>Based on your end goal and the current situation, define where you&rsquo;d like to be in 3 months or less</li>
<li>Use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDCA">Plan-Do-Check-Act</a> to experiment your way to this new situation

<ol>
<li>Plan an experiment</li>
<li>Do this experiment</li>
<li>Check the results of this experiment</li>
<li>Act on these results. 

<ul>
<li>Either drop the experiment and plan a new one (go back to &lsquo;Plan&rsquo;).</li>
<li>Or spread the change at a larger scale.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>


<p><a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/Homepage.html"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-07-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/katapattern.jpg" alt="The Improvement Kata Pattern" /></a><div class="image-credits">Image from Mike Rother on <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/Homepage.html">Toyota Kata Website</a></div></p>

<p>The coaching kata is a way to coach someone into applying the improvement kata. The fun thing is that you can coach yourself ! The idea is to ask questions to the coachee to remind him of where he stands in his improvement kata.</p>

<p><a href="https://traccsolution.com/resources/coaching-infographic/"><img src="../imgs/2017-09-07-how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-1/The-coaching-Kata-questions.jpg" alt="The Coaching Kata Questions" /></a></p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll find tons of details and material about these katas on the <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/Homepage.html">Toyota Kata website</a>.</p>

<h2>Our end goal</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s how I started to apply the improvement kata in my team. I already had an idea of our end goal : to be more productive. To be more precise :</p>

<blockquote><p>Generating enough profit for the business while sticking to a sustainable pace.</p></blockquote>

<p>Retrospectives could not get us there. Would the improvement kata would succeed ?</p>

<p>This is the first part of a <a href="/blog/categories/first-improvement-kata-series/">series of 4 posts</a> relating our first use of the improvement kata. In the <a href="/how-we-used-the-improvement-kata-to-gain-25-percent-of-productivity-part-2/">next post</a>, I&rsquo;ll explain what we did to understand the current situation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Most Scrum teams are not agile]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-09T06:36:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being agile is about adapting to change and continuously improving. I&rsquo;ve seen (and been) in too many teams blindly following Scrum (<a href="/how-to-kill-scrum-zombies/">Scrum Zombies</a>) without figuring out how to continuous improve. The most obvious symptom is a boring (or no) retrospective.</p>

<p>Usually, it did not start that way, people had good intentions, and tried to follow the Scrum cookbook. Unfortunately, without any guidance or extreme perseverance, it is plain too easy to mess up the retrospective. If no concrete actions are scheduled at the end of the retro, if the same problems keep coming up at every retro, or if no problems at all are raised during the retro : your Scrum is somehow broken !</p>

<p>One of the promises of Scrum is to keep code quality high, in order to be able to adapt to late changes. Without a good retro to update the coding standards, the working agreements, or to spot and organize large scale refactoring, this will not happen.</p>

<p>One of the agile principle <a href="http://agilemanifesto.org/principles.html">explicitly states</a> the need for motivated team members. In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Drive-Surprising-Truth-About-Motivates/dp/1594484805/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494561757&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=pink+drive">Drive</a> Daniel Pink explains that one of the ingredient for motivation is autonomy. As a way to fix recurring problems, effective retrospectives will create autonomy, and enable motivation. Dysfunctional retros will slowly kill both &hellip;</p>

<p>Although continuous improvement at all levels is one of the most important element in your process, it needs a bit of practice to setup right. After trying different approach in different teams, I compiled a list of the things that worked for me :</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Drive-Surprising-Truth-About-Motivates/dp/1594484805/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494561757&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=pink+drive"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-09-most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/drive.jpg" alt="The cover of the Daniel Pink's &quot;Drive&quot; book" /></a></p>

<h2>How to do successful retrospectives</h2>

<h3>Start !</h3>

<p>Sounds obvious ! The first step is to schedule a recurring meeting and invite all the team. Someone should take care of facilitating. If you want to improve things, do this yourself at the beginning ! Once the practice is in place and everyone sees the benefits, you&rsquo;ll be able to get some help.</p>

<p><a href="/how-we-introduced-efficient-agile-retrospectives/">Here</a> is a crash-course about how to organize and drive your first retrospective. If your team is distributed, you&rsquo;ll need a slightly different setup. In my previous team, we had success using <a href="https://trello.com">Trello</a>, you can read more about it <a href="/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">here</a>.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-05-09-most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/just-do-it.jpg" alt="Just Do It picture" /></p>

<h3>Make sure everyone talks</h3>

<p>Retros should not be &ldquo;just-another-boring-meeting&rdquo; ! People should be excited to be there and to solve their recurring problems. I&rsquo;ve seen retros where no one would speak, as if there was absolutely nothing to improve ! I&rsquo;ve also been in retros where people raised collaboration issues, and came up with drastic improvements to the way they work, like adopting pair-programming for example.</p>

<p>There can be many reason why people don&rsquo;t speak : habit, organizational culture &hellip; Whatever the cause, if you show them the path, if you demonstrate that retro work and that it is safe to speak, you&rsquo;ll get them to participate.</p>

<p>Here are a few tricks to guide a team there :</p>

<ul>
<li>It is said that if someone does not speak in the first 5 minutes of a meeting, he&rsquo;ll remain silent for the rest. That&rsquo;s why <a href="www.funretrospectives.com/category/energizer/">energizers</a> work. They force everyone to participate to a Fun activity right from the start. <a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/">Fun Retrospective</a> contains a lot of engaging energizers.</li>
<li>Bring food ! Having food at work was one of Kent Beck&rsquo;s main advises in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0201616416/ref=sr_1_2?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494561932&amp;sr=1-2&amp;keywords=extreme+programming+explained+embrace+change">eXtreme Programming, Embrace Change</a>. Food is social and create a more relaxed and safer atmosphere.</li>
<li>Before you start the meeting, it might be useful to repeat the <a href="http://www.retrospectives.com/pages/retroPrimeDirective.html">Retrospective&rsquo;s Prime Directive</a>.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>Regardless of what we discover, we understand and truly believe that everyone did the best job they could, given what they knew at the time, their skills and abilities, the resources available, and the situation at hand.</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li>As the animator, you should make sure the discussions don&rsquo;t degenerate into some kind of trolling or blaming. If it&rsquo;s the case, remind that this is not the way the retro is meant to work. In worst case, give a 5 minutes break to everyone to calm down.</li>
<li>If needed, have a private discussion with people outside the retro to make sure that they understand the &ldquo;Blame the process, not the people&rdquo; principle of the retro well enough.</li>
</ul>


<p>Dealing with &ldquo;bad&rdquo; behavior in retros is a wide topic which I am only scratching the surface here. I guess I could write a full post about it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-09-most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/fun-retro.jpeg" alt="The cover of the &quot;Fun Retrospectives&quot; book" /></a></p>

<h3>Get out of with actionable tasks</h3>

<p>If you want a sure way to screw up your retros here it is : end the first one with no actionable things to do ! People will learn that it&rsquo;s a useless pscho-blabla meeting for agile softies.</p>

<p>This should be the absolute priority during the first retros. There are various kind of actionable tasks. Teams can adopt new conventions, decide to tackle some specific refactoring, or build a small new tool &hellip;</p>

<p>Actionable items should be small enough to be completed in one sprint. This is fine for refactoring a class, adding a <a href="https://www.sonarqube.org/">SonarQube</a> rule or asking for something from another team. What about larger tasks ? Suppose you just identified a large refactoring to do, how do you get started ? I know 2 strategies for that :</p>

<ul>
<li>Only identify the first step of what you want to start. At least, that&rsquo;s enough to get started and learn what to do later.</li>
<li>Agree on a <a href="https://mikadomethod.wordpress.com/">Mikado</a> discovery task to understand what needs to be done. Code is not the only thing that can be refactored with the Mikado method ! People have used it to transform <a href="http://nomad8.com/organisational-change-with-mikado/">organizations</a> !</li>
</ul>


<p>It&rsquo;s also a good habit to book the rooms for extra time after the official retro time. Nothing is as frustrating as being interrupted while investigating a promising improvement !</p>

<p>Finally, I think it&rsquo;s a good practice to review what happened of the improvements that were selected during last retro. It stresses the importance of doing what was scheduled in retrospective. It also gives a chance to investigate the reason why they were not done !</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mikado-Method-Ola-Ellnestam/dp/1617291218/ref=sr_1_1?tag=pbourgau-20&amp;amp;s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1494562230&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=mikado+method"><img src="../imgs/2017-05-09-most-scrum-teams-are-not-agile/mikado-method.jpg" alt="The cover of the &quot;Mikado Method&quot; book" /></a></p>

<h3>Put them in the sprint</h3>

<p>When actions are selected in the retro, you should add them to the coming sprint before it starts. Obviously, you&rsquo;ll add non business related items in your sprint backlog. Whatever you might have hear from agile zealots, do it ! Process improvements are fist class backlog citizens, just don&rsquo;t discuss them with your <a href="https://www.scrum.org/resources/blog/who-professional-scrum-product-owner">product owner</a>.</p>

<p>If you want a chance to deliver what you committed to in your sprint backlog, you&rsquo;ll need bandwidth for that ! They are many ways to do get that. Some teams use <a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/slack.html">slack time</a>, others reserve an &lsquo;improvement day&rsquo; every sprint. My personal favorite (and the one we&rsquo;ve been doing at work) is to estimate the improvements in story points and reserve a fraction (ex 20%) of your story points for improvements.</p>

<p>You can try to negotiate your improvement ratio with your product owner &hellip; or you might also just set it yourself ! The team is responsible for the quality of its work. Better be sorry than ineffective. If you stick to your ratio and only work on the most important improvements, it&rsquo;s usually pretty easy to justify working on them. Plus if you manage to go under the radar for a few sprints, the results of the improvements should speak by themselves.</p>

<h3>Do them as soon as the sprint starts</h3>

<p>One last thing. Start to work on your improvements as soon as the sprint starts.</p>

<p>Improvements are similar to investments : you invest in process, tools or code in exchange for more value creation downstream. Once you&rsquo;ve decided to invest in something, what&rsquo;s the point of waiting 1 week ? Plus if you wait for later in the sprint, you run the risk of having unfinished improvements at the next retro, which might interfere when prioritizing new ones.</p>

<h2>Continuously improving teams</h2>

<p>Being part of a continuously improving team is easier to live than to describe. It feels like the future is bright. Once a team has mastered continuous improvement, people can be optimistic that they&rsquo;ll manage to adapt to change later down the road :</p>

<ul>
<li>They could switch gears and go full speed on a particular re-architecture</li>
<li>They could change their working agreements to adapt to new constraints</li>
<li>They could re-focus their efforts to handle a maintenance pike</li>
</ul>


<p>At the end of the day, bottom-up continuous improvement makes everyone&rsquo;s lives easier. Developers experience more autonomy while improving their productivity, they can do good work (which also means spending less time bug-fixing). Product owners learn that they can trust the team to do their best. Sponsors get more value for their money.</p>

<blockquote><p>Agile teams bend so they don&rsquo;t break !</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to get your team to do code reviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-get-your-team-to-do-code-reviews/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-19T09:18:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/how-to-get-your-team-to-do-code-reviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As software developers, we very <del>always</del> often get to work in code bases that are not perfect. In this situation we have 3 choices : leave, grumble, or make some changes ! Team wide code reviews are a recognized way to increase the quality of the code.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, installing code reviews as part of the daily work habits of a team can be very challenging. When I joined my team 3 years ago, no one was doing any kind of code reviews. With a small push here and there, I managed to get the team to adhere to a strict 4 eyes principle (full story <a href="/from-zero-to-pair-programming-hero/">here</a>).</p>

<p>Here are a few strategies that I have either used or seen that should get your team mates to do code reviews.</p>

<h2>Overall principle</h2>

<p>Even if you are at the bottom of the org chart, you have far more influence than you would first think. My favorite way of bringing change is to demonstrate a valuable practice :</p>

<ul>
<li>First, you need to be trustworthy</li>
<li>Then, do the practice you want to introduce</li>
<li>Make sure it is seen as valuable</li>
<li>Be ready to forgo the credits of the introduction of the practice</li>
<li>Keep on until people start to copy what you are doing</li>
</ul>


<p>As <a href="http://quoteinvestigator.com/2010/12/21/doing-good-selfless/">someone famous</a> said</p>

<blockquote><p>A man may do an immense deal of good, if he does not care who gets the credit</p></blockquote>

<p>I won&rsquo;t go in the details about how to be trustworthy, which could be a post of its own. Basically, putting our customers interests first, speaking the truth and avoiding to appear dogmatic can get us a long way already. <a href="https://www.amazon.fr/dp/B0050JLC9Y/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1">The Clean Coder</a> is an excellent read on the subject.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.fr/dp/B0050JLC9Y/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><img src="../imgs/2017-04-19-how-to-get-your-team-to-do-code-reviews/clean-coder.jpg" alt="Front cover of the Clean Coder book" /></a></p>

<h2>Strategies</h2>

<h3>If you have retrospectives in place</h3>

<p>In this case, you already have a place and time dedicated to discussing changes to your working agreements. Expressing your concerns about code quality (or another problem related to code reviews) and suggesting code reviews as a way to fix that problem might get a quick team buy-in.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t manage to get a definitive buy-in, try to get the team to &lsquo;beta-test&rsquo; code reviews for a while. If the experiment demonstrates value, it will convert into a full fledged working agreement.</p>

<h3>If you practice collective code ownership</h3>

<p>Unfortunately, if you don&rsquo;t have retrospectives in place, or if you did not manage to get your team to discuss code reviews in retrospectives, yo&rsquo;ll need to find another way to introduce them.</p>

<p>If you have collective code ownership, it should be ok to comment on your team mates code (if not, jump directly to the next strategy). In this setting, just start to do some code reviews for others ! Make sure your reviews are helpful and &lsquo;nice&rsquo;.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll need to stick to doing code reviews long enough before people actually start to mimic you. Reserve some time in your daily agenda for code reviews. Your goal is to win over people, so it might be a good idea to start with a selected few at the beginning, preferably people who are more likely to jump in. If asynchronous (tool based) reviews don&rsquo;t get answered, be ready to fallback to face to face discussions : review on your own, then just ask the author for a few minutes so that you can discuss his change. When you feel someone is interested by your reviews, ask him to review your own code in return.</p>

<p>Remember to always try to get some feedback : ask people what they think of the exercise, keep note of the good points, and adapt to smooth out the rest.</p>

<p><img src="../imgs/2017-04-19-how-to-get-your-team-to-do-code-reviews/collective.jpg" alt="Illustration of a team working collectively" /><div class="image-credits">Photo from <a href="https://www.emotuit.com/blog">emotuit</a></div></p>

<p>Once you won over your first team mate, involve him in your grand plan to spread the practice, explaining how much you think this could make a difference. As more and more people get convinced, the practice will eventually tacitly become part of your working conventions.</p>

<p>Depending on your context, this might take more or less time. I said it was possible, I never said it would be easy ! Grit, patience and adaptation are key here.</p>

<h3>Otherwise</h3>

<p>This is the worst starting point, basically, you have nothing yet. The strategy is very similar to the one with collective code ownership, with a different first move.</p>

<p>Instead of providing code reviews to your team mates, start by walking over to them to ask for a face to face code review of your own commits. Use the same tactic as stated before : stick to the same people at first. Once the practice starts to stick within this group, bring in a basic tool to ease up the process.</p>

<p>At some point, you should be asked to review others code, that&rsquo;s a good sign ! If not, try again with other people.</p>

<p>Continue using the same strategy as with collective code ownership and you should eventually get there !</p>

<h3>When it does not seem to stick</h3>

<p>There could be many reason why the practice is not adopted. The key for you is to understand why and to adapt your strategy. The reason is often that the perceived value is not big enough, for example :</p>

<ul>
<li>the team is not aware of its problems that reviews would fix : try to make them more visible</li>
<li>reviews are seen as too expensive or painful : try better tools or taking more on yourself</li>
<li>the team has bigger problems to fix first : spend your energy on these first !</li>
<li>reviews just don&rsquo;t work in your context (ex: your job is to write one time, throw away code) : it&rsquo;s up to you to stay or leave !</li>
</ul>


<h2>Tools</h2>

<p>There are a ton of tools and best practices to run code reviews. It&rsquo;s important that you know them, so that you know where you are going.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t expect to use the best tools from the start though. At the beginning, your goal is to win over your team mates. In this context, only 2 things matter :</p>

<ul>
<li>It should have almost no adoption curve, so that others start using it</li>
<li>It should have almost no maintenance cost, as you don&rsquo;t want to spend your time doing that</li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s why at the beginning, low tech tools are so great. Spending a month setting up a top notch code review system before the first review won&rsquo;t work. If your VCS has code reviews built-in, by all means use it ! Otherwise, diff in mails and face to face conversations are a good starting point. You&rsquo;ll later hook something in your VCS to automatically send mails with commit diffs &hellip;</p>

<p>As people gradually get convinced of the value of code reviews, regularly meet and discuss a better setup. This is how you&rsquo;ll introduce state of the art tools and agree on refinements such as pre or post commit reviews.</p>

<h3>Best practices</h3>

<p>As a code review champion, it&rsquo;s very important that you provide great reviews to your team mates. You must become the local expert on the subject ! You don&rsquo;t want all your efforts to be ruined because one of your reviews has been perceived as aggressive.</p>

<p><a href="https://static.rainfocus.com/oracle/oow16/sess/1473264722807001CoS2/ppt/code-reviews-vs-pull-requests.pdf"><img src="../imgs/2017-04-19-how-to-get-your-team-to-do-code-reviews/atlassian.jpg" alt="A slide from Atlassian presentation about styles of code reviews" /></a></p>

<p>There is a ton of resources on the internet about how to perform good code reviews, here are a few :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/mariakhalusova">Maria Khalusova</a>&rsquo;s talk at Devoxx 2016 <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-tcy4z0hszg">How to stop wasting your time and start performing useful code reviews</a></li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@kannonboy/">Tim Pettersen</a> from <a href="https://www.atlassian.com">Atlassian</a> talked about <a href="https://static.rainfocus.com/oracle/oow16/sess/1473264722807001CoS2/ppt/code-reviews-vs-pull-requests.pdf">Code Reviews vs Pull Request</a> at JavaOne 2016</li>
<li><a href="http://marcotroisi.com/">Marco Troisi</a> wrote an extensive blog post about <a href="http://marcotroisi.com/how-run-code-reviews-in-your-workflow/">How to run code reviews in your dev team&rsquo;s workflow</a></li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@mrjoelkemp">Joel Kemp</a>&rsquo;s post <a href="https://medium.com/@mrjoelkemp/giving-better-code-reviews-16109e0fdd36">Giving better code reviews</a></li>
<li>Gareth Wilson&rsquo;s post <a href="https://blog.fogcreek.com/effective-code-reviews-9-tips-from-a-converted-skeptic/">Effective Code Reviews – 9 Tips from a Converted Skeptic</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>What&rsquo;s next ?</h2>

<p>Congratulations ! Your team will start to reap the benefits of code reviews. Keep on improving the practice !</p>

<p>To end the story, after a few months of code reviews, during a retrospective, my team (<a href="http://www.murex.com/">at work</a>) decided to take it one step further and started to do almost full time pair programming ;&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trello Templates to Boost Your Remote Retrospectives]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-11T20:31:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I already wrote how we started to use <a href="http://trello.com">Trello</a> to do our <a href="/trellospectives-remote-retrospectives-with-trello/">remote retrospectives</a>. A while ago, my team mate <a href="http://bilal.eltayara.net/blog/2015/09/20/agile-retrospectives-using-trello/">Bilal Tayara</a> started to collect our activities into <a href="https://trello.com/agileretrospectives">trello templates</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-11-trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives/retrospective_meetings.jpg" title="&lsquo;Stop Doing&rsquo;, &lsquo;Continue Doing&rsquo; &amp; &lsquo;Start doing&rsquo; panels of a retrospective activity" ></p>

<h2>New activities</h2>

<p>I just imported new activities we have been using in the past months :</p>

<ul>
<li>SMART Goals</li>
<li>5 Whys</li>
<li>Circle of Questions</li>
<li>Communication</li>
<li>Engagement</li>
<li>ESVP</li>
<li>Fishbone</li>
<li>Focus On/Focus Off</li>
<li>Force Field Analysis</li>
<li>Gifts</li>
<li>Glad Sad Mad</li>
<li>Health Radar</li>
<li>HHH</li>
<li>Hot Air Balloon</li>
<li>How are you feeling today ?</li>
<li>Improvements Brainstorming</li>
<li>Learning Matrix</li>
<li>Note To Self</li>
<li>Plus / Delta</li>
<li>Problem &ndash;> Action</li>
<li>Punctual Paulo</li>
<li>Retrospective Planning Game</li>
<li>Risk Brainstorming</li>
<li>ROTI</li>
<li>Sail Boat</li>
<li>Satisfaction Histogram</li>
<li>Take Away</li>
<li>Team</li>
<li>Team Radar</li>
<li>Warmup Question</li>
<li>What happened since last retro ?</li>
</ul>


<h2>How to use these templates</h2>

<p>Clone the template to your organization every time you want to use it. There are instructions in the template to explain how to use it. For more detailed instructions, have a look at the original :</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://pragprog.com/book/dlret/agile-retrospectives">Agile Retrospectives, Making Good Teams Great</a> by Esther Derby and Diana Larsen, Foreword by Ken Schwaber</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://pragprog.com/book/dlret/agile-retrospectives"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-11-trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives/AgileRetrospectives.jpg" title="The cover of Agile Retrospectives" ></a></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.infoq.com/minibooks/agile-retrospectives-value">Getting Value out of Agile Retrospectives, Second Edition</a> by Luis Gonçalves and Ben Linders</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.infoq.com/minibooks/agile-retrospectives-value"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-11-trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives/GettingAgileOutOfAgileRetrospectives.jpg" title="The cover of Getting Agile Out Of Agile Retrospectives" ></a></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://leanpub.com/funretrospectives">Fun Retrospectives</a> by Taina Caetano and Paulo Caroli</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://leanpub.com/funretrospectives"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-11-trello-templates-to-boost-your-remote-retrospectives/FunRetrospectives.jpg" title="The cover of Fun Retrospectives" ></a></p>

<p>One last thing : in order to improve this collection, we&rsquo;d like to have your feedback on existing activities, or your own new templates for other activities.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
