<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: kanban | Philippe Bourgau's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/blog/categories/kanban/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-24T04:39:57+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Philippe Bourgau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Books About Data Driven Lean Software Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/5-books-about-data-driven-lean-software-development/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-29T05:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/5-books-about-data-driven-lean-software-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In french, we say &ldquo;Le cordonnier est toujours le plus mal chaussé&rdquo; which I found an English equivalent in &ldquo;the shoemaker’s son always goes barefoot&rdquo;. I believe this is nowhere more true than in the software industry !</p>

<p>&ldquo;Software is eating the world&rdquo; they say. Software is now able to do things that only humans used to be. So why the hell are we driving our projects as if we were a horde of amateur hitch hikers ?</p>

<h2>What does it mean to be data driven ?</h2>

<p>Being data driven would allow us to answer questions such as :</p>

<ul>
<li>How much is the feature we delivered last week contributing to the bottom line ?</li>
<li>How much is the feature we are currently developing expected to contribute to the bottom line ?</li>
<li>What are the estimated cost <em>and value</em> of increasing our test coverage of 1% ?</li>
<li>What are the estimated interests and nominal amounts of our current technical debt ?</li>
<li>Which is the most valuable : improving our build system or building this new feature ?</li>
</ul>


<p>Most projects I&rsquo;ve worked in have absolutely no clue about the answers to these questions. The decision is left to experts, to the one with most influence, or simply to the developer, who can do how he thinks is best &hellip;</p>

<h2>The books</h2>

<p>Hopefully, some people are thinking differently, they believe it is possible to quantify all this, they even explain how !</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Running-Lean-Iterate-Works-OReilly/dp/1449305172/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1461906957&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=running+lean">Running Lean: Iterate from Plan A to a Plan That Works</a> by <a href="https://ashmaurya.com/">Ash Maurya</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Running-Lean-Iterate-Works-OReilly/dp/1449305172/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1461906957&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=running+lean"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-29-5-books-about-data-driven-lean-software-development/running_lean.jpg" title="The cover of the Running Lean book" ></a></p>

<p>Details a very practical guide about the lean startup process, which is a very good starting point to any kind of lean software development.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kanban-Successful-Evolutionary-Technology-Business/dp/0984521402/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1461906998&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=kanban+anderson">Kanban: Successful Evolutionary Change for Your Technology Business</a> by <a href="http://www.djaa.com/">David J. Anderson</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kanban-Successful-Evolutionary-Technology-Business/dp/0984521402/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1461906998&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=kanban+anderson"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-29-5-books-about-data-driven-lean-software-development/kanban.jpg" title="The cover of the Kanban book" ></a></p>

<p>This book explains with real world examples how to use Kanban board to control your work queues and improve your flow of work, a real basic for any lean product development.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Principles-Product-Development-Flow-Generation/dp/1935401009/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1461907905&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=principles+of+product+development+flow">The Principles of Product Development Flow: Second Generation Lean Product Development</a> by <a href="http://reinertsenassociates.com/">Donald G. Reinertsen</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Principles-Product-Development-Flow-Generation/dp/1935401009/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1461907905&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=principles+of+product+development+flow"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-29-5-books-about-data-driven-lean-software-development/flow.jpg" title="The cover of the Flow book" ></a></p>

<p>This book is rather theoretical, but it links all subjects together : lean startup, risk management, Kanban, and economics. I guess it&rsquo;s a must read on the subject.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Measure-Anything-Intangibles-Business/dp/1118539273/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1461908177&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=how+to+measure+anything">How to Measure Anything: Finding the Value of Intangibles in Business</a> by <a href="http://www.hubbardresearch.com/">Douglas W. Hubbard</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Measure-Anything-Intangibles-Business/dp/1118539273/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1461908177&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=how+to+measure+anything"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-29-5-books-about-data-driven-lean-software-development/how_to_measure_anything.jpg" title="The cover of How to measure anything" ></a></p>

<p>If the flow book gives a big picture view of what you want, this one explains how you can actually measure all the aspects of your product development in $ value.</p>

<h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Waltzing-Bears-Managing-Software-Projects/dp/0932633609/ref=sr_1_sc_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1461908398&amp;sr=8-1-spell&amp;keywords=walzting+with+bears">Waltzing With Bears: Managing Risk on Software Projects</a> by <a href="http://www.systemsguild.com/">Tom DeMarco and Timothy Lister</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Waltzing-Bears-Managing-Software-Projects/dp/0932633609/ref=sr_1_sc_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1461908398&amp;sr=8-1-spell&amp;keywords=walzting+with+bears"><img class="center" src="/imgs/2016-04-29-5-books-about-data-driven-lean-software-development/waltzing_with_bears.jpg" title="The cover of Waltzing with bears" ></a></p>

<p>Although this book is getting old, and is a bit outdated when compared to agile development practices, it provides real world examples of how scientific measurement can be applied to software product development.</p>

<h2>An opportunity</h2>

<p>Reading these books was a real eye opener for me. The software development world is plagued with cargo cult and supposed best practices. We follow advises, but most often without verifying if they actually work ! I believe that by applying the techniques in these books, we could create standard ways to measure the values of productivity, technical debt, quality, testing &hellip;</p>

<p>I see real opportunities to avoid a lot of useless argument between proponents of A and B, but also to communicate better with all stakeholders and finally, to reduce stress for all of us.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bye Bye Programmer's TODO List, Hello Personnal Kanban on Jira]]></title>
    <link href="http://philippe.bourgau.net/bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-17T05:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://philippe.bourgau.net/bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not long ago, I wrote that <a href="/real-programmers-have-todo-lists/">Real Programmers have TODO lists</a> &hellip; I was wrong, I now work without a TODO list ! So either I&rsquo;m not a real programmer anymore, or I&rsquo;m actually using TODO List v.2.0. Read on !</p>

<h2>Motivations</h2>

<p>My work has become quite varied lately. On top of programming and pairing, I am also doing quite some coaching within the team. For the whole Murex programmers community, I&rsquo;m organizing <a href="https://github.com/murex/murex-coding-dojo">Coding Dojos</a>, <a href="http://www.brownbaglunch.fr/">Brown Bag Lunches</a> and Technical Talk Video Sessions. Finaly, like all of us, I have to cope with my share of organization overhead.</p>

<p>Multitasking was starting to kill me. I was feeling exhausted at the end of the day, with the certainty that I was not getting much done &hellip;</p>

<h2>Personnal Kanban To The Rescue</h2>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban">Kanban</a> is a method to organize your work relying on <a href="http://www.personalkanban.com/pk/featured/why-limit-work-in-progress/#sthash.QFI0D8l5.dpbs">Work In Progress limits</a> : it minimizes multitasking and encourages prioritization.</p>

<p>As its name suggests it, <a href="http://personalkanban.com">Personal Kanban</a> is simply applying Kanban to your own tasks. It turns out that :</p>

<ul>
<li>My team tasks are already in <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira">JIRA</a></li>
<li>Some guys have already tried to <a href="https://jira.atlassian.com/browse/JRA-13472">use JIRA as a todo list</a></li>
<li>JIRA supports Kanban boards with WIP limits and all</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Kanban Board</h2>

<p>In our team, <a href="http://bilal.eltayara.net">TAYARA Bilal</a> had already experimented the approach and asked to JIRA admins to create us a custom project for our todo lists. I piggybacked on it and created my own kanban board. Here is what it looks like.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-08-17-bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/board.png" title="Screenshot of the full JIRA board" ></p>

<h3>Mixing Project Stories And Personnal Tasks</h3>

<p>JIRA allows creating a kanban board that spans many projects ! You can simply choose multiple projects when you setup the board for the first time, or you can edit your board filter like this :</p>

<p><code>sql
project in (POPIMDB, POPABTODO) ...
</code></p>

<p>This makes it possible to see <em>all</em> of my work at a glance on the same board.</p>

<h3>Work In Progress Limit</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-08-17-bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/wip.png" title="Zoom on the wip constraints of the JIRA column" ></p>

<p>JIRA allows WIP limits, warning me with a red background when I am multitasking or when I am getting late on my tasks</p>

<h3>Color Conventions</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-08-17-bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/color-cards.png" title="Different colors of JIRA cards" ></p>

<p>JIRA makes it possible to assign different colors to cards, for example</p>

<ul>
<li>Red for tasks that are due soon</li>
<li>orange for cards that are due some time</li>
<li>light brown for project stories</li>
<li>green for other programming tasks</li>
<li>blue for other tasks</li>
</ul>


<h3>Swimlanes</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-08-17-bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/swimlanes.png" title="Closup on a JIRA swimlane" ></p>

<p>JIRA has swimlanes, separating project from personal tasks</p>

<h3>Reports</h3>

<p>An extra bonus with JIRA Kanban board is that they have reports ! Here is my cumulative flow diagram for my first week of usage :</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/imgs/2015-08-17-bye-bye-programmers-todo-list-hello-personnal-kanban-on-jira/cumulative-flow.png" title="A screenshot of the JIRA cumulative flow diagram" ></p>

<h3>Configuration</h3>

<p>Here is the JQL query I used to configure it this way.</p>

<p>```sql
&mdash; board filter
project in (POPIMDB, POPABTODO) AND (Assignee = pbourgau OR Co-Assignees in (pbourgau) OR mentors in (pbourgau)) AND (status != CLOSED OR updated >= -1d) ORDER BY Rank ASC</p>

<p>&mdash; Swimlanes
priority = &ldquo;1-Very High&rdquo; &mdash; Expedite
project in (&ldquo;POP IMDB&rdquo;) and (labels not in (SLACK) OR labels is EMPTY) &mdash; IMDB Stories
&mdash; and a blank filter for Other Tasks</p>

<p>&mdash; Card Colours
duedate &lt;= 7d or priority = &ldquo;1-Very High&rdquo; &mdash; red
duedate is not EMPTY &mdash; orange
labels in (SLACK) &mdash; green
type = Task &mdash; blue
&mdash; and an empty filter for light brown
```</p>

<h2>The End Result</h2>

<p>By setting a WIP limit of 3 on the &ldquo;In Progress&rdquo; column, the following naturally happened :</p>

<ul>
<li>Once I have started a programming task, I now defer any other activity in the TODO column until I am finished. (HINT: If you get invited to meetings all the time, lock your agenda with &lsquo;Unbookable&rsquo; days when you start programming)</li>
<li>It actually pushed me into finishing the <a href="https://github.com/philou/concurrency-kata">concurrency-kata</a> training I had started long ago.</li>
</ul>


<p>I also set a high WIP limit (around 10) on the TODO column, this way, I get a kind of warning that next time I finish a programming task, I should take some time off to prune the column.</p>

<p>The overall result is that I do lot less multitasking. I get the feeling of doing steadier, more efficient work.</p>

<p>If you are suffering from multitasking and decide to give it a try, I&rsquo;d love to read about your experience !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
